<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd" >
<TEI.2 id="tp005">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Dutton LB1 and the Sources of Garci Sánchez de Badajoz<note n="1">Earlier versions of
            this paper were given at a meeting of the Seminar in Editing and Textual Studies at
            King's College London on 17 February 1976, and at a two-day conference on 'Spanish
            Cancioneros: Materials and Methods' held at the Institute of Romance Studies and Queen
            Mary and Westfield College, 27-28 June 1997.</note> (tp005)</title>
        <author>
          <name type="foreName">B W</name>
          <name type="surname">Ife</name>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Article by B W Ife</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>It is a commonplace of literary studies that problems of text and interpretation are
          really the same thing. Is Hamlet's 'too, too solid flesh' really 'sullied'? Is Cressida
          'the Trojans' trumpet' or 'the Trojan strumpet'? While the poetry of Garci Sánchez de
          Badajoz is hardly in Shakespeare's league, it nevertheless poses some interesting
          challenges both to the editor and the critic. In common with many poets of the late
          fifteenth and early sixteenth centuries, Garci Sánchez's poetry has not been transmitted
          in the form of neat compilations of 'collected works', but has to be assembled from
          numerous relatively scattered printed and manuscript <foreign>cancioneros</foreign>. <note
            n="2"><bibl>Patrick Gallagher, <title>The Life and Works of Garci Sánchez de
              Badajoz</title> (London: Tamesis Books), 1968</bibl>. See also <bibl>J. Castillo,
                <title>Cancionero de Garci Sánchez de Badajoz</title> (Madrid: Editora Nacional),
              1980</bibl>. A further poem attributed to Garci Sánchez was subsequently identified in
            Madrid, <bibl>Nacional MS 5602 by N.F. Marino, 'An early attribution to Garci Sánchez de
              Badajoz', <title>Anuario medieval</title> 2, 132-40</bibl>.</note> The nature of these
          sources creates complex problems for the production of a critical edition, and the purpose
          of this study is to re-examine one of the sources in particular, British Library Add. MS
          10431 (Dutton LB1), <note n="3"><bibl>Brian Dutton, <title>Catálogo-Indice de la poesía
                cancioneril del siglo XV</title>, 2 vols in 1 (Madison: Hispanic Seminary of
              Medieval Studies), 1982</bibl>; <bibl>Brian Dutton and Jineen Krogstad, <title>El
                cancionero del siglo XV</title>, 7 vols (Salamanca: Universidad de Salamanca),
            1990</bibl>. LB1 appears on pp 131-275 of vol 1.</note> in order to reassess its
          authority as a source for Garci Sánchez, and to use it to draw some wider methodological
          and interpretative conclusions.</p>

        <p>For a writer who was famed as a lunatic lover and spent at least part of his life as a
          court poet, Garci Sánchez's extant corpus of poems is fairly small. Altogether, some 66
          poems have survived in 30 sources up to 1520 (Table 1). The headline points are fairly
          obvious: the sources which have the greatest number of poems by Garci Sánchez are the two
          printed collections 11CG and 14CG (the first and second editions of the
            <foreign>Cancionero general</foreign>, compiled by Hernando del Castillo and printed in
          Valencia in 1511 and 1514), and the British Library MS now known as Dutton LB1. <note
            n="4">MN14 is a 19th-century MS in the Biblioteca Nacional Madrid (MS 3777) whose
            importance for Garci Sánchez studies has yet to be clearly established.</note>
          Understanding the relationship between these three early sources is therefore central to
          determining their relative authority as sources for Garci Sánchez and for many other poets
          represented in them.</p>

        <p>[Table 1: requires two pages]</p>

        <p>British Library Add. MS 10431, formerly known as the British Museum cancionero, is an
          important collection of some 470 pieces by 112 named poets from the reigns of John II,
          Henry IV and the Catholic Monarchs. <note n="5">Dutton's numbering is from 1-470, but
            numbers 83 and 318 are not used, while three poems are numbered 81b, 319b and
          380b.</note> It is a quarto volume currently consisting of 120 folios written in a single
          hand, mostly in double columns. A second hand has added a small number of comments and
          annotations. The MS may once have been longer, since the rubric of fol 1r alludes to works
          by 'el famoso poeta' Pedro de Herriega, which do not appear in the volume. <note n="6"
            >Since we have no record of such a poet, and since the attribution has been added in a
            later hand, I am inclined to suspect festivity on the part of a previous owner of the
            MS.</note> The date of the MS is uncertain. Hugo Rennert estimated a date between the
          1470s and 1500, <note n="7">H.A. Rennert, 'Der spanische Cancionero des Brit. Museums
            (Mss. Add. 10431)', <title>Romanische Forschungen</title> 10 (1895), 1-176. Rennert only
            printed the poems which were unique to this MS.</note> Carolina Michaëlis de Vasconcelos
          preferred 1500-1520, <note n="8">In a review of Rennert's edition in
                <bibl><title>Literaturblatt für germanische und romanische Philologie</title>
              XVIII-4 (1897), 127- 43</bibl>, she pointed out that, from internal evidence, the MS
            cannot have been compiled in its present form before 1498.</note> Dutton estimates
          'hacia 1500' (I,131), J. González Cuenca thought that it predated 11CG, <note n="9"
              ><bibl>'Cancioneros manuscritos del Pre-renacimiento', <title>Revista de
              literatura</title> (1978), 177-215</bibl>.</note> while Patrick Gallagher placed it
          between 11CG and 14CG (3- 5).</p>

        <p>We have no record of ownership until the MS was sold by Sotheby's on 17 February 1836
          from the library of Richard Heber to the British Museum for the sum of one shilling. Two
          pieces of evidence led R.O. Jones to conclude that the collection could have been the
          personal anthology of Juan del Encina: a marked similarity between certain aspects of the
          orthography of the MS and that of the 1496 edition of Encina's
          <foreign>Cancionero</foreign>, above all the use of intervocalic <emph>v</emph> rather
          than <emph>u</emph>; and the presence at the end of the MS of a group of poems attributed
          to the 'actor deste libro' among which there are two versions of poems from Encina's
          printed collection together with at least one other which is very reminiscent of Encina.
          Jones argued that the 'actor' ('compiler'?) was Encina himself. <note n="10"
              ><bibl>R.O.Jones, 'Encina y el Cancionero del British Museum',
              <title>Hispanófila</title> 11 (1961), 1-21</bibl>.</note>
        </p>

        <p>Carlos Alvar has subsequently produced a helpful survey of the relationships between LB1
          and several other MS and printed collections, and has been unable to escape the conclusion
          that LB1, 11CG and 14CG are closely related, both textually and chronologically: LB1 and
          11CG have 202 poems in common; 17 of those dropped from 11CG are in common with LB1; and
          19 of those added to 14CG are in common with LB1. 'LB1 presenta composiciones que se
          encuentran sólo en 11CG, y que no volvieron a ser publicadas en las ediciones posteriores,
          y también presenta otras piezas que se incluyeron por primera vez en 14CG: parece que es
          lógico pensar que LB1 es posterior a ambos Cancioneros impresos.' <note n="11"
              ><bibl>Carlos Alvar, 'LB1 y otros cancioneros castellanos' in Madeleine Tyssens (ed.),
                <title>Lyrique romane médiévale: la tradition des chansonniers. Actes du Colloque de
                Liège, 1989</title>. Bibliothèque de la Faculté de Philosophie et Lettres de
              l'Université de Liège, fascicule CCLVIII, (Paris: Droz), 1991, 469-97</bibl>. The
            quotation is on page 495. The relationship between LB1 and CG is even closer than is
            apparent in Alvar's summary. 15 of the poems added to 14CG and common to LB1 were by one
            author, Garci Sánchez de Badajoz. In addition, at least four poems were lengthened in
            14CG and each of these exists in LB1 in its longer version. There is also a striking
            similarity between LB1 and CG in terms of the poets omitted from both collections,
            especially those poets whose work was extensively published in the 1490s and might
            reasonably be expected to have been known to both Castillo and to the compiler of LB1:
            Mendoza, Montesinos and Encina. See <bibl>Jane Whetnall, 'El <emph>Cancionero
              general</emph> de 1511: textos únicos y textos omitidos' in Juan Paredes (ed.),
                <title>Medioevo y literatura. Actas del V Congreso de la Asociación Hispánica de
                Literatura Medieval. Granada 1993</title>. 4 vols. Granada, 1995. IV, 505-15</bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>

        <p>While it is impossible to disagree with this conclusion as far as it goes, there is a
          case for questioning the assumption (which Carlos Alvar does not make, but which might
          easily be drawn from his conclusion) that chronology and authority are necessarily
          causally related. Put simply: is the authority of LB1 any weaker because it appears to
          postdate 1514? Let us turn some of the earlier figures around: of the 1033 poems in 11CG,
          831 (80.4%) are <emph>not</emph> in LB1; if the compiler of LB1 used 11CG, how is it that
          19 poems are included which appeared for the first time in 1514? And if he used 14CG, how
          is it that he includes 17 poems which were dropped after the first edition? Furthermore,
          how is it that of 191 poems in common with 11CG, and 189 in common with 14CG, there is
          only one common sequence of four poems, one of three poems, and six pairs? And is it
          possible to account for the presence of unique poems in the midst of common groups without
          assuming a much more complex relationship than that which is implied by Carlos Alvar's
          analysis?</p>

        <p>These questions are important because the relationship between
          <foreign>cancionero</foreign> sources on the one hand and editions of the work of
          particular poets on the other is fundamentally an assymetrical one, and the editorial
          practices involved are very different in each case. Almost always,
          <foreign>cancionero</foreign> sources are compilations or anthologies, whether of one or
          several writers. They are a record of an individual's or group's interests, tastes and
          collecting habits, compiled at a particular place and time. <note n="12"><bibl>V. Beltrán
              Pepió, 'Tipología y génesis de los cancioneros', <title>Cultura neolatina</title> 55,
              233-65</bibl>.</note> By their very nature, then, the <foreign>cancionero</foreign>
          anthologies impose uniformity on variety. The process of collection and selection is
          normative in cultural and artistic terms, while the material processes of preparing the
          anthology for presentation, private enjoyment or publication result in a 'fair copy' which
          appears to be consistent in look and feel. If we were able to look beneath the visual and
          editorial uniformity at the surface, we would almost always find a ragbag of sources drawn
          from different places at different times, displaying conflicting orthgraphical and
          typographical conventions, and most important, sources of widely divergent textual
          authority.</p>

        <p>None of this is very different from the normal process of preparing any work for
          publication; behind the smoothly printed surface lies an agony of recensions, drafts,
          re-drafts, last-minute corrections and second thoughts at final proof stage. What makes
          this observation important in the case of <foreign>cancionero</foreign> sources is the
          warning it gives us that no statement about the authority of a particular text in a
            <foreign>cancionero</foreign> anthology can safely be applied to any other in that
          collection. The texts of Palgrave's <title>Golden Treasury</title>, for example, are just
          as likely to derive from an autograph presented to the compiler by the poet himself as
          from a unreliable printed source which perpetuates mis-readings from the first edition.
          The typography of the finished collection, and Palgrave's own editorial conventions as
          well as those of the publisher, would obscure those discrepancies from view.</p>

        <p>The implications of this for editorial practice may be summarised in Figures 1 and 2.
          Figure 1 is a simple representation of what normally happens when one edits a text. There
          are one or more extant witnesses whose relationship has to be established before a series
          of procedures can be applied to the texts of the witnesses to attempt to establish the
          lost archetype. What we do when evaluating <foreign>cancionero</foreign> sources is almost
          exactly the reverse (Figure 2). We usually have one witness, which we know, suspect or
          have reason to believe has been compiled from several sources, all of which are lost. In
          order fully to evaluate the authority of the witness, we have to try to reconstruct all of
          the missing sources, or at least their relationship to each other and to the witness we
          have. A less conventional form of stemma is required to express these relationships, and
          an example is given in Figure 3.</p>

        <p>[Figures 1, 2 and 3: require 1 page between them]</p>

        <p>How can we get behind the blank wall of uniformity presented by the
          <foreign>cancionero</foreign> text? A great deal of evidence about the process of
          compilation can be gleaned from a close examination of the physical characteristics of the
          MS. LB1 now consists of 120 leaves, written throughout in a single legible but
          non-professional hand, and in a single ink. The MS originally consisted of 124 folios, as
          is indicated by the original foliation, of which numbers 13 to 16 inclusive have been
          removed. They almost certainly contained the <title>Liciones de Job</title> of Garci
          Sánchez de Badajoz ('Pues amor quiere que muera', Dutton 1769), since the last poem on the
          verso of folio 12 is the beginning of a dedication of the <title>Liciones</title> to a
          friend. The poem was presumably removed in deference to a change of spiritual climate in
          the 1520s. This poem is also largely missing from a MS now preserved in the University of
          Salamanca (Dutton SA10b-95), from which four folios have also been removed, except that in
          this case the censor omitted to remove the first 17 lines. The opening rubric of LB1
          ('Aqui comiençan las obras de garci sanches de vadajos con otras obras de algunos
          syngulares poetas') and the concluding 'finnis deo gratias' suggest that, apart from the
          four missing leaves, the MS is substantially complete.</p>

        <p>The paper on which LB1 is written is unfortunately unwatermarked, but an irregularity in
          the spacing of the chain lines makes it clear that it was all made from the same pair of
          moulds and that presumably it was bought as a batch for this particular purpose. There is
          also evidence to suggest that the paper was made into a book before the MS was written.
          The original format is difficult to establish, since when the British Museum acquired the
          MS it was rebound and the leaves supplied with new hinges and quired in 15 lots of eight.
          It is unlikely that it will ever be possible to establish the original format with
          certainty, which is a pity, since quiring in 4s would suggest a ready-made book, whereas
          quiring in 2s need not. But it is noticeable that the final four leaves are significantly
          less closely written than the rest of the book and point to the copyist's possibly having
          some difficulty in filling his prescribed length, and might also account for the addition
          of the poems attributed to the mysterious 'actor'. Physical evidence, then, points to, but
          does not prove, that the MS was written 'at a sitting', into a loose or possibly bound
          batch of paper whose length had probably been estimated to fit the job in hand, and that
          it was written with the object of drawing together a disparate collection of material
          between two covers. The MS does not suggest a collection in the process of being formed or
          added to gradually over a long period of time.</p>

        <p>More physical evidence of a slightly different sort is given by what we can deduce from
          the copyist's working habits. The MS is written for the most part in double columns: the
          only exceptions are some poems in <foreign>arte mayor</foreign> where the format will only
          allow single columns, and a couple of pages written in three columns where the verse is
          basically hexasyllabic. There are two other exceptions which will be mentioned later. For
          the most part, the copyist seems anxious to fill his page as tightly as possible, and
          throughout the MS one has the impression of never a wasted space. But from time to time
          the copyist has punctuated his progress through the book by leaving small areas of blank
          space, usually at the end of a page, but sometimes in the middle, so as to divide, in
          effect, the collection into 34 sections. Sometimes the division is reinforced by a change
          in the rubric; or by writing the rubric across both columns; or by using the formula 'de
            <emph>x</emph> cancion' where the 'de <emph>x</emph>' means that all the following poems
          until the first attribution are by <emph>x</emph>; by the use of some formula such as
          'comiençan las obras de <emph>x</emph>'; or by the use of what passes for a 'florid'
          capital (eg. fol 104r). The 34 sections of the MS are summarised in Table 2.</p>

        <p>[Table 2: requires 1 page]</p>

        <p>Two alternatives are suggested by this unconsious ordering of the MS. Does it represent
          an attempt to classify the material, and if so what system of classification was used? Or
          do the divisions represent the points at which the copyist changed his exemplar? In the
          first alternative - the compiler or the copyist if they were not the same person - might
          have taken his shuffled collection of odds and ends and dealt them into piles
          corresponding roughly to a division by authorship. This is quite possible, since changes
          of section never come in the middle of a group attributed to one author, though some
          authors, for example Pinar and his sister Florencia, are common to more than one section.
          It is likely that the longest and most substantial sections were put together in this way,
          since within the section one can detect changes in the type of source, although these
          could well have been present in the immediately preceding exemplar.</p>

        <p>On the other hand, some divisions correspond more obviously to particular sources,
          especially where a number of poets are grouped around a particular theme or subject or are
          related geographically or by period. Besides, the copyist sometimes indicates a change of
          author by a florid capital within a section [90v-91r], and some of the sections consist of
          a main author plus a fill-up, which would suggest that the source might have been a MS or
          printed <foreign>pliego</foreign> with the characteristic make-weight to fill out the
          extra space left by a longer work. In another section the familiar tone of the
          attributions, the preponderance of first names in the rubrics, suggest a group of domestic
          pieces originating in one place at one time and recorded by one of their number, or a
          secretary who knew them well and expected his readers to share that familiarity. Some
          sections are little more than scraps, and this impression becomes stronger in the final
          groups where the copyist seems hard pressed to fill the remaining pages [119v-120r] and
          where the attribution of all the pieces to the 'actor' is not entirely clear.</p>

        <p>Although the realisation that the MS is organised in some not very obvious way represents
          a considerable step forward in our study of the collection, it is at the next stage that
          the major unknown quantities enter the argument. If some at least of the divisions do
          represent changes of source, it should be possible to be more precise about the nature and
          status of these sources, provided we can be reasonably certain that the copyist has given
          us an accurate record of what he saw. To that extent, then, are any differences
          discernible from section to section an accurate reflection of the state of the sources? To
          answer this question would involve demonstrating that the copyist was or was not an
          accurate worker, a task which is strictly speaking not possible unless one has the
          original from which he worked. But it should be possible to gain some indications without
          straying too far in the direction of guesswork.</p>

        <p>We need to know as much as possible about the scribe's orthographical preferences, the
          relative strengths of his preferences for some forms rather than others, his general
          attitude towards his exemplar, his willingness to leave difficulties or irregularities
          unsolved or alternatively his readiness to intervene with his own suggestions and
          solutions: in short, some guide to the literalness of his mind. The first source of such
          information is where a text appears twice in the MS and where it can only have been copied
          from the same exemplar. For all practical purposes this means places where the copyist has
          corrected himself, such as Figure 4, where three lines of the poem 'O mi dios y giador
            [<emph>sic</emph>]' (Dutton 0706) were copied at the wrong point in the poem, have been
          crossed through and repeated at the correct position, 11 lines later. The differences in
          orthography between the two appearances of these three lines are trivial
          (que/q<emph>ue</emph>; alunbra/alu<emph>n</emph>bra; y/e; <emph>vir</emph>go/virgo) while
          the similarities are telling (the long final s in 'nos'; the spelling of 'gia'; the
          contraction of 'lacrimar<emph>um</emph>'). Furthermore, the rhyme scheme of the poem
          indicates that in each instance there is a line missing.</p>

        <p>[Figure 4: requires half page]</p>

        <p>Unfortunately, such relatively long examples are very rare. More common is the opposite
          case where a poem is repeated but we can be fairly sure that two different exemplars are
          involved. Figure 5 shows two versions of the poem 'La vida seria perdella' (Núñez; Dutton
          0843) which appear on fols 43v and 44r. The orthography is virtually identical until the
          last line, where the variant reading almost certainly indicates a different source. Note
          the contracted final e on 'muerte', which is a strong preference of this copyist. There
          are seven such repeated pairs in LB1 and they can be quite helpful in gaining an insight
          into the copyist's habits.</p>

        <p>[Figure 5: requires half page]</p>

        <p>A further guide is provided by cases where a contrast in spellings, especially names,
          indicates a respect for both readings. Figure 6 illustrates a section of the text and
          commentary of Garci Sánchez's poem 'El dia infelix noturno' (Dutton 0731). Note how the
          lemma from the text preserves the spelling 'tis', while the commentary gives the more
          correct form 'Stix', and Figure 7 shows several examples of contrasting pairs of spellings
          from the same poem: 'menalanpo/melampo'; 'pamphago/panphago'; 'dorçeo/doçeo'. Note too the
          clue given by the cancelled 'fuero<emph>n</emph>' just before the poetic text resumes.
          These are clear cases where spellings seem deliberately contrasted rather than being the
          result of variation or carelessness: if the copyist knows that 'tis' should be spelled
          'Stix', then he could have changed it in the text of the lemma. All the lemmata in this
          commentary show the same kind of literal attitude to the text.</p>

        <p>[Figure 6: requires half page]</p>

        <p>A further source of information about the nature of the sources is provided by those
          occasions where the copyist abandons his normal working pattern, such as Figure 8
          ('Caminando por mis males'; Dutton 0693), where the double-column format is abandoned in
          favour of the common convention of writing the <foreign>romance</foreign> across the page.
          The <foreign>mise en page</foreign> makes it clear that he prepared for this change of
          format by making sure that the preceding poem ('No pido triste amador') finished in the
          top half of the page, so that he could set off the <foreign>cantar</foreign> which is
          included in the <foreign>romance</foreign> by reverting to double-column layout at the
          bottom of the page. On the verso of this leaf he has the rubric 'torna a romance' and
          resumes writing across the full width of the page. Only four poems are written in this
          way, all are <foreign>romances</foreign> and all are in the sections dedicated to Garci
          Sánchez de Badajoz, and they give a strong indication that the copyist was trying to
          preserve the format of his exemplar.</p>

        <p>[Figure 8: requires 1 page]</p>

        <p>I have already suggested that the abandonment of preferred forms, especially strongly
          preferred forms, and the choice between forms in free variation might also provide
          evidence of the original source. This approach is suggested by the implications of textual
          critics working in the field of the printed book, such as D.F. McKenzie's work on the
          composition of <title>The Merchant of Venice</title>. <note n="13"><bibl><title>Studies in
                Bibliography</title> 12 (1959), 75-90</bibl>. Harold Jenkins's magisterial analysis
            of the Q1, Q2 and Folio texts of <bibl><title>Hamlet</title> (London: Methuen), 1982,
              pp. 18-74</bibl> was equally helpful in this regard.</note> McKenzie demonstrates that
          when Jaggard's compositor B abandons his preferred spelling he rarely does so when his
          copy coincides with his preference, and when that preference is very strong he never sets
          the alternative unless it is in the copy. Applied over a wide range of examples, this
          study supports our intuition that when a compositor has no preference he will tend to
          follow the copy, and this observation might be expected to apply even more strongly to a
          scribe than a compositor, since the scribe has fewer restrictions caused by justification
          and the constraints of his fount, and is less likely than the compositor to alter spelling
          to assist justification.</p>

        <p>Now although it is interesting to know the scribe's preferences, (and in the case of LB1
          we can say with some certainty that they are: hard gi- and ge-; final <emph>-e</emph>;
          final <emph>-es</emph>; and final long s, in descending order of strength) it is unlikely
          that these alone will tell us much about the state of the exemplar, which is really what
          we are interested in. But one feature which can tell us a good deal is the type and degree
          of contraction present in a text, since there are considerable differences in the use of
          contraction and ligatures by scribes and compositors. For the scribe, the primary function
          of the contraction is ease and speed of writing, though it could be and often was used to
          assist in fitting a text into a given space. For the compositor, the function of
          contraction is almost solely that of justifying a line of type to the measure, and the
          range of its use is constrained by the characteristics of the fount: he can only set the
          ligatures which he has in his type cases. Inevitably, then, a compositor's contractions
          can easily be distinguished from those of a scribe, which tend to show a greater variety
          and density, and where we find significant deviations from the copyist's norm in respect
          of contractions, it is reasonable to look for a different kind of exemplar. Figure 9
          contrasts two columns of LB1. The left-hand column (fol 1va) has 42 contractions, the
          second (fol 10ra) has 22. Note also the different treatment of final -es/<emph>-es</emph>.
          The right-hand column is part of a series of four poems which share the same
          characteristics (see Table 3, below); the left-hand column is nearer the norm for this
          copyist.</p>

        <p>[Figure 9: requires 1 page]</p>

        <p>The final test of a copyist's attitude to his exemplar is the surviving state of the
          texts themselves. At this point in the argument it is convenient to concentrate on the
          section of the MS devoted to the poems of Garci Sánchez de Badajoz, in order to bring
          together the two threads of the argument: that it is dangerous to generalise about the
          reliability of texts within an anthology; and that a close scrutiny of the physical
          features of the collection, especially the accidentals, can give some idea of the type of
          exemplar used and the extent to which the copyist accurately reproduced what he saw before
          him. This section of LB1 is also a good test because it raises in microcosm all of the
          larger questions mentioned earlier about the relationship of LB1 to the first and second
          editions of the <title>Cancionero general</title>.</p>

        <p>[Table 3: requires 1 page]</p>

        <p>Table 3 shows the order of poems by Garci Sánchez in LB1, 11CG and 14CG. It should be
          noted that six poems added in 14CG do not appear in LB1 (seven, if the <title>Liciones de
            Job</title>, Dutton 1769, are included) and that the only significant consecutive
          grouping common to LB1 and 14CG is 17, (17a=9), 18, 19. These four poems are the same
          group of four which showed a markedly lower density of contraction than the norm for LB1
          (Figure 9), and which might therefore be supposed to have derived from a printed source.
            <note n="14">There are also three pairs of poems common to LB1 and 14CG. Note that poems
            10 and 35 in LB1 (498 and 515 in 14CG) are each a single poem, with a slightly different
            treatment of self-quotation in each case. To that extent, they help to differentiate LB1
            and 14CG even further. </note> 17a is an extra stanza which has been added to 17 in the
          MS, but which is in fact the last stanza of the poem which occurs between 17 and 18 in
          14CG and which appears in full as no 9 in LB1. Since this rogue stanza is headed 'fin' it
          seems likely that a massive case of haplography has elided the two poems into one. As the
          evidence of contraction suggests a printed exemplar, it is probable that these four poems
          circulated in a printed <foreign>pliego</foreign> as a group and that they found their way
          independently into LB1 and 14CG. It is unlikely that they were taken from 14CG since poem
          no 17 and the rogue stanza do not appear on the same page of the <title>Cancionero
          general</title> until the 1517 edition, and in any case there is a major variant in the
          penultimate line.</p>

        <p>Although the occurrence, or co-occurrence, of poetic texts in various collections can be
          used to establish textual and chronological relationships, there is a great deal more to
          be learned from detailed study of the variants between these texts. One of the reasons
          which led Patrick Gallagher to prefer CG readings to LB1 was the fact that, although
          neither tradition, in his view, had more authority, the LB1 tradition was 'badly damaged
          in this sole surviving copy by inaccurate and fragmentary transcription' (48). Carlos
          Alvar's subsequent conclusion that LB1 postdates 1514 could be said to cast further doubt
          on the reliability of the LB1 texts: if LB1 derives in some way from CG, why are so many
          of the texts so different from each other? But the implicaton that LB1 is a poor copy of
          CG is open to challenge when we come to consider differentially the degrees of variation
          between LB1 and CG from poem to poem. This raises an interesting question about rates of
          decay in the transmission of texts, and could provide the editor with another tool for
          investigating and elucidating the nature of a <foreign>cancionero</foreign> anthology.</p>

        <p>It is commonly accepted that every act of copying introduces changes, some voluntary and
          some accidental. We might call this 'the law of textual entropy'. But textual entropy is
          not constant; not all acts of copying will introduce the same amount of change, so that
          there is no such thing as a textual 'half life', a constant rate at which texts will decay
          through successive copying. But it might be reasonable to expect a single copyist who
          copies several texts under similar circumstances to cause a much more constant rate of
          decay, even allowing for variations in mood, tiredness, hunger and other working
          conditions. If MS A shows a 10% divergence from its supposed exemplar B, whereas another
          MS C shows a 30% divergence from the same supposed exemplar B, we might question whether C
          did indeed derive from B, or at least whether it derived via the same route.</p>

        <p>In the case of LB1 and CG, we find a range of divergence from poem to poem of between 10%
          and 50%, <note n="15">In this case 'divergence' is measured in terms of the number of
            lines which contain a variant other than an orthographic variant. Another way of
            measuring divergence might be to compare the number of bytes which differ between texts.
            Neither is ideal, because variants, whether orthographic or substantive, can differ
            greatly in their significance. However, the method chosen may at least serve as an
            approximate indicator of the order of magnitude of difference which exists between two
            texts.</note> and it might be reasonable to ask whether this wide range of divergence
          called into question whether all the MS texts derived from printed exemplars, or indeed
          whether any of them did: 10% of lines with variants is in any case a high figure, as the
          rate of variation between 11CG and 14CG, for example, which we know to be directly
          related, is less than 1%. The importance of this line of argument can be seen in Figure
          10, where the 14CG text is longer than that of 11CG and where the rate of divergence
          between LB1 and 14CG is different in different parts of the poem:</p>

        <table>
          <row>
            <cell>ll. 1-34, 49-94</cell>
            <cell>43/79 lines different (54%)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>ll. 35-48</cell>
            <cell>8/14 lines different (57%)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>ll. 95-129</cell>
            <cell>10/35 lines different (28.5%)</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>[Figure 10: requires 2-3 pages]</p>

        <p>It would be reasonable to conclude from this evidence that it is very unlikely that
          whoever copied this poem into LB1 ever saw Castillo's text, since the only possible
          hypothesis - that he already had the short version and added the extra lines from
          Castillo, just as Castillo had simply added extra lines to the 11CG version - is belied by
          the markedly different rate of divergence between the two sections common to LB1 and 14CG.
          Since there are no variants between 11CG and 14CG in the sections they have in common, we
          might assume that, rather than reprint the new, longer text in its entirety, Castillo
          simply added the new lines at the appropriate points in the 1511 text. This could affect
          any conclusions which might be drawn from the above analysis of differential rates of
          variation.</p>

        <p>We should be wary, in any case, of imposing modern ideas and expectations about textual
          transmission onto those of another period, especially when we have no clear idea of what
          Castillo meant by 'ordenado y corregido por la mejor manera y diligencia que pude', and
          when we note that he himself was aware of the lack of authority for some of his texts: 'no
          fue en mi mano aver todas las obras que aqui van de los verdaderos originales o de cierta
          relacion de los auctores que las hizieron'. Yet Castillo's finished product is (like
          Palgrave's?) visually very impressive and, by implication, authoritative. His texts seem
          to be the longest, the tidiest and metrically the most consistent, but are they
          hyper-correct by contrast with other sources?</p>

        <p>Furthermore, it will often not be possible to locate the 'verdaderos originales' for the
          simple reason that the author never intended to produce a finished product, but rather an
          open-ended scheme, which like the music of the period and that of today, would take as
          many forms as it had performances. <note n="16"><bibl>Simon Gaunt, 'Orality and writing:
              the text of the troubadour poem' in Simon Gaunt and Sarah Kay (eds.), <title>The
                Troubadours. An Introduction</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press), 1999,
              228-45</bibl>.</note> Such a scheme is that of Garci Sánchez's <title>Infierno de
            amores</title> (Dutton 0662), which consists of a sequence of stanzas each telling of
          the sufferings of the most famous poets of the period, and ending with an injunction to
          any gentleman who feels excluded to write himself a stanza. As this poem exists in at
          least five sources it is possible to get an idea of the way in which it grew in response
          to Garci Sánchez's invitation. In Table 4, 13*BI is a rare early <foreign>pliego
          suelto</foreign> preserved in the Bibliothque Nationale and assigned by Norton to
          Cromberger, Seville, 1511-1515, and SA10b is a late 15th-century anthology now in the
          University of Salamanca. Note that SA10b is complete in that, although it is the shortest,
          it has the stanza with the invitation; that the series A-H is unlikely to be a response to
          the publication of the invitation in 11CG since parts of it appear in two other sources;
          that the group 10,14,24,29 is absent from all versions except Castillo's; and the pairing
          28+30 is common to all versions except CG, since Castillo makes the Don Sancho of stanza
          30 the brother of Antonio de Velasco in stanza 29, whereas all the others make him the
          brother of Diego de Castilla. The common sequences between LB1 and 13*BI are very
          impressive and strongly indicate without recourse to variants that LB1 does not in this
          case derive from CG.</p>

        <p>[Table 4: requires 1 page]</p>

        <p>Figure 11 shows just how cavalier the anthologist of 1500 could be towards his texts. The
          Figures contrasts four stanzas from Garci Sánchez's poem 'A la ora en que mi fe' (Dutton
          0687) as recorded in LB1 and 11CG. Very few stanzas from the LB1 text of this poem retain
          anything like the correct prosodic structure of the poem, and yet there are very few
          places where the text does not make sense. The reason seems to be that this is an example
          of memorial transmission, since what has been lost is in almost all cases the structure of
          the stanza, particularly the second half of each. Most stanzas preserve something like the
          tight formal arrangement of the first six lines - abc, abc - but the second part with its
          two <foreign>quebrados</foreign> has been elided into a straight prose account of the
          sense. This is almost certainly because of the rarity of the form (Le Gentil notes only
          six examples) which seems to have been enough to defeat someone who had not seen it
          written down. It is most unlikely that the text could have been reduced to this condition
          had it been copied from a written, still less printed, source. Yet the loss of the
          prosodic structure does not in itself render the text useless, since there is nothing to
          prevent the compiler having captured the sense more accurately than Castillo's neater
          version; that kind of evaluation can only be made by looking at the variants themselves,
          and there are a great many to be taken into account. <note n="17">In line 88, for example,
            LB1 appears to have the better reading.</note>
        </p>

        <p>[Figure 11: requires 1 page]</p>

        <p>It would be reasonable to draw a number of general and particular conclusions from this
          discussion:</p>


        <list type="unordered">

          <item><foreign>cancionero</foreign> texts are not homogeneous and any statement about the
            textual authority of one poem will not necessarily apply to the next</item>

          <item>it is vital to look below the surface uniformity of the anthology to discern, as far
            as is possible, the variety of exemplars which underlay the compilation of the
            collection</item>

          <item>although LB1 is more closely related to 11CG and 14CG than to any other source, the
            differences are just as striking as the similarities</item>

          <item>although LB1 may be more closely related to 14CG than to 11CG, there is no clear
            evidence that LB1 postdates either 1511 or 1514</item>

          <item>LB1 was compiled from a wide range of sources, some oral, some MS, and some printed</item>

          <item>some of those sources, probably the majority, predate CG and were transmitted
            independently of CG</item>

          <item>no generalisations can be made about the relative authority of the CG and LB1
            traditions in the case of Garci Sánchez de Badajoz, and probably other poets of the
            period, and decisions about the relative authority of textual sources have to be made on
            a poem-by-poem basis</item>

          <item>the evidence of the various text traditions of Garci Sánchez de Badajoz suggests
            that there is a large degree of textual variation between them</item>

          <item>the degree of textual variation found in Garci Sánchez's sources could be evidence
            of: extensive circulation of much larger numbers of MSS than those which have survived;
            oral and/or sung transmission; relatively high degrees of <foreign>mouvance</foreign>
            (textual instability) and/or <foreign>remaniement</foreign> (reworking) <note n="18"
                ><bibl>Gaunt, 'Orality and writing', 229</bibl>.</note>
          </item>

          <item>in evaluating printed sources (such as CG) as against MS sources (such as LB1), care
            must be taken to avoid anachronistic assessments of relative accuracy and authority,
            since the pressure towards normalisation inherent in printed media may have led to
            hyper-correction during the preparation of texts for the press.</item>
        </list>


        <p>Finally, Table 5 summarises my own best estimates of the likely sources of the Garci
          Sánchez poems in LB1.</p>

        <p>[Table 5: requires 1 page]</p>

      </div>



    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
