<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd" >
<TEI.2 id="tp002">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Introduction (tp002)</title>
        <author>
          <name type="foreName">Barry</name>
          <name type="surname">Ife</name>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <pubPlace/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="spa">Spanish</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction to the <title>Letters from America</title></head>
        <div>
          <p>The purpose of this edition is to make available for the first time, in a convenient
            format, two of the letters which Columbus is known to have dispatched immediately upon
            his return from the first voyage to the New World in March 1493. The two letters in
            question were addressed to Their Majesties <name>King Ferdinand</name> and <name>Queen
              Isabella</name>, the Catholic Monarchs, and to a court official, Luis de Santángel,
            who played a key role in arranging the finance for the voyage. The letter to Santángel
            has been a seminal document in Columbus studies for some time, and is often referred to
            simply as 'the Columbus letter'; but the letter to the Catholic Monarchs has only
            recently come to light. This edition provides a reliable Spanish text of both letters,
            with facing translation, and a parallel edition of the two texts to facilitate detailed
            comparative study.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Accounts of the 1492 Voyage</head>
          <p>Almost everything we know about the 1492 voyage to the New World has come down to us
            directly or indirectly from Columbus's own hand. This presents the historian - and the
            cultural and literary historians who are increasingly drawn to the importance of
            Columbus's writings - with a unique body of first-hand source material, and some
            formidable problems of interpretation.</p>
          <p>For a man of action, Columbus was uncommonly aware of the importance of making written
            records of everything he did. When he set sail for the Far East in August 1492 he
            decided, in view of the significance of what he was about to attempt, to record the
            findings of the voyage in the form of charts and a log book:</p>
          <p>... I decided to write down the whole of this voyage in detail, day by day, everything
            that I should do and see and undergo, as will be seen in due course.<note id="fn01"><q
                lang="spa">...pensé de escrevir todo este viaje muy puntualmente de día en día todo
                lo que yo hiziese y viese y passasse como adelante se veyrá</q>. Prologue (Ife,
                <title>Journal</title>, pp. 4, 5). The keeping of a log-book was not standard
              practice, and did not become a legal requirement for captains of vessels flying the
              Spanish flag until 1575.</note></p>
          <p>However, it would be a mistake to attribute this decision entirely to bureaucratic
            motives. Columbus had an almost uncanny sense that, whatever happened to him on his
            great voyage, it would have no substance until or unless it took a tangible form, either
            as booty or the balance of trade, or as a written account through which his readers
            could reconstruct the reality of the events. The log-book and other written documents
            serve as verbal testimony of the truth of the voyage; they lend authority to Columbus's
            legal and personal claims, and act as touchstones of his achievement.<note id="fn02"
              >Greenblatt, <title>Marvellous Possessions</title>, offers the most sustained and
              intelligent defence of this point, especially in chapter 3.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The '<foreign>Diario</foreign>'</head>
          <p>Test: <foreign n="portuguese_a">ã</foreign></p>
          <p>The most detailed account of the voyage was the day-to-day record or log-book which
            Columbus presented to Queen Isabella on his return to Spain in the spring of 1493. She
            had it copied, retained the original, and gave the copy to Columbus before he set out on
            the second voyage in the autumn of 1493. The original disappeared within the Queen's
            lifetime and what survives is not the copy that Columbus took back with him to the New
            World, but a lengthy summary with extensive verbatim extracts made by Bartolomé de las
            Casas at some time around the 1520s. This document, called variously the <title
              lang="spa">Diario</title> or <title>Journal</title>, has been for over 150 years the
            major source of information about the first voyage, and the problematic form in which it
            survives has made it the object of intense scrutiny and lively debate.<note id="fn03"
              >Las Casas's digest of the log was first published by Martín Fernández de Navarrete in
              1825. For an excellent summary of the issues surrounding its interpretation see
              Henige, <title>In Search of Columbus</title>; Henige and Zamora, 'Text, context,
              intertext'; Zamora, '"<foreign>Todas son palabras formales del
            Almirante</foreign>"'.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Columbus's own summaries</head>
          <p>After the initial euphoria of finding land more or less exactly where he said it would
            be, the months following the landfall were a period of some difficulty for Columbus. The
            expedition was at first nonplussed, and then increasingly frustrated, at the refusal of
            the new-found lands to conform to the discoverers' cultural expectations and to yield
            the expected economic rewards. Dissent, compounded by the tragic loss of the Santa María
            which ran aground and broke up on Christmas day, forced Columbus to return to Spain
            before he had been able to carry out the detailed surveys and gather the tangible
            evidence of great oriental wealth which would have ensured him a rapturous reception.</p>
          <p>Columbus frequently comments in the <title lang="spa">Diario</title> on the difficulty
            of communicating a new and unimagined reality to an absent audience, and during the
            return journey he was obviously exercised by the question of how he was going to break
            the news about the success of the voyage and his findings. The Catholic Monarchs
            themselves were not the real problem: he would obviously have to report to them in
            person and would have ample opportunity to impress them with first-hand accounts, and to
            show them how the discoveries could best be exploited. What is more, he would leave with
            them the detailed log-book through which the voyage could be re-created in their
            imaginations. More difficult was the problem of managing the public response, which, if
            he were not careful, could become coloured by garbled accounts from disaffected
            crew-members. The worst outcome would be for the Monarchs to get wind of the news
            through these unofficial and undoctored channels.</p>
          <p>Columbus's problems of information management became particularly acute around the
            middle of February 1493, when he was experiencing very heavy seas in the Atlantic off
            the Azores during the return voyage. He had long since lost the Santa María, and he had
            become separated from the Pinta during the bad weather in mid Atlantic. He was left with
            the Niña, the smallest ship of the three, and faced the very real prospect of going to
            the bottom of the Ocean and taking the news with him, or, worse still, of Martín Alonso
            Pinzón getting home first. On February 14, he decided to summarise the main points of
            the voyage in writing:</p>
          <p>...and so that, if he were to perish in that storm, the Monarchs would have news of his
            voyage, he took a piece of parchment and wrote on it everything he could about
            everything he had found, beseeching whomsoever might find it to take it to the Monarchs.
            He wrapped the parchment tightly in a waxed cloth and called for a large wooden barrel
            and put it in the barrel without anyone knowing what it was, for they all thought it was
            some act of devotion, and then ordered it to be thrown into the sea.<note id="fn04"><q
                lang="spa">...y porque si se perdiese con aquella tormenta los Reyes oviesen noticia
                de su viaje, tomó un pargamino y escrivió en él todo lo que pudo de todo lo que avía
                hallado, rogando mucho a quien lo hallase que lo llevase a los Reyes. Este pargamino
                enbolvió en un paño ençerado atado muy bien, y mandó traer un gran barril de madera
                y púsolo en él sin que ninguna persona supiese qué era, sino que pensaron todos que
                era alguna devoçión y así lo mandó echar en la mar</q> (Ife, <title>Journal</title>,
              pp. 218, 219).</note></p>
          <p>This incident illustrates, if proof were needed, the almost painful fragility of
            communications at that period. In Columbus's perilous situation, there was literally
            only one thing that he could do - resort to writing. The summary which he produced -
            which has naturally not survived - almost certainly resembled very closely the reports
            which he subsequently sent to the Catholic Monarchs and to Luis de Santángel, and which
            may already have existed in draft at that time.</p>
          <p>
            <foreign>conquistadores</foreign>
          </p>
          <p>Columbus survived the storms in the Atlantic that February, and lived to tell the tale.
            The letters which he dispatched on his arrival in Lisbon became the model for hundreds
            of similar reports from future generations of <foreign>conquistadores</foreign>, and in
            the hands of such a consummate salesman as Columbus was, the
            <foreign>carta-relación</foreign> turned out to be an extremely effective way of
            managing information. In modern terms, the brief accounts he sent to the Crown and their
            officers were the 'executive summaries' to which the later, more detailed reports
            became, in effect, appendices. The brevity and narrow focus of the
              <foreign>carta-relación</foreign> allowed Columbus to concentrate the attention of his
            addressees on precisely those issues which he wished to emphasise, and to ensure that
            his was the version of events which first caught their attention.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The 'Letter to Santángel'</head>
          <p>The news of the first voyage spread throughout Europe with enormous speed, largely by
            means of the so-called 'letter to Santángel'. This letter was published twelve times, in
            six cities, in five countries, and in three languages, all within a few months of
            Columbus's return. The rapid diffusion of this letter bears testimony not just to
            contemporary perceptions of the importance of the voyage in itself, but also to the way
            in which new printing technology created, almost simultaneously throughout Europe, a
            sense that a new age was beginning.<note id="fn05">Ramos, <title lang="spa">La carta de
                Colón</title>, p. [2].</note></p>
          <p>The Santángel letter was first published in Castilian, by Pedro Posa in Barcelona, in
            April of 1493. It was immediately translated into Latin by Leandro Cosco and published
            in Rome (twice), Antwerp, Basle and Paris (three times). It also circulated in an
            Italian verse translation, and in German, and was printed again in Spanish in Valladolid
            in 1497.</p>
          <p>The Santángel letter poses a number of problems, not the least of which is the fact
            that Santángel's name does not appear anywhere on the document. The opening salutation
            is simply <q lang="spa">Señor</q>, and the printer's colophon merely states that the
            letter was sent by Columbus <q>to the Controller of the Household</q> and that it was
              <q>enclosed in another to Their Majesties</q>.<note id="fn06">See pp. 64, 65 n.
            46.</note> The Latin version interprets the holder of this post as Gabriel (or, in one
            case, Rafael) Sánchez, who was in fact Treasurer. It has usually been assumed that
            Columbus must have sent two letters, one to Santángel and another to Sánchez. However,
            the texts are virtually identical, allowing for the translation, and whereas Columbus
            was deeply indebted to Santángel he is not otherwise known to have had any contact with
            Sánchez. It could be, therefore, that the attribution to Sánchez resulted from confusion
            about who held the post of Controller.</p>
          <p>The dating of the Sántangel letter is also problematic. The letter itself is dated
              <q>on board the caravel, off the islands of the Canaries, 15 February in the year
            1493</q>. If this date is correct, it means that Columbus wrote the letter at sea before
            or during those storm-tossed days around the middle of February, about the time when he
            was reduced to putting messages in barrels. But Columbus was nowhere near the Canaries
            on 15 February. He was off the island of Santa Maria in the Azores, as he well knew, and
            as the Diario makes clear.<note>See the entry for 18 February (Ife,
              <title>Journal</title>, pp. 222, 223).</note></p>
          <p>This curious detail has its counterpart in other errors in the letter. The opening
            sentence states that the newly discovered islands lie at a distance of twenty days'
              sail,<note id="fn08">The correct figure of 33 appears in all editions subsequent to
              Posa's, but not in two of the MSS (p. 46 n. 2).</note> and their latitude is given
            later as 26°N (pp. 58, 59). That is, the new discoveries are much further north and not
            as far west as Columbus knew them to be. There appears to be clear evidence here of
            deliberate disinformation by an administration which was acutely sensitive to the
            political and diplomatic implications of the discoveries. The Santángel letter attempts
            to associate in the mind of the reader the islands of the Indies with the archipelago of
            the Canaries - Spain's only Atlantic possession -, and tries to avoid a public admission
            that on 15 February 1493 Columbus had been in Portuguese territorial waters.</p>
          <p>It is not clear whether these falsifications are attributable to Columbus himself or to
            the spin doctors in the court of the Catholic Monarchs.<note id="fn09">Demetrio Ramos
              has argued that the Santángel letter is a complete fabrication, not written by
              Columbus at all but drafted, at the request of the Monarchs, for public consumption on
              the basis of Columbus's report to them. It could even be that Santángel was the
              author, not the recipient, of the letter. However, the subsequent discovery of what
              appears to be Columbus's earliest report to the Monarchs makes it clear that the
              Santángel letter could not have been based on that report, since it contains
              information which Columbus did not include in his letter to Their Majesties (see
              below, pp. 15-16).</note> But it is difficult to avoid the conclusion that the
            Santángel letter was published in part to create the impression, in the context of
            territorial negotiations with Portugal taking place in Rome, that the new discoveries
            were Spanish possessions by right. The almost simultaneous publication of the Santángel
            letter in some of the major commercial and political centres of Europe - Barcelona,
            Rome, Antwerp, Basle and Paris - is clearly an attempt at blanket press coverage of an
            important event on the world stage, and it shows an early appreciation of the advantages
            of media manipulation on a grand scale.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The 'Letter to the Monarchs'</head>
          <p>It has long been known that the Santángel letter was not the only report Columbus sent
            on his return in March 1493. For one thing, it is extremely unlikely that he would break
            the news to a private individual, albeit an officer of the Crown and a valuable ally in
            the original financing of the voyage, without first or at least simultaneously reporting
            to Their Majesties. Secondly, the colophon of the Santángel letter says that it was an
            enclosure to another letter, addressed to the Monarchs. And thirdly, Columbus himself
            later recalled that he wrote to Their Majesties on 4 March that year.<note id="fn10">In
              a letter dated Española, 3 February, 1500. <title lang="spa">Libro copiador</title>,
              pp. 37-38 and 567-8.</note> That would make sense, since 4 March was the date of his
            arrival in Lisbon.<note>The post-script, or <foreign>ánima</foreign>, to the Santángel
              letter is dated 14 March <q lang="spa">en este puerto de Lisbona oy</q>, <q>in this
                port of Lisbon today</q>. But Columbus was not in Lisbon on 14 March. Having reached
              Lisbon on 4 March, he left on the thirteenth to finish his journey in Palos de la
              Frontera on the fifteenth. On 14 March he was off Cape St Vincent.
                  <q><foreign>Quatorze</foreign> [fourteen] <foreign>días de marzo</foreign></q> in
              the Santángel letter may therefore be an error for <q><foreign>quatro</foreign>
              [four]</q>. If so, Columbus dispatched at least three documents on that day: the
              letter to the Monarchs, inside which was the Santángel letter dated 15 February,
              inside which was the post-script dated [4] March.</note></p>
          <p>The recent discovery of an important new Columbus MS in Spain has led scholars to
            conclude that this missing letter to the Monarchs has been found. The <title lang="spa"
              >Libro copiador</title>, acquired in the late 1980s by the Spanish government from a
            private vendor and lodged in the Archivo General de Indias, contains nine Columbus
            documents of which seven are previously unknown. The first of these is a letter to the
            Catholic Monarchs dated <q>on the Spanish sea, 4 March 1493</q>.<note id="fn12">See Note
              on the Texts, pp. 19-20.</note></p>
          <p>The letter to the Monarchs offers a clear and coherent structure which can be divided
            into six main sections (see Table 1). The letter begins with a summary of the voyage as
            a whole, outlining the route taken, listing the main islands visited and affirming the
            legitimacy of the acts of possession. He is careful to explain the reasons for the
            important change of course on 31 October, when he decided to abandon the westerly route
            along Cuba and to turn east. He reports on attempts to reconnoitre the interior of Cuba,
            the lack of any sign of a large town or city, and the eventual sighting of Española to
            the east. He concludes this introductory section by giving reasons for his relatively
            early return (he was in the Caribbean for only a little over three months): he had found
            most of what he was looking for, including the town of Navidad, and had been betrayed by
            'someone from Palos' - a dark reference to his ongoing disputes with Martín Alonso
            Pinzón.</p>
          <p>Columbus then proceeds to give basic ethnographic information about the native
            inhabitants of the area as a whole, giving everything a strongly paradisiac gloss. The
            people are 'the finest under the sun, without evil or deception'; naked, weaponless,
            eschewing private property, without religion, and generous in the extreme. They insisted
            that the Spaniards came from heaven (or, at least, from the sky) and they insisted on
            offering hefty pieces of gold in exchange for broken crockery.</p>
          <p>Columbus next provides specific details about the two major islands, Juana (Cuba) and
            Española. These are by far the largest of those he visited, and he compares them, not
            unreasonably, with Great Britain and the Iberian Peninsula in terms of size. Cuba is
            impressively mountainous, but Española - the 'Spanish Isle' - is better; more lush, more
            fertile, and watered by copious rivers 'of which the majority carry gold'.</p>
          <p>Notwithstanding the richness of the lands he has encountered, the voyage itself was not
            without its difficulties, as Columbus goes on to relate: contrary winds, problems of
            communication, unsuitable ships foisted on him before he left Castile and only accepted
            with reluctance in order to get the enterprise under way. Nevertheless, the Almighty
            rewarded his steadfastness with the gift of the town of Navidad and the first Christian
            settlement in Española.</p>
          <p>
            <foreign>conquistadores</foreign>
          </p>
          <p>The economic benefits of the discoveries receive extensive treatment. Having located
            the sources of supply of some of Europe's most expensive imported goods - gold, pepper,
            mastic, aloe, rhubarb and cinnamon - opens up the prospect of great wealth and the
            potential to fund another campaign to recapture Jerusalem. Columbus himself offers to
            underwrite the costs of ten thousand cavalry and one hundred thousand infantry, and
            suggests not only that great celebrations should take place throughout Christendom, but
            that they should remember the sacrifices he himself has made, and should reward him
            accordingly, together with his son Diego and the faithful Villacorta.</p>
          <p>Columbus ends, as all good writers of travellers' tales should end, with some exotica:
            reports of islands populated exclusively by women, by cannibals, by people with tails
            and people without hair, and of lands yielding 'gold beyond measure'.</p>
          <p>Columbus's summary of the first voyage offers something for everyone, combining
            accurate geographical and ethnographical detail on the one hand with some wild
            speculation about economic and religious benefits on the other. All this is packaged
            with great skill. What emerges is an account of the new discoveries which shows how
            right Columbus had been - the land was where he said it would be, 2400 miles out into
            the Atlantic - and how wise the Catholic Monarchs had been to back him. In exchange, he
            offers them prospects of vast riches based largely on misreadings of Arawak and Carib
            culture and too much reading of medieval travel literature.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The two letters compared</head>
          <p>Reference to Table 1, in which the two letters are analysed under 38 thematic
            sub-heads, reveals both striking similarities and obvious differences. In the early
            stages (nos 1-6) the letters are so close that it is difficult to be certain whether we
            are dealing with a single text and a variant, or with two different texts. Detailed
            textual comparison of these early paragraphs (pp. 68-70) shows, however, that even when
            Columbus is using identical syntax and lexis, the letters are not sufficiently close to
            suggest that one was directly copied from the other. The impression is rather that
            Columbus is using language in an almost formulaic manner, as he does elsewhere, most
            notably in the <title lang="spa">Diario</title>,<note id="fn13">Ife, <q>Journal</q>, pp.
              xi-xii.</note> or that he may conceivably be drawing on two separate occasions on the
            phraseology of a common reference point, presumably the log itself.<note id="fn14">There
              are numerous places in both texts where it seems likely that Columbus was using his
              log as an <foreign>aide-mémoire</foreign>. See Rumeu de Armas, <title lang="spa">Libro
                copiador</title>, pp. 70-73.</note></p>
          <p>As the two letters proceed, however, they grow further apart, although the overall
            structure is similar. The letter to Santángel is shorter by about 300 words and differs
            from that to the Monarchs in two major respects: it does not contain the petitions (nos
            24-26), which is reasonable given that there is no point in making petitions to someone
            who cannot grant them; and it is markedly less messianic. The Santángel letter says
            nothing about the providential aspects of the voyage, or about the opportunities which
            the new lands offer to fund a new crusade against Jerusalem. This omission is surprising
            in view of the importance which is normally attached to messianic issues in accounts of
            Columbus's career,<note id="fn15">E.g. A. Milhou, <title lang="spa">Colón y su
                mentalidad mesiánica</title>.</note> but shows, perhaps, how sensitive Columbus was
            to the enthusiasms of his readers. Crusades may well be of interest to the Monarchs, but
            might cut less ice with merchants and financiers than would news about the riches of
            this world.</p>
          <p>Consistent with his playing down of religion in the Santángel letter, Columbus gives
            many more ethnographical details than he does in the letter to the Monarchs, and in
            general there is both a greater use of mercantile discourse and a greater sense of
            'scientific' rigour. The Santángel text gives the name of the landfall island Guanahaní
            - incorrectly, it is true, but then that may be the fault of the compositors - and gives
            more details about such things as canoes, about the native diet, and about the relative
            status of men and women, all of which are missing from the letter to the Catholic
            Monarchs. Also significant in this respect is the way in which the Santángel text
            elaborates at some length on the generosity of the Indians (compare pages 31 and 53).</p>
          <p>The two texts differ significantly in the ways in which they treat the exotic. The
            Santángel letter admits quite frankly that Columbus has found no monsters ('as many
            expected', he says), although he has heard tell of caribs and people with tails and an
            island where 'they assure me' the inhabitants have no hair. Furthermore, the Santángel
            text ends with a surprisingly modest observation given the arrogance which he so often
            affects: 'although these lands may have been spoken or written of, that was all
            conjecture, without eye-witness, and those who heard the stories listened to them and
            judged them more as fables than as having the least vestige of truth' (p. 63). Others
            may have speculated about the existence of lands to the west; his contribution was to be
            the eye-witness, to supply scientific proof from empirical observation. Columbus seems
            curiously aware of the fabulous nature of much medieval cosmography while being heavily
            dependent on it for his discourse of success; and, at the same time, there emerges a
            strong sense of Columbus building on the work of others and acting as part of a
          team.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Eloquent silence - the case of Navidad</head>
          <p>Each letter has details and, more important, has a hidden agenda, which is missing from
            the other, but both letters are eloquent, to different degrees, in what they omit to
            mention altogether. In this, Columbus shows his skill at manipulating the silences, the
            gaps between the interstices of the text. Both letters betray an element of
            defensiveness about what he was actually able to achieve on the first voyage,
            particularly in terms of tangible benefits, and Columbus has often been accused of
            exaggerations and outright lies.<note id="fn16">E.g. Phillips and Phillips, <title>The
                Worlds of Christopher Columbus</title>, pp. 182-187, and Sale, <title>The Conquest
                of Paradise</title>, p. 124.</note> Cuba is not quite as large as England and
            Scotland; Española is quite a bit smaller than the Iberian Peninsula; and the mountains
            of Cuba are not as high as those of the Canaries. He did not find gold, or gold mines,
            as the letters say; he did not even find rhubarb or cinnamon.</p>
          <p>In particular, he did not find a large town. This last assertion comes about in
            response to what was probably the major disaster of the voyage, the running aground and
            destruction of his flagship, the Santa María. It could not have happened at a worse
            time. The Pinta had sailed off on its own initiative, and the loss of the flagship
            reduced him to a single caravel, the Niña, the smallest of the three, and nowhere near
            big enough to get everyone home. Once Columbus had recovered from his shock, and his
            freely admitted distress, he began to see the incident as providential. The loss of the
            Santa María gave him the opportunity to found a town, which he called Navidad after the
            date on which the accident took place.</p>
          <p>The disaster itself is all but ignored in both letters, and one can see why: financiers
            do not like to be told that they will have to write off the costs of expensive pieces of
            hardware like ships. But returning home without his largest ship had to be explained
            somehow, and that would best be done in person, when there would be plenty of
            opportunity to put the best face on what happened after the news of the triumph had had
            time to sink in. Meanwhile he had say something, and he really had to mention the
            founding of Navidad.</p>
          <p>This incident is mentioned three times in the two letters, once in the Santángel text,
            and twice in the letter to the Monarchs:</p>
          <p>...I had left my flagship with the men in Your Highnesses' town of Navidad, where they
            were establishing a fortress, as I shall later report...(p. 27)</p>
          <p>...He gave me a place with evident wonderment where I might build a fort, which must by
            now be completely finished.And it was His wish that I should leave there, in possession
            of the town of Navidad, the men I had with me on the flagship and some from the
            caravels, equipped with provisions for more than a year and a lot of artillery, free of
            any danger from anyone, and, indeed, with the firm friendship of the king of the area,
            who took great pride in calling me his brother and treating me as such...(p. 33)</p>
          <p>...I have taken possession of a large town to which I gave the name the town of Navidad
            and I have made a fortress, the building of which should by now be finished and I have
            left there sufficient men for the purpose, together with arms and artillery and supplies
            for more than a year, and a boat and a shipwright to build others, and with the firm
            friendship of the king of that land, so much so that he took great pride in calling me
            his brother and treating me as such...(p. 57)</p>
          <p>It is evident from these extracts that Columbus manages to convey with great skill a
            number of things which were not the case: that Navidad already existed, and was a large
            town; that he had taken possession of this fortress; that he had left the crew there by
            design; and that the absence of the flagship was due to the fact that he had left it
            there to assist the Spaniards in the defence of the town. The reality was very
            different: Navidad was built from nothing, on the beach on the north coast of Española
            using the timbers from the striken ship, destroyed by the elements and by carelessness;
            and the crew had to be left behind because they could not fit into the Niña, the only
            ship left him by the ill-discipline of Martín Alonso Pinzón. Nevertheless, he does his
            best, and builds towns on sand with as much facility as others build castles in
          Spain.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion</head>
          <p>Much anachronistic outrage is directed at Columbus for his cavalier approach to the
            truth. But there are two caveats to enter. One is simply to remind ourselves that as far
            as the first voyage is concerned, we cannot know what the truth is. Indeed, the
            historiography of this voyage illustrates perfectly the fact that history is always an
            account, a narrative, and a narrative always has an author and an audience. All the
            narratives of the first voyage derive from a single author, Columbus himself. How can we
            judge if any one is any more or less true than any other?</p>
          <p>The other caveat is to remind ourselves that the rhetorical basis of all acts of
            communication relates to their purpose. Columbus was a compulsive writer, but he never
            wrote in order to give posterity a comprehensive account of what happened. Most of the
            time he wrote because he wanted something. What he wanted at the beginning of March 1493
            was more time and more money. He had made a tremendous scientific and cultural
            breakthrough, the importance of which not even he was equipped to appreciate, but he had
            not quite delivered the goods in economic terms. He was sure that he could, given time
            and money.</p>
          <p>The purpose of the letters both to the Monarchs and to Santángel was not just to break
            the news of the discoveries, but to stoke the enthusiasm and commitment of the very
            people Columbus needed on his side: the authorities in the shape of the Monarchs, and
            the financiers in the shape of Santángel. He told them what they wanted to hear,
            contouring the message to their lusts and desires. He bent the truth, and sometimes he
            broke it; but he did it with skill, and with eloquence.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
