<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd" >
<TEI.2 id="tp003">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Don Quixote's Diet (tp003)</title>
        <author>
          <name type="foreName">Barry</name>
          <name type="surname">Ife</name>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Article by B W Ife</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>

      <div type="section" n="1">
        <p>In chapter six of Part I of <title>Don Quijote</title>, the priest and the barber conduct
          a scrutiny of the books in <name>Don Quixote</name>'s library in a vain attempt to
          expurgate the malady of the chivalresque. But not all the books end up on the fire. Among
          those that are spared is the 1511 Castilian translation of <name>Martorell</name>'s
          Catalan romance <title>Tirant lo blanc</title>. This book is praised both for its style,
          and for its down-to-earth treatment of the lives of its heroes: 'aquí comen los
          caballeros, y duermen y mueren en sus camas, y hacen testamento antes de su muerte, con
          estas cosas de que todos los demás libros deste género carecen' (I.6.83). <note n="1"
            >References are by part.chapter.page to the edition of <bibl>Francisco Rico (Barcelona:
              Crítica), 1998</bibl>. An early version of this essay was read at the International
            Conference 'Hacia un Nuevo Humanismo', Córdoba 1997, and successive revisions have also
            been presented at the Universities of Bristol and Edinburgh. The conference proceedings
            not having appeared as planned, I am grateful to Paul Lewis-Smith for offering to
            publish the essay at Bristol.</note> To find a book praised as 'el mejor libro del
          mundo' because its characters eat, sleep and die testate in their beds is rather odd when
          one comes to consider <title>Don Quijote</title> itself. It is true that Quixote also dies
          in bed, and not before he has made a will. But even a cursory reading of the novel shows
          that for most of the time Don Quixote sleeps little and eats less. Even before he embarks
          on his chivalric career, the run-down and neglected character of his estate and household
          is reflected in the miserable diet he has to endure: 'Una olla de algo más vaca que
          carnero, salpicón las más noches, duelos y quebrantos los sábados, lantejas los viernes,
          algún palomino de añadidura los domingos' (I.1.35-36). Just what these dishes imply about
          Don Quixote's economic and social status, and just what they tell us about the state of
          his health, will be discussed later in this essay. But for the present it seems clear that
          Don Quixote's diet is frugal, monotonous and unappetising, and it is hardly surprising
          that with such meagre fare Don Quixote is as thin as he is always portrayed. But Quixote's
          bad habits are not limited to diet. He also neglects his sleep: 'se le pasaban las noches
          leyendo de claro en claro, y los días de turbio en turbio' (I.1.39). Here we have the
          classic syndrome of the single male: the fatal combination of late nights and junk food.
          Most men go through this stage at some point in their lives, and most men grow out of it.
          But Don Quixote never does, and eventually he makes himself so ill that his brain dries up
          and he starts to lose his wits: 'se le secó el celebro de manera que vino a perder el
          juicio' (I.1.39). Cervantes did not need to be a qualified doctor to recognise the
          symptoms of sleep deprivation and malnutrition, or to know what the combined effect would
          be on his hero's behaviour in the novel. I am by no means the first reader to notice the
          frequent, if not always prominent, references to food (and sleep) in the book. <note n="2"
            >The classic study is by Francisco Rodríguez Marín, <bibl><title>El yantar de Alonso
                Quijano</title> (Madrid: Real Academia Española), 1916</bibl>. See also <bibl>José
              Luis Peset and Manuel Almela Navarro, 'Mesa y clase en el Siglo de Oro español: la
              alimentación en "El Quijote"', <title>Cuadernos de Historia de la Medicina
              Española</title> 14 (1975), 245-60</bibl>. I am grateful to Bob Goodwin for providing
            me with copies of these notes, and for other bibliographical assistance which is
            acknowledged elsewhere in the notes by the initials [RG]. E.C. Riley also notes the
            importance of food and sleep in his <bibl><title>Don Quixote</title> (London: Allen and
              Unwin, 1986), p. 107</bibl>: 'His [Don Quixote's] condition is aggravated by further
            neglect of proper food and rest.' During the Córdoba conference, Professor Arthur Terry
            informed me of a paper, then forthcoming, which he had delivered in 1996 to the 25th
            Anniversary symposium of the British Comparative Literature Association. This paper was
            subsequently published as <bibl>'A consuming interest: eating and not eating in Don
              Quixote', <title>New Comparison</title> 24 (1997), 57-71</bibl>. I am grateful to
            Professor Terry for providing me with an advance copy of this extremely interesting
            article. Coincidentally, he and I independently took the same quotation as our point of
            departure, and our subsequent developments of the theme, though quite different, are
            nevertheless complementary.</note> But it is worth revisiting the subject now, since in
          recent years, in France, Italy, Britain and the US, there has been a small explosion in
          the study of food and of eating from a wide range of perspectives, -anthropological,
          historical, and cultural. <note n="3">To the studies mentioned in later footnotes can be
            added <bibl>Robert I. Rotberg and Theodore K. Rabb (eds.), <title>Hunger and History:
                the Impact of Changing Food Production and Consumption Patterns on Society</title>
              (London and New York: Cambridge University Press), 1983</bibl>; <bibl>Maggie Kilgour,
                <title> From Communion to Cannibalism: An Anatomy of Metaphors of
              Incorporation</title> (Princeton and Oxford: Oxford University Press), 1990</bibl>
            [RG]; <bibl>Massimo Montanari, <title>The Culture of Food</title> (Oxford and Cambridge,
              Mass.: Blackwells), 1994</bibl>; <bibl>Jean-Louis Flandrin and Massimo Montanari,
                <title>Histoire de l'alimentation</title> (Paris: Fayard), 1996</bibl>; <bibl>Carole
              Counihan and Penny Van Esterik (eds), <title>Food and Culture. A Reader</title> (New
              York and London: Routledge), 1997</bibl>; <bibl>Sian Griffiths and Jennifer Wallace
              (eds), <title>Consuming Passions. Food in the Age of Anxiety</title> (Manchester:
              Mandolin), 1998</bibl>. Spanish contributions to the field largely centre on the
            medieval period, especially <bibl>Miguel Angel Ladero Quesada, 'La alimentación en la
              España medieval. Estado de las investigaciones', <title>Hispania</title> xlv (1985),
              211-20</bibl> and <bibl>María Teresa Castro, <title>La alimentación en las crónicas
                castellanas bajomedievales</title>, Granada, 1996</bibl> [RG]. There is also a
            series of publications from the Grupo de Investigación Cultura Alimentaria at the
            University of Córdoba, including <bibl>Antonio Garrido Aranda (ed.), <title>Cultura
                alimentaria de España y América</title> (Córdoba: La Val de Onsera),
          1995</bibl>.</note> Not the least important aspect of this fascinating and complex field
          is the dark side, the many ways in which diet implies hunger or starvation, from the
          psychology of anorexia to the politics of famine. The purpose of this essay, then, is
          twofold: first, to offer a simple taxonomy of food studies, an outline guide to what is a
          very wide and complex field of enquiry; and, second, to raise a number of questions which
          arise from the treatment of food in Don Quijote. In particular, I want to discuss the
          significance of both malnutrition and hunger in the formation of Don Quixote's character,
          and then ask what light these aspects of the novel can shed on the wider culinary economy
          of early-modern Spain. Although I cannot hope to resolve these questions at present, they
          nevertheless form an important part of research which is being carried out at King's
          College London on the emergence of food as a significant feature of Spanish literary and
          artistic culture around 1600. </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="2">
        <head>II</head>
        <p> One could hardly claim that recent awareness of the importance of food in human history
          and culture is revolutionary. Armies have been marching on their stomachs for centuries;
          generations of women have been taught that the way to a man's heart is through his
          stomach, and one does not need to be a biochemist to recognise the truth of
          Brillat-Savarin's dictum that we are what we eat. <note n="4">'Tell me what you eat and
            I'll tell you who you are.' <bibl>J-A Brillat-Savarin, <title>La physiologie du
              got</title>, 1825</bibl> .</note> In some ways one could hardly think of a less
          usefully generalised aspect of human behaviour on which to found an academic discipline. </p>

        <p> However, it is important to try to make some sense of the large number of diverse
          studies of food and its central role in human development which have recently been
          published by anthropologists, historians, political scientists, ecologists, nutritionists
          and students of culture and gender. Maurice Aymard has suggested three main paths through
          the field: first, what he calls 'une psycho-sociologie de l'alimentation', dealing with
          the codes, values and rules which society assigns to food; second, 'une approche
          macroéconomique', focusing on population, consumption and prices; and third, a study of
          the nutritional value of foodstuffs in history. <note n="5"><bibl>Maurice Aymard, 'Pour
              l'histoire de l'alimentation. Quelques remarques de méthode', <title>Annales
              ESC</title>, xxx (1975), 431-44</bibl> : '...l'histoire de l'alimentation para”t
            hésiter entre de multiples solicitations. Trois grandes voies lui sont en fait ouvertes.
            Celle d'une psycho-sociologie de l'alimentation: l'homme se nourrit non de nutriment,
            mais d'aliments, et ceux-ci s'ordonnent selon un code relativement rigoureux de valeurs,
            de rgles et de symboles, qui n'évolue qu'avec lenteur. Celle d'une approche
            macroéconomique, qui chercherait ˆ atteindre, ou du moins ˆ encadrer statistiquement,
            par le détour de la consommation, de la population, du commerce extérieur et des prix,
            "l'impossible production". Celle en fin de la valeur nutritive des alimentations
            anciennes, et de leurs carences, en quantité comme en qualité: c'est la direction de
            recherches la plus évidente, mais non la plus aisée' [RG].</note>
        </p>

        <p> An alternative approach would be to look at the various usages of the word 'diet'
          itself, and to use them to provide a structure within which to work. 'Diet' means a number
          of things: the lifestyle of a whole society or social group; provisions in daily use; a
          planned or prescribed selection of food; a restricted allowance for medical, cosmetic or
          penal purposes; and even a fast. Such usages cover a number of general social, economic
          and cultural factors as well as particular issues governing the physical and mental
          well-being of individuals. </p>

        <p> A third approach would be simpler still, and might begin by establishing two
          intersecting axes, one concerned with the production of food, and the other concerned with
          its consumption. This is the approach I propose to take in this essay. If I start with
          consumption it is simply because food is essential for survival, and nutrition has
          therefore to be at the centre of any sensible study of the subject. </p>

        <p> The 'greening' of science that has gathered pace over the past 25 years has led to
          enormous advances in our understanding of the ways in which the principal nutrients of
          food -proteins, carbohydrates, fats, vitamins and minerals- combine together to ensure the
          healthy growth and development of the body and to ensure that it can cope with the energy
          demands placed on it in terms of work. We know that there are some 50 or so substances
          that are essential to this process. The body can synthesise some of them, but, if
          essential nutrients which cannot be synthesised are absent from the diet, serious
          long-term damage will result. Certain of the vitamins, particularly vitamin B-complex and
          vitamin C, fall into this category. A number of serious diseases have long been known to
          result from vitamin deficiencies: beriberi (thiamine, vitamin B1), pellagra (niacin,
          vitamin B3), scurvy (vitamin C), and rickets (vitamin D). </p>

        <p> It is the centrality of the notion of a balanced diet that leads to my second axis, that
          of production. Because the plant and animal species that provide the range of essential
          nutrients are themselves very often soil- and/or climate-specific, no human population can
          be certain that it will have the ingredients of a balanced diet within easy reach. The
          pasture which produces the sweet spring roast lamb will not also support the growing of
          the salad that accompanies it to the table, or the wine (rich in iron, an essential
          mineral for the production of haemoglobin) with which to wash it down. Variety is just as
          important to a good diet as nutritional balance, and, given that few people any longer go
          out and catch their food, variety is provided by the movement of goods through trade. </p>

        <p> This much is obvious, but the study of food gets more interesting when we come to look
          at the ways in which the two axes of consumption and production intersect. Take for
          example the complex relationships between the natural occurrence and migration of plants
          and the influence of soil and climate; the cultivation and genetic improvement of those
          plants; the production of derived foodstuffs and their preservation for transport and
          trade. Take the range of issues concerning culinary traditions, the preparation of food
          for the table and the circumstances of its consumption, the rituals and ceremonies and the
          use of food to underpin social organisation and signal social hierarchy; and consider the
          migration of those culinary traditions along with the associated plants, animals and food
          products, and you have another way of charting movements of human populations and cultures
          in history. Hence the interest of work such as Redcliffe Salaman's classic study of the
          potato first published in 1949; <note n="6"><bibl>Redcliffe N. Salaman, <title>The History
                and Social Influence of the Potato</title> (London: Cambridge University Press),
              1970</bibl> .</note> or studies of other commodities such as sugar by Sidney Mintz,
            <note n="7"><bibl>Sidney W. Mintz, <title>Sweetness and Power: the Place of Sugar in
                Modern History</title> (New York and London: Sifton), 1985</bibl> .</note> peppers
          by Jean Andrews, <note n="8"><bibl>Jean Andrews, <title>Peppers: the Domesticated
                Capsicums</title> (Austin, Texas: University of Texas Press), 1984</bibl> .</note>
          and chocolate by Sophie and Michael Coe. <note n="9"><bibl>Sophie D. Coe and Michael D.
              Coe, <title>The True History of Chocolate</title> (London: Thames and Hudson),
            1996</bibl> .</note>
        </p>

        <p> This is something the British, like all post-imperial and post-colonial powers, are
          constantly aware of, as is underlined by James Walvin's recent study of six products which
          have profoundly influenced British taste - tea, coffee, tobacco, chocolate, sugar and
          potatoes. <note n="10"><bibl>James Walvin, <title>Fruits of the Empire: Exotic Produce and
                British Taste 1600-1800</title> (London: Macmillan), 1997</bibl> .</note> The
          British eat and drink (and for those that do, smoke) the history of their empire on a
          daily basis, yearly if we include the 'traditional' Christmas lunch, of which hardly any
          element is indigenous to the British Isles. And more recently the high street of even the
          smallest country town in England has been testimony to the fact that we live in a global
          kitchen, with Chinese, Japanese, Indian, Bangladeshi restaurants on every corner, not to
          mention French and Italian, <foreign>tapas</foreign> bars and take-away Mexican, and the
          all-conquering Big Mac. </p>

        <p> Other intersections of the two axes bring wider cultural issues into play. Systems of
          belief have raised certain foodstuffs to the status of cult objects or icons -bread, fish
          and wine in the Christian tradition, for example, or corn and maguey in Mesoamerica. They
          have also drawn powerful and long-standing divisions between animals within their
          economies and cultures; take the way that Judaism and Islam exclude pork in favour of
          lamb, or the way that the cow is held sacred by Hindus. Many of these food taboos start
          life as responses to problems of hygiene, but they persist because they are convenient and
          effective ways of consolidating identity and marking territory. As religious conventions,
          they also perform the useful function of linking consumption and abstention, which is a
          theme I will want to mention later. It is not just what we eat that matters; it is what we
          do not eat, what we abstain from, that makes us members of a religious or ethnic
          community. </p>

        <p> One of the most interesting areas of the subject, and one which requires more space than
          I have available, unfortunately, is the confluence of eating and sexuality. This is a
          complex area in which food as the fuel of life, and its influence on health, fertility and
          reproduction, overlaps with the use of the body's orifices for the purposes of sexual
          gratification. Freud's identification of orality as an early, immature, phase of sexuality
          is helpful in understanding why food is so often associated with sex, and particularly why
          food so often becomes a substitute for sex. The modern world has shown us many examples of
          the way in which low self-esteem, particularly among women who are intimidated by
          conventional media representations of female beauty, becomes transformed into the craving
          to gain control demonstrated by sufferers from bulimia and anorexia nervosa. <note n="11"
              ><bibl>Joan Smith, <title>Hungry for You</title> (London: Chatto and Windus), 1996,
              especially chapters 1 and 2</bibl> .</note> This cluster of issues reminds us that
          abstinence and malnutrition are just as important to understanding the central role of
          food in society and culture as over-consumption and the associated political and moral
          issues of over-production. </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="3">
        <head>III</head>

        <p> Of all the aspects of this field considered so far, the intersection of the physical and
          the mental is the least well understood and the most fascinating. Physical size and shape
          often appear to correlate with personality: the fact that Don Quixote, for example, is
          thin and Sancho Panza is fat is not accidental; it is part of Cervantes's design, because
          those shapes are among the vocabulary of signifiers which most languages and cultures have
          in common. But in spite of attempts to divide us all into endomorphs, ectomorphs and
          mesomorphs, there are still plenty of morose, fat people and plenty of jolly, thin people;
          and everyone knows at least one fat person who eats very little but cannot lose weight, or
          at least one person who eats like a horse and looks like a rake. Metabolism and heredity
          are just as important as what we eat. </p>

        <p> If anything, the influence of diet on states of mind is even less well understood,
          though, again, it is obvious that many substances if ingested will induce a radically
          altered psychic state (alcohol, drugs, and even fizzy drinks), while any parent knows that
          the best way of dealing with fractious children is to raise their blood sugar by
          administering rapid doses of sweets and cakes. </p>

        <p> All of these factors are revelant to our consideration of the relationship between Don
          Quixote's physical and mental state and his diet. For Quixote is presented to the reader
          as, above all, a sick man, a man who is physically infirm and mentally unstable, and a man
          whose infirmity and instability are related to specific aspects of his life-style,
          principally the excessive reading of books, lack of sleep and a poor diet. </p>

        <p> In Cervantes's day, the explanation for Don Quixote's psychological profile, the fact
          that he is 'ingenioso', would have been sought in the classical theory of the humours
          developed by Galen and Hippocrates, and which was based on a conjunction of the four
          cosmic elements -air, earth, fire, and water- with the four basic body fluids -blood,
          phlegm, black bile, and yellow bile. According to their relative predominance in the
          individual, these elements were supposed to produce the four temperaments: sanguine,
          phlegmatic, melancholic, and choleric. Emotional stability as well as general health
          depended on an appropriate balance among the four bodily humours; an excess of one
          produced a particular personality trait, such as Quixote's eccentricity, caused by an
          excess of hot, dry elements in his body. <note n="12">See <bibl>Lawrence Babb, <title>The
                Elizabethan Malady</title> (East Lansing: Michigan State College Press), 1951</bibl>
            and <bibl>Otis H. Green, 'El "ingenioso" hidalgo', <title>Hispanic Review</title> 25
              (1957), 175-93</bibl> . The nature of Quixote's melancholy has recently been
            re-examined by Teresa Scott Soufas, who argues that it has a more marked dry quality
            than the cold moist melancholy with which it has traditionally been associated (<bibl>
              <title>Melancholy and the Secular Mind in Spanish Golden Age Literature</title>
              (Columbia and London: University of Missouri Press), 1990</bibl> ).</note>
        </p>

        <p> Although this approach has been largely superseded by more 'scientific' explanations, it
          is important to note that the theory of the humours is above all a
          <emph>physiological</emph> account of mental and emotional states, one in which mental
          imbalance correlates with physical imbalance, or, put another way: <foreign>mens sana in
            corpore sano</foreign>, a sound mind requires a healthy body. <note n="13">Mary
            Lindemann's fascinating survey <bibl><title>Medicine and Society in Early Modern
              Europe</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press), 1999</bibl>, underlines the
            relationship between physiology and psychology in the Renaissance view of mental
            illness: 'Throughout the early modern period there was a strong tendency to link
            afflictions of mind with bodily disturbances, such as a perturbed humoral imbalance or
            indigestion. The body moved mind as easily as the mind affected the body' (p.
          32).</note> Cervantes understood this relationship not only in <title>Don Quijote</title>,
          but in at least two other accounts of delusions and madness: the bed-ridden and feverish
          Campuzano who overhears the dogs' colloquy while recovering in hospital from a dose of the
          pox (<foreign>El casamiento engañoso y coloquio de los perros</foreign> ); and the
          hypersensitive Tomás Rodaja, whose delusions are triggered by the ingestion of a poisoned
          quince (<foreign>El licenciado vidriera</foreign> ). And Cervantes's contemporary Mateo
          Alemán was clear in his understanding that there was a causal relationship not just
          between the humours and the personality, but between what people ate and the kind of
          people they were: 'como en buena filosofía los manjares que se comen vuelven los hombres
          de aquellas complexiones' (<title>Guzmán de Alfarache</title> II.iii.8). </p>

        <p> With the benefits of modern biochemistry, we can in some ways offer more sophisticated
          accounts of the relationship between physical and mental states, but they are not
          substantially different in kind from what was provided by the classical doctors. In order
          to illustrate this point, we might take the virtual contents of Don Quixote's virtual
          stomach and subject them to analysis. We know that his staple diet before the first sally
          consisted of five elements: 'olla', by which we may assume is meant the classic
          slow-cooked stew made with beans and sausages known as 'olla podrida', eaten as the main
          midday meal; <note n="14">As its name implies, this dish is a relative of the <foreign>pot
              pourri</foreign> or cassoulet, and was a staple for the majority of Spaniards of all
            classes (<bibl>Rodríguez Marín, <title>Yantar</title>, pp. 13-18</bibl> ). Cervantes
            describes Don Quijote's version as 'de algo más vaca que carnero', implying that it was
            made with the cheaper cuts, mutton being more expensive than beef at that time (p.
          18).</note> 'salpicón' or cold meat sliced thinly with onions and vinegar for supper;
            <note n="15">Ambrosio de Salazar (1615, cited in Rodríguez Marín, p. 20): 'salpicón es
            hecho con carne cozida y fiambre, cortada menuda con cebollas y vinagre, y assí se come
            fría en lugar de lechugas o otra ensalada.'</note> 'lantejas' or lentils on Fridays;
            <note n="16"><bibl>Rodríguez Marín, <title>Yantar</title>
            </bibl>, describes them as 'cosa pésima' and wonders if they might not have been the
            cause of Don Quixote's madness, citing <bibl>Juan de Aviñón, <title>Sevillana
              medicina</title>
            </bibl> : 'generalmente las lantejas son malas y melancólicas' (p. 29).</note> 'duelos y
          quebrantos', probably some form of omelette, on Saturdays; <note n="17">This dish,
            assuming that it is a dish, since some commentators and translators have taken the
            phrase to refer either to hunger or to wind, has given rise to much discussion, which is
            summarised by <bibl>Rodríguez Marín, <title>Yantar</title>, pp. 21-8</bibl> .
                <bibl><title>Autoridades</title> (1732)</bibl> defines the phrase as follows:
            'Llaman en la Mancha a la tortilla de huevos y sesos' and gives Don Quijote as the only
            source. Other authorities such as María Moliner (1987) broaden the range of ingredients,
            but only to those parts of the animal that could be consumed on days of semi-abstinence:
            'Fritada que se hacía con huevos y alguna parte de animal, como torreznos ['pedazo de
            tocino frito o preparado para freir'] o sesos; antiguamente se solía comer los sábados,
            por ser comida de semiabstinencia.' A further group of authorities, following Juan
            Antonio Pellicer in the late 18th century, refer to a dish made by shepherds from the
            remains of any sheep in their care who might meet with an accident or ill fortune. One
            such source is the <bibl><title>Diccionario enciclopédico de la lengua española</title>
              (Madrid: Imprenta y Librería de Gaspar y Roig), 1853</bibl>, which defines the phrase
            as follows: 'La olla que de los huesos quebrantados y de las estremidades de las reses
            que se desgraciaban y morían entre semana se hacía en algunos lugares de la Mancha y en
            otras partes, para comerla los sábados, cuando en los reinos de Castilla no se permitía
            comer en tales días las demás partes ni la grosura, cuya costumbre derogó Benedicto XIV
            el año de 1748.' Rodríguez Marín quotes Pellicer himself on p. 23, before going on to
            suggest (without any real authority other than its plausibility) that eggs and bacon
            were the common standby when the larder was bare and all was 'duelos y quebrantos' (28).
            Sancho fears that the innkeeper in chapter 59 of Part II of <title>Don Quijote</title>
            will resort to 'las sobras que debe de haber de tocino y huevos' in similar
            circumstances (see below).</note> and the occasional pigeon on Sundays. We may assume
          also that, in real life, Alonso Quijano would have supplemented this diet with bread and
          wine, and he may possibly, but not necessarily, have also eaten some fruit and vegetables;
            <note n="18">Vegetables were much despised by the middle and upper classes, and fruit
            was usually eaten stewed, as in England, since fresh fruit was commonly regarded with
            suspicion: 'Fruites generally are noyfulle to man and do ingender ill humours'
              (<bibl>Sir Thomas Elyot, <title>Castel of Helth</title>, 1541</bibl>, quoted in
              <bibl>Sara Paston-Williams, <title>The Art of Dining: a History of Cooking and
              Eating</title> (London: The National Trust), 1993</bibl>, p. 102).</note> the
          conventions of literary analysis, however, do not allow us to take into account what is
          not in the text. </p>

        <p> Figure 1 gives a summary analysis of the likely nutritional value of this fictional
          diet, together with some of the principal nutrients expressed as a percentage of the
          recommended daily allowance (RDA). </p>

        <table>
          <head>Figure 1 - Analysis of Don Quixote's Diet</head>

          <row role="label">
            <cell role="heading">Nutrient</cell>
            <cell role="heading">Amount</cell>
            <cell role="heading">Units</cell>
          </row>

          <row role="data">
            <cell>Cholesterol</cell>
            <cell>72.24</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Carbohydrates</cell>
            <cell>49.97</cell>
            <cell>gm</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Dietary Fiber</cell>
            <cell>16.53</cell>
            <cell>gm</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Energy</cell>
            <cell>524.75</cell>
            <cell>Cal</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Fat</cell>
            <cell>17.33</cell>
            <cell>gm</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Saturated Fat</cell>
            <cell>5.58</cell>
            <cell>gm</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Potassium</cell>
            <cell>1099.80</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Sodium</cell>
            <cell>661.59</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Unsaturated Fat</cell>
            <cell>10.01</cell>
            <cell>gm</cell>
          </row>
        </table>

        <table>
          <row role="label">
            <cell role="heading">Nutrient</cell>
            <cell role="heading">Amount</cell>
            <cell role="heading">Units</cell>
            <cell role="heading">%RDA</cell>
          </row>

          <row role="data">
            <cell>Calcium</cell>
            <cell>67.18</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Folate</cell>
            <cell>357.68</cell>
            <cell>µg</cell>
            <cell>89</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Iron</cell>
            <cell>8.20</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>82</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Magnesium</cell>
            <cell>96.55</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>28</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Niacin</cell>
            <cell>7.99</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>50</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Phosphorus</cell>
            <cell>570.84</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>71</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Protein</cell>
            <cell>42.44</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>76</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Riboflavin</cell>
            <cell>0.38</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>27</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Thiamine</cell>
            <cell>0.68</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>57</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Vitamin A</cell>
            <cell>225.82</cell>
            <cell>µg</cell>
            <cell>23</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Vitamin B</cell>
            <cell>121.00</cell>
            <cell>µg</cell>
            <cell>33</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Vitamin B6</cell>
            <cell>0.79</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Vitamin C</cell>
            <cell>3.63</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Vitamin E</cell>
            <cell>1.05</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>10</cell>
          </row>
          <row role="data">
            <cell>Zinc</cell>
            <cell>5.07</cell>
            <cell>mg</cell>
            <cell>34</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p> Several things about this analysis require comment. Firstly, such a diet would have left
          Don Quixote seriously deficient in energy; his calory intake is only about a quarter of
          that required by a 50-year-old male with even a sedentary lifestyle. <note n="19">Rotberg
            sounds a note of proper warning against misinterpreting historical dietary evidence by
            comparison with modern nutritional requirements (<bibl><title>Hunger</title>, 1-5</bibl>
            ). However, there is ample contextual evidence to suggest that Don Quixote's diet is
            intended to strike the reader as deficient.</note> The consequences of long-term
          malnourishment of this order would be wasting of the flesh and loss of muscle tone.
          Secondly, he is below the recommended daily amount of all nutrients, but is especially
          deficient in Calcium (8%), Vitamin C (6%) and Vitamin E (10%). </p>

        <p> The calcium deficiency is extremely serious and would lead to osteoporosis (loss of bone
          mass), and inhibit blood-clotting. It would also account for the poor state of his teeth,
          frequently commented on in the novel. Vitamin C also helps wounds to heal and keeps bones
          and teeth strong. His low dietary intake of vitamin C probably meant that he was suffering
          from scurvy, a disease that causes weakness, slow healing of wounds, and extreme soreness
          of the gums and joints. The very low intake of vitamin E would also result in weakened red
          blood cells and neurological dysfunction, causing loss of muscle coordination, and vision
          problems. Vision problems, from which it might be said Don Quixote suffers throughout at
          least the first part of the novel, are also caused by deficiency of vitamin A, which at
          23% of recommended daily amount is also among the lowest percentages in the analysis. </p>

        <p> However, there are other reasons for concern about Don Quixote's diet, which go beyond
          basic concerns about malnutrition, and they have to do with the 'duelos y quebrantos' he
          had every Saturday. As Rodríguez Marín points out, the earliest authorities define this
          dish as an omelette made with brains, brains being one of the parts of an animal permitted
          to be eaten on days of semi-abstinence. <note n="20">See note 17.</note> However, there is
          contemporary evidence that the consumption of brains was regarded as a danger to mental
          health. In his <bibl><title>Libro de cocina</title> of 1525, <note n="21">The first
              Castilian edition of this popular cookery book was printed in Toledo in 1525, although
              there is an earlier Catalan edition (Barcelona, 1520). Roberto de Nola was cook to
              King Ferdinand of Naples.</note> Roberto de Nola</bibl> gives an infamous recipe for
          roast cat: 'Gato asado como se quiere comer'. In preparing the cat for cooking, Nola is at
          pains to stress that the head should be cut off and thrown away because 'se dice que
          comiendo los sesos podría perder el seso y juicio el que la comiese.' </p>

        <p> This is an interesting observation in the context of any study of the physiological
          origins of mental states, and could provide a further explanation for Don Quixote's
          unstable mental condition: the regular consumption of offal, and more particularly brains,
          on days of semi-abstinence. Recent experience in Britain, and the development of public
          policy on the production and consumption of meat products offers a thought-provoking
          parallel with sixteenth-century Spain. Cats do suffer from a form of bovine spongiform
          encephalopathy (BSE), and Spaniards in the sixteenth century clearly thought, quite
          rightly, that human beings could go mad from eating the brains of animals. <note n="22"
            >For a fuller discussion of this topic see my <bibl>'Mad Cats and Knights Errant:
              Roberto de Nola and Don Quixote', <title>Journal of the Institute of Romance
              Studies</title>, VII (1999)</bibl> .</note>
        </p>

        <p> Now, I am not seriously proposing that biochemistry can be used for character analysis
          in literary texts. But what I am suggesting is that Cervantes has constructed a credible
          continuum between Don Quixote's social and economic status, his lifestyle, diet, physical
          health and mental condition, and that all these factors combine to produce patterns of
          behaviour which are convincing and consistent. What is more, Cervantes must sustain this
          continuum if Don Quixote is to retain his essential character once he leaves behind his
          sedentary habits and hits the road as a knight errant. </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="4">
        <head>IV</head>

        <p> Don Quixote might have expected his diet to improve once he embarked on his new career.
          All those banquets he read about in novels of chivalry would have been as powerful an
          incentive for a knight-errant as the opportunity to right wrongs and do good. In fact
          things get much, much worse. Indeed, Cervantes appears to do his best to ensure that Don
          Quixote eats as little as possible. On his first evening he arrives at the inn which he
          mistakes for a castle, and the innkeeper brings him 'una porción del mal remojado y peor
          cocido bacallao y un pan tan negro y mugriento como sus armas' (I.2.53). But he cannot eat
          it because he cannot take off his helmet: 'como tenía puesta la celada y alzada la visera,
          no podía poner nada en la boca con sus manos si otro no se lo daba y ponía' (53-54). And
          the same goes for drinking, which he can only manage when the landlord finds him a straw.
          Not surprisingly, this failure to eat a decent supper is immediately followed by one of
          the early exhibitions of Don Quixote's chivalric eccentricity, as he proceeds to sit up
          all night keeping vigil over his armour, prior to his investiture as a knight. </p>

        <p> In this episode Cervantes shows that he intends to keep Don Quixote tired and hungry for
          as long as possible, a strategy which is assisted in the second sally by the convenient
          theft of Sancho's ass, along with the saddlebags containing their supplies for the
          journey. The resulting loss of both food and drink ensure constant hunger, which induces
          the lightheadedness and hallucinations characteristic of Quixote's response to the world.
            <note n="23">Guzmán de Alfarache also comments on the lightheadedness caused by hunger.
            As he first leaves home, on a Friday, he laments that he cannot even rely on a pie to
            give him comfort: 'si fuera día de carne...comprara un pastel con que me entretuviera y
            enjugara el llanto... Entonces eché de ver cuánto se siente más el bien perdido y la
            diferencia que hace del hambriento el harto. Los trabajos todos comiendo se pasan; donde
            la comida falta, no hay bien que llegue ni mal que no sobre, gusto que dure ni contento
            que asista: todos riñen sin saber porqué, ninguno tiene culpa, unos a otros la ponen,
            todos trazan y son quimeristas, todo es entonces gobierno y filosofía' (I.i.3).</note>
          Unlike Sancho, however, Don Quixote rarely complains about hunger; indeed, for the most
          part he seems completely oblivious to it and, as we shall see, on occasions seems rather
          pleased with his ability to do without food. Only during the episode of the Cave of
          Montesinos does Quixote seem at all aware of the relationship between the physical and
          mental strain he has been under, and he asks for something to eat, 'que traía grandísima
          hambre' (II.22.817). </p>

        <p> Cervantes subjects Sancho to the same regime, although Sancho is much more prone to
          complain. He suffers almost systematic starvation during his governorship of the island,
          perhaps the episode in the novel in which the squire comes closest to emulating the
          wayward brilliance of his master. Soon after the beginning of his tenure of office Sancho
          is shown into a palatial dining room and invited to sit at a table laden with many
          sumptuous dishes. But they are each promptly whisked away from him by a doctor who decries
          the ill effects of all types of food, especially partridges: 'Omnis saturatio mala,
          perdicis autem pessima' (II.47.1005). This is one of the reasons Sancho gives for
          resigning the governorship after the enemy invasion: 'más quiero hartarme de gazpachos que
          estar sujeto a la miseria de un médico impertinente que me mate de hambre' (II.53.1065). </p>

        <p> That Cervantes understood the relationship between hunger and hallucination is clear
          from the cases where the contrary is shown to be true. Don Quixote does have his moments
          of lucidity, and not surprisingly they follow the rare opportunities he has to eat. The
          two discourses, on the Golden Age and Arms and Letters, for example, are both after-dinner
          speeches. In the first case, in chapter 11, Quixote and Sancho join a group of goatherds
          who offer to share their evening stew around the fire. Quixote tops this off with a
          handful of acorns, which are rich in protein as well as nostalgic potential. In the second
          example, in chapter 37, the innkeeper puts on a good supper on don Fernando's
          instructions, before Quixote goes on to give one of his best and most memorable speeches
          of Book I. <note n="24">'Y, así, cenaron con mucho contento, y acrecentóseles más viendo
            que, dejando de comer don Quijote, movido de otro semejante espíritu que el que le movió
            a hablar tanto como habló cuando cenó con los cabreros, comenzó a decir:...' (I.37.442).
            Bob Goodwin argues convincingly in his unpublished University of London doctoral thesis,
              <title>Food, Art and Morality in Early Modern Spain</title>, that Quixote's account of
            his visit to the Cave of Montesinos is also an after-dinner speech, since the narrative
            is delivered after he, Sancho and the guide have consumed a meal which is breakfast,
            lunch and supper all in one, and the cloth has been cleared away.</note>
        </p>

        <p> Part II begins, as does Part I, with an immediate mention of the state of Don Quixote's
          diet. If his meagre rations in chapter 1 of Part I had brought him to the verge of
          insanity, in the opening chapter of Part II, he has been nursed back almost to the brink
          of sanity. The priest and the barber had left instructions to his household to feed him
          'cosas confortativas y apropiadas para el corazón y el celebro, de donde procedía, según
          buen discurso, toda su mala ventura' (II.1.625). <note n="25">In this regard, <bibl>Arthur
              Terry ('Consuming interest', 60-61</bibl> ) draws attention to the discussion in I.47
            about whether Don Quixote is enchanted or not. Sancho has heard it said that 'los
            encantados ni comen, ni duermen, ni hablan' (I.47.545) whereas his master 'tiene su
            entero juicio, él come y bebe y hace sus necesidades como los demás hombres.'</note> The
          regime appears to have brought some benefits 'porque echaban de ver que su señor por
          momentos iba dando muestras de estar en su entero juicio'. But he hardly looks the picture
          of health, sitting up in bed in a green vest and red knitted cap, 'tan seco y amojamado,
          que no parecía sino hecho de carne momia' (626). His fragile grip on the real world is
          soon broken when the priest decides to test his sanity to destruction by leading him on to
          the subject of chivalry, and the barber's ensuing tale about the madman of Seville
          underlines the lesson that 'todas nuestras locuras proceden de tener los estómagos vacíos
          y los celebros llenos de aire' (II.1.631). </p>

        <p> Although Don Quixote enjoys considerable celebrity in Part II, he conspicuously fails to
          benefit from the hospitality he might have expected. It is true that he spends a lot more
          time as the guest of the well-heeled, especially with the Duke and Duchess, but there are
          still many occasions when opportunities to eat are passed over. In fact, Camacho's wedding
          feast is one of the rare occasions when Sancho's inability to turn down a free meal causes
          him to take sides against his master. Don Quixote is captivated by Quiteria's and
          Basilio's romantic escape from an arranged marriage, but Sancho finds more to appreciate
          in the jilted Camacho's catering arrangements. When Don Quixote decides to leave before
          the guests start to tuck into the buffet, Sancho is left bewailing one of many lost
          opportunities to satisfy his gluttony while having to make do with a spoonful of broth:
          'así se dejó atrás la ollas de Egipto, aunque las llevaba en el alma, cuya ya casi
          consumida y acabada espuma, que en el caldero llevaba, le representaba la gloria y la
          abundancia del bien que perdía' (II.21.808). </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="5">
        <head>V</head>

        <p> In the discussion so far, one of the main themes has been hunger, or denial of food,
          rather than the satisfaction of hunger. Sometimes the food is there, but Don Quixote is
          prevented from getting at it; at other times, the food is simply not there, or is so poor,
          so frugal or so inedible that virtual starvation is the result. This is not surprising
          since <title>Don Quijote</title> shares at least some of the features of the picaresque, a
          genre pioneered in Spain and dominated by the theme of hunger and its destructive effect
          on the moral fibre of societies and individuals alike. Lazarillo's battle of wits with the
          bread chest, Pablos's eternal meal at Cabra's academy, eternal because it is 'sin
          principio ni fin', are exceptional only for the memorably grotesque humour with which they
          illustrate the desperation which hunger can cause. In all other ways they are entirely
          characteristic of a society defined in terms of lack. And they prompt the thought that if
          people are what they eat, and there is nothing for them to eat, how can they be expected
          to make anything of their lives? </p>

        <p> But putting <title>Don Quijote</title> in the context of the picaresque prompts the
          further question: is Don Quixote's malnutrition peculiar to him or is it systemic? The
          difficulty here is the danger of reading literary texts as historical documents and of
          assuming that they necessarily mean what they say. But it is well to remember that
            <title>Don Quijote</title> is a novel which takes place in history; anachronism is one
          of its central themes, so a strong sense of the contemporary landscape is vital to the way
          it makes its impact. I have argued elsewhere that we should take, for example, the
          frequent use of pastoral in <title>Don Quijote</title> very seriously, and that
          contemporary tensions between agriculture and livestock farming form an important part of
          the countryside through which Quijote and Sancho wander. <note n="26"><bibl>B.W.Ife, 'Some
              uses of pastoral in Don Quijote', <title>Journal of the Institute of Romance
              Studies</title>, IV (1996), 107-21</bibl> .</note> And in Part II there is an incident
          which, albeit humorously, does indeed suggest that Quixote's and Sancho's search for a
          chivalric banquet takes place against a background of serious undersupply. </p>

        <p> In chapter 59 of Part II, Don Quixote and Sancho fetch up at an inn in search of supper.
          The landlord invites them to order anything they wish 'que de las pajaricas del aire, de
          las aves de la tierra y de los pescados del mar estaba proveída aquella venta'
          (II.59.1109). This turns out to be an unjustified boast. Not wishing to appear greedy,
          'porque mi señor es delicado y come poco', Sancho takes him at his word and orders up a
          couple of roast chickens. What follows quickly descends into a preview of the Monty Python
          sketch about the cheese shop which has no cheese. Sancho runs through a whole range of
          dishes -chicken, veal, kid, bacon, eggs- but all of them are off. Either the chickens have
          been eaten by predators, or the pullets have been sent to market, or they are fresh out of
          veal (but there'll be plenty next week), and of course there aren't any eggs because there
          aren't any hens. In the end, Sancho has to settle for cowheel. Either this is part of a
          systematic attempt to blacken the reputation of Spanish hoteliers, or Cervantes is telling
          us something about the level, the quality or the reliability of the food production and
          supply system of early 17th-century Spain. <note n="27">As the innkeeper goes on to imply,
            it was the custom for travellers in Spain to carry food with them for the journey, and
            either have it cooked by the staff at the inn or by their own staff who would travel
            with them. See <bibl>J.M. Diez Borque, <title>La sociedad española y los viajeros del
                siglo XVII</title> (Madrid: Sociedad General Española de Librería), 1975</bibl>
            [RG]. See also <bibl>Trevor J. Dadson, 'El viajar en el siglo de oro: análisis
              comparativo de gastos de comida y posada', <title>Boletín de la Real Academia de la
                Historia</title>, CXCI (1994), 437-54</bibl> and <bibl>'The road to Villarubia: the
              journey into exile of the Duke of Híjar, March 1644', in <title>New Frontiers in
                Hispanic and Luso-Brazilian Scholarship. 'Como se fue el maestro': For Derek W.
                Lomax. In Memoriam</title> (Lewiston: Mellon Press, 1994), pp. 124-55</bibl>
          .</note>
        </p>

        <p> How much do we really know about these issues, about food production, farming, product
          distribution and supply in early-modern Spain? Is the picture of serious underprovision we
          glimpse both in the picaresque novels and in Don Quijote anything like the true picture,
          as has often been supposed, or is it selective, got up by novelists in support of some
          other agenda? <note n="28">In her doctoral thesis, Matilde Santamaría Arnaiz argues that,
            in general, Spaniards enjoyed a relatively good diet in the sixteenth and seventeenth
            centuries (<bibl><title>La alimentación de los españoles bajo el reinado de los
              austrias</title>, Madrid, Complutense, Faculty of Pharmacy, 1986</bibl> ) [RG].</note>
          What is more, how would we handle this information if we had it? These are some of the
          questions which should inform future work on the social and economic history of this
          period. </p>

        <p> In order to fill out the picture, we might also take into account the fact that at
          precisely the time when novels such as <title>Guzmán de Alfarache</title> and <title>Don
            Quijote</title> were being written and published, food was acquiring a prominent
          iconographic role in Spain through the emergence of the still-life genre. Why was it that,
          at the very time when the writers were bemoaning widespread underprovision of food,
          artists such as Juan Sánchez Cotán, and later Velázquez, were celebrating food in paint?
          Is this a contradiction, or is it a case of artists raising humble vegetables to near
          sanctified status in some kind of ironic commentary on their rarity? </p>

        <p> These issues are discussed in Bob Goodwin's doctoral thesis mentioned earlier (note 24).
          I do not want to trespass on his work or to attribute conclusions to him with which he
          would not necessarily agree, but he has been attempting to address the spiritual context
          of Sánchez Cotán's work in terms of the period of preparation which he was undergoing to
          enter the Carthusian order. Paintings such as Sánchez Cotán's celebrated <title>Still Life
            with Quince</title>, <title>Cabbage</title>, <title>Melon and Cucumber</title> are
          striking because they share with Velázquez and other painters of the Spanish school, and I
          would argue, with Cervantes, the ability to give humble, everyday objects an aura of
          profound spirituality. </p>

        <p> Now there might be a temptation to say that Sánchez Cotán's cabbages are the painterly
          equivalent of Lazarillo's bread -regarded as holy because so rare and so eagerly sought
          after. I would not be inclined to take such a view, but would prefer to see these
          paintings as expressions of a common intention at this period to illuminate the spiritual
          dimension of the most lowly person or object. <note n="29"><bibl>B.W. Ife, 'General
              Introduction' to Miguel de Cervantes, <title>Exemplary Novels</title>, 4 vols
              (Warminster: Aris and Phillips), 1992</bibl> : 'the purpose of mixing genres lies in
            the potential to show the spiritual truth which underlies the commonplace
            exterior...like Velázquez, Cervantes imbues the tawdry and the down-at-heel with beauty
            and nobility, and shows the human spirit triumphantly at odds with its surroundings' (p.
            xiii).</note> The fact that Sánchez Cotán uses vegetables, almost to the exclusion of
          other foodstuffs, except, significantly, partridges and other game birds, may be explained
          by the Carthusian commitment to vegetarianism in the life of their order. </p>

        <p> Bob Goodwin's readings in the history and iconography of Carthusianism, and particularly
            <bibl>Juan de Madariaga's <title>Vida del seráfico padre San Bruno, patriarca de la
              Cartuja</title>, published in 1596</bibl>, reveal a range of fascinating
          justifications for the order having formally prohibited eating meat, except in extremely
          rare cases where the only food available is meat, and to refuse to eat it would result in
          starvation. A number of these justifications, interestingly, are based on dietary rather
          than moral considerations, and are backed up with references to medical textbooks: meat is
          not essential for health, fish and vegetables provide adequate sustenance, and meat will
          do positive harm, as is borne out by lay men who become ill after returning to eating meat
          after Lent. Madariaga goes on to give numerous examples of miraculous interventions to
          prevent the eating of meat, including the miracle of Saint Hugo (of which Zurbarán painted
          a version for the Charterhouse at Seville), and two stories of miracles in which
          Carthusian monks on the verge of eating partridges are saved from doing so when the
          roasted birds are either miraculously restored to life or turned into fish. </p>

        <p> What I am suggesting is that we may have here an example of a culture collaborating to
          convert a negative concept into a positive one. The Carthusian agenda, as expressed
          pictorially by Sánchez Cotán, is effectively an exercise in redefinition. A society which
          finds it difficult to feed its population can use a number of expedients: it can import
          more food, or it can export the hungry, or it can attempt to make people feel more
          satisfied with what little they have, it can try to turn lack into a positive value.
          Instead of associating underprovision with 'hunger', 'starvation', or 'malnourishment',
          all concepts with a negative value, that society might try to replace these concepts with
          more positive ones, such as 'abstinence' and the whole range of spiritual, religious and
          cultural values associated with abstinence: flight from the world, evasion of the carnal,
          pursuit of a higher form of reality or a world of the spirit. Sánchez Cotán may have
          little in his larder but a cardoon or a slice of melon, but he can turn them into a feast
          for the eye and a spiritual banquet in which the world of the flesh is cast off and left
          behind. It is an artistic counterpart to the miracle of the loaves and the fishes. </p>

        <p> Something of the same could be said of Don Quixote and his value systems; he is not
          hungry, he is merely 'delicado'. Beaten, starved and deprived of sleep, he enters a world
          of the imagination, a world of <foreign>ingeniosidad</foreign>, in which physical
          impediments become less and less important. As a result, he is able to draw strength from
          abstinence. When Sancho can find nothing better than bread, cheese and an onion in his
          saddlebag, Don Quixote reassures him that 'es honra de los caballeros andantes no comer en
          un mes, y, ya que coman, sea de aquello que hallaren más a mano' (I.10.117). Later, as he
          is about to embark on his penitence in the sierra, Sancho asks him what he is going to do
          for food. 'No te dé pena ese cuidado...porque aunque tuviera, no comiera otra cosa que las
          yerbas y frutos que este prado y estos árboles me dieren, que la fineza de mi negocio está
          en no comer y en hacer otras asperezas equivalentes' (I.25.289). As Arthur Terry comments,
          'the vocation of knight errant is essentially an ascetic calling and, in its context,
          privation is a virtue.'30 <note n="30"><bibl>Terry, 'Consuming interest',
          58</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="6">
        <head>VI</head>

        <p> In summary, then, I would suggest that our focus on food in some texts and some
          paintings from the Spanish Golden Age has shown that we are in fact looking at a complex
          set of cultural responses to a fundamentally negative economic reality; an attempt, so to
          speak, to make virtues out of necessity. </p>

        <p> To take this approach is not to read <title>Don Quijote</title>, or the picaresque
          novels, or the paintings of Sánchez Cotán as historical documents in the conventional
          sense, but to see them as texts and objects that were created in a context which has
          become historical with the passage of time, and to see them as standing in some
          relationship with that context, a relationship which itself has become more complex with
          the passage of time. </p>

        <p> In trying to understand that context and that relationship we are responding to a marked
          shift in the late 20th century away from a view of cultural objects as self-contained and
          eternal, things which dropped to earth like meteorites. We are even moving beyond
          postmodernism to a new kind of historicism, broader still than the so-called New
          Historicism of Stephen Greenblatt and Louis Montrose. We are trying to bring together a
          range of cultural and historical disciplines -anthropology, history, economics, art
          history and literary criticism- in order to illuminate the many complexities of that most
          fascinating and intriguing period of intellectual and artistic endeavour which is
          early-modern Spain. </p>
      </div>


    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
