<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd" >
<TEI.2 id="tp004">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Historical And Social Context (tp004)</title>
        <author>
          <name type="foreName">B W</name>
          <name type="surname">Ife</name>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>King's College London</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Article by B W Ife</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>At a critical point in his short story <title>La española inglesa</title>, Cervantes has
          to repatriate the heroine Isabela from London to Seville. Writers of romance
          conventionally handled journeys of this kind by supernatural means or by an authorial
          stroke of the pen. But Isabela would be taking with her a dowry of 10,000
          <foreign>escudos</foreign>, and England and Spain were at war: how was she going to get
          home with the fortune intact? Interested readers can consult the text to see exactly how
          it was done, but the solution is a masterpiece of early modern capitalism involving a
          network of French merchant-bankers acting on commission: one in London to take care of the
          cash and arrange the transfer; another to issue the documents in Paris to throw the
          authorities off the scent; and another to cash the cheque once Isabel arrives back in
          Seville.</p>

        <p>This mixture of high romance and precise documentary detail is a trademark of Cervantes,
          and one of the reasons why it is important to try and understand, four centuries later,
          the relationship between his work and the world in which he lived. Although it is
          impossible to overstate the dangers of extrapolating biography from fiction, it is safe to
          say that few writers of the early modern period travelled as extensively as Cervantes did,
          or turned their hands to so many occupations, or knew as much as he did about their
          contemporary world; and he put more of that knowledge into his work than most. </p>

        <p>Born in 1547 in Alcalá de Henares to a poor professional family, Cervantes was largely
          self-taught; he studied for a while in Seville and Madrid, but most of his learning came
          from wide and -by his own admission- indiscriminate reading. In 1569, he left Madrid for
          Italy, and entered the service of Giulio Acquaviva before enlisting in the Spanish army.
          He fought under Don John of Austria in the great Christian victory over the Turks at
          Lepanto in 1571, and lost his left hand, an injury of which he was inordinately proud,
          'since it was collected in the greatest and most memorable event that past centuries have
          ever seen'. Other military operations followed, in Corfu, Navarino and Tunis, and during
          his return journey to Spain in 1575, he was captured at sea by Turkish corsairs and taken
          to Algiers. There he spent five years in captivity before being redeemed by the payment of
          a ransom in 1580. Cervantes's experiences of military life in Italy, and more especially
          of prison life in north Africa, colour a great deal of his writing, and, in particular,
          several of the <title>Novelas ejemplares</title>.</p>

        <p>Back in Spain, Cervantes found the life of an ex-serviceman frustrating and
          disappointing, and his attempts to build a literary career met with little success in the
          early years. An unhappy marriage to a much younger girl and continued financial
          difficulties forced him to take a series of poorly-paid public posts, including
          tax-collecting and provisioning for the Armada (1588). In 1590 he made the first of two
          unsuccessful applications for a post in America. During these years Cervantes travelled
          widely and gained a considerable knowledge of rural Spain, knowledge displayed most
          obviously in <title>Don Quijote</title>, but he was accused of fraudulent accounting and
          spent at least two periods of time in prison in Seville. There he learned a great deal
          about organised crime and the Seville underworld, including <foreign>germanía</foreign>,
          the language of criminals featured in <title>Rinconete y Cortadillo</title>.</p>

        <p>In 1605 Cervantes, now settled in Valladolid, published Part I of <title>Don
          Quijote</title>. Although the work brought few financial rewards, it was well received in
          some circles and earned him a place on the fringes of the literary establishment there,
          and later in Madrid. The last four years of his life saw the culmination of his literary
          career: the <title>Novelas ejemplares</title> (1613) were followed by a long allegorical
          poem, the <title>Viaje del Parnaso</title> (1614); the following year brought Part II of
            <title>Don Quijote</title> and the <title>Ocho comedias y ocho entremeses</title>. His
          great epic novel <title>Los trabajos de Persiles y Sigismunda</title> was published
          posthumously in 1617.</p>

        <p>Cervantes's career -from soldier to tax-gatherer, from unpromising writer to literary
          celebrity-makes a historicist approach to his work particularly appropriate. Reputation
          has transformed the historical Cervantes into a universal genius, independent of time or
          place; yet the very work which made his name, <title>Don Quijote</title>, is not only
          profoundly steeped in the social and economic reality of Habsburg Spain, but has
          anachronism as its central theme. So we have two leaps of the historical imagination to
          make if we want to place Cervantes in context: back to the sixteenth and early seventeenth
          centuries, to the reigns of Philip II and Philip III; and then beyond that to the late
          medieval world of knight errantry which Don Quixote was so keen to revive. <title>Don
            Quijote</title> telescopes together nearly 150 years of Spanish history, and unless we
          adjust our sights accordingly, we are likely to misread the complex relationships between
          past and present which are a central theme of Cervantes's fiction.</p>

        <p>When Don Quixote first rode out onto the plains of La Mancha, the rural landscape he
          encountered would have seemed reassuringly familiar. The windmills, the flocks of sheep
          and the fulling mills testified to the long-standing importance of agriculture in general
          and the wool industry in particular in the Spanish economy and way of life. The country
          roads and wayside inns which populate the novel, and the drovers and the goatherds that
          frequent them, would hardly have struck the contemporary reader as worthy of comment. Yet
          this was a world which was experiencing profound social, political and economic change;
          change to which Don Quixote was largely oblivious, but from which he could not remain
          unscathed.</p>

        <p>La Mancha lay at the heart of one of greatest empires the world has ever seen. In a
          little over 100 years Spain had undergone an astonishing transformation from a collection
          of intermittently warring kingdoms to become an emerging nation state, and had then
          rapidly gone on to acquire a world-wide empire. It is vital to understand the outlines of
          this process because the long-term consequences for Spaniards at all levels of society
          were both profound and far-reaching, and because it is important to dispel some myths
          about Spain and Empire, particularly those which detect in, or read back into, the events
          of the long sixteenth century a conscious strategy for world domination by a unified
          political machine. Throughout the early modern period, what we think of as (and for
          convenience will continue to call) 'Spain' had very little constitutional basis: both as
          'nation' and 'empire', Spain was never more than a composite monarchy, an association of
          autonomous realms united only by what they had in common: a single monarch. At its most
          extensive, this global <foreign>monarquía</foreign> had as many as seventeen constituent
          parts, and like all federal or quasi-federal structures (such as the United States of
          America, the European Union, or Spain since Franco) it was as diverse as it was
          homogeneous. Time and again in the development of Spain and empire we see the laws of
          serendipity and unintended outcomes prevailing over those of historical inevitability.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>II</head>

        <p>The emergence of Spain as a world power in the sixteenth century can be understood in
          terms of two major cycles of growth and development characterised by a small number of
          recurring issues: how to balance political unity with cultural diversity; assert crown
          authority while working constructively with powerful elites; maintain and defend the
          growing number of territories within the monarchy; discharge responsibilities for
          defending the Catholic faith; and meet the growing costs of operating on an international
          stage.</p>

        <p>The first of these two cycles begins with the so-called 'union of the crowns', initiated
          by the marriage of Isabel, step-sister of Henry IV of Castile, to Ferdinand, son of John
          II of Aragon, in 1469. Although this marriage created the potential to unite two of the
          major powers in the Iberian peninsula, the potential was not realised without several
          years of struggle, in which Isabel's determination and Ferdinand's strategic and
          diplomatic skills were forged into an outstanding partnership. On the Castilian side,
          Isabel's claim to succeed her half-brother Henry would not normally have taken precedence
          over that of his daughter, Joanna. But it was widely rumoured that Henry was impotent and
          Joanna was illegitimate. Henry's sudden death in 1474 precipitated a succession crisis and
          civil war which was resolved in Isabel's favour in 1479. It was during the struggles of
          the 1470s that Isabel laid the unassailable foundations of the power base on which she and
          her successors would build. On the Aragonese side, the political landscape was dominated
          by a long-term dispute with France and civil war in Catalonia. Ferdinand's marriage to a
          Castilian had therefore been seen as an effective alliance against the French.</p>

        <p>The first ten years of their marriage were a testing time for both Ferdinand and Isabel,
          but when Ferdinand succeeded his father in 1479, two of the four major power blocks of the
          Iberian peninsula had begun to forge a stable alliance bordering on union. But this
          'union' was both provisional and conditional. The two crowns were united only by virtue of
          the marriage and only for its duration: the terms of the marriage contract preserved the
          independence of both parties and their respective territories.<note n="1">This provision
            was designed to ensure that the property of the partner who died first could not be
            alienated by the surviving spouse. Similar provisions are found in the contracts of
            other dynastic marriages, such as that of Mary Tudor and Prince Philip, later Philip II
            of Spain; and they are increasingly used in modern pre-nuptial agreements</note>
          Furthermore, Castile and Aragon were unequal partners: Castile was much the larger
          territory in geographical terms, and enjoyed numerically superior human and economic
          resources. The constituent kingdoms had been moulded into a much more unitary state than
          Aragon, and a more absolutist style of monarchy had been developed. Aragon was physically
          and economically less powerful, but had possessions in the Mediterranean (Majorca,
          Minorca, Ibiza, Sardinia, Sicily and, from 1504, Naples), and was still a federation of
          distinct kingdoms or principalities (Aragon, Catalonia and Valencia) under a single
          monarch who governed by consent rather than by absolute right. The kingdoms in the
          Aragonese federation were all fiercely loyal to different systems of local government and
          different sets of rights and privileges, all of which the monarch was required to respect
          as a condition of allegiance.</p>

        <p>Once the foundations of the union had been laid, the second phase of the reign, to the
          early 1490s, was concerned with consolidation and development. One of the most frequently
          debated questions about the reign of Ferdinand and Isabel concerns unification: did they
          set out to unify the peninsula, and in either case, did they succeed? There is no evidence
          that they pursued a conscious policy of unification, but it might be argued that, if they
          had, their principal policies would have been the same. The territories over which they
          had only recently consolidated control were diverse in every conceivable way, and
          Ferdinand and Isabel had none of the structures and resources -army, exchequer,
          administration- which would normally be considered necessary for unitary rule; the Council
          of the Inquisition was the only body with a unified responsibility for an aspect of the
          affairs of both kingdoms.</p>

        <p>It is hardly surprising that the monarchs made no effort to harmonise the many systems of
          local government, taxation, currency, or internal trade conventions, which made such a
          varied patchwork across the peninsula.<note n="2">Internal customs posts appear frequently
            in Cervantes's fiction. When the protagonists of <title>Rinconete y Cortadillo</title>
            arrive in Seville, the party they are travelling with is stopped at the Custom-house
            Gate (La Puerta de la Aduana) for payment of import duty on the goods they are
          carrying.</note> They appear instead to have concentrated on a few major, interrelated
          themes: enforcing law and order; restructuring relations between the crown and the local
          elites; reinforcing the power of the church; securing the territorial integrity of the
          peninsula; and developing the structures and systems needed to deliver these. It was an
          ambitious agenda designed to assert the authority of the crown, secure popularity with the
          people, promote a common ideology and harness the military power of the nobility by giving
          them something useful to do.</p>

        <p>The re-establishment of law and order was long overdue. The peninsula had been dominated
          by military conflict for several centuries, the frontier culture was a violent one, and
          internal security had rarely been strong. Powerful local elites were able to capitalise on
          the general feeling of insecurity both in the towns and the countryside. The civil wars of
          the 1470s had not helped this situation. It was therefore essential that Ferdinand and
          Isabel act quickly to restore the confidence of the common people in a system of security
          and justice which clearly had support at the very top. By reorganising the local militias
          or <foreign>hermandades</foreign> into larger units responsible to the crown, by
          increasing the number of crown officials (<foreign>corregidores</foreign>) charged with
          maintaining a watching brief over local government, and by reforming the administration of
          justice, Isabel was able to gain popular support and curb the power of the municipalities
          and the nobles.<note n="3">The fruits of this stability are apparent in the pages of
              <title>Don Quijote</title>. Don Quixote sets out to rescue damsels and right wrongs,
            but whenever there is a fight it is Quixote who starts it; the criminals he encounters
            have been lawfully convicted and are being transported to serve their sentence; and the
            only example of banditry comes late in Part II and in the neighbourhood of Barcelona.
            Law officers and crown officials (the <foreign>alcalde</foreign> and the
              <foreign>corregidor</foreign>) are ever-present in the pages of Spanish Golden-Age
            literature, and when a dead man falls at Periandro's feet in <title>Persiles y
              Sigismunda</title> (Book III, chapter 4) the Santa Hermandad are at the scene of the
            crime within seconds. The sex and violence which feature in the more urban context of
            the <title>Novelas ejemplares</title> undoubtedly reflect, if not always literally, the
            more dangerous world of the larger towns and cities, but there was also a long-standing
            literary prejudice against the sophistication of town-dwellers and in favour of the
            supposedly superior moral values of country folk.</note></p>

        <p>The nobles were a particular problem. The feudal model of allegiance had never been
          strong in Spain, and the military and political power of the aristocracy was considerable.
          The image of the medieval baron living in a fortified castle on a huge estate, running a
          private army and living off tributes and taxes extorted from terrified peasants may be a
          caricature, but it is one which came close to reality in parts of late fifteenth-century
          Spain. Although Isabel had found the nobles useful while they were supporting her claim to
          the throne, once she had secured it, their habit of fighting amongst themselves, and their
          potential to act as focal points for sedition and rebellion, had to be addressed. The
          solution to this and to many other problems was one favoured by governments throughout the
          ages: war. Governments find wars useful because they distract the populace from more
          immediate problems, encourage people to sink their differences in the face of a common
          enemy, and if they end in victory, wars invariably make governments popular.</p>

        <p>The war against Granada, which was successfully concluded in January 1492, fulfilled all
          of these objectives, and more. The capture of the last remaining Muslim territory in the
          peninsula brought to an end a long period of invasion and reconquest which began in 711.
          Muslim domination once extended almost as far north as the Pyrenees, but from the early
          thirteenth century the Christian territories had begun to fight back. A relatively
          peaceful coexistence (<foreign>convivencia</foreign>) had been achieved between the
          Christian kingdoms and the Emirate, and had lasted for over two centuries. Political
          coexistence, however, had not always been matched by religious and racial tolerance.
          Whereas the advancing Muslims had been generally tolerant of Christianity, and had
          encouraged Jews to settle and practice their religion in the peninsula, the reconquering
          Christians pressed for conversion of the Jews and the Muslims living under Christian rule,
          or their expulsion. Only in Valencia and Aragon were the civil and religious customs of
          Muslims respected to any great extent. The capture of Granada gave Isabel the excuse she
          needed to impose a single religion in Castile. In 1492 all Jews were required to be
          baptised or be expelled, and within ten years the same requirement was made of the
          Muslims.</p>

        <p>Had this happened today, NATO planes would undoubtedly have been in action over southern
          Spain; but ethnic cleansing of the kind which has taken place in the former Yugoslavia in
          the 1990s was not to become policy in Spain until 1609, when Philip III decreed the
          expulsion of all descendants of former Muslims (<foreign>moriscos</foreign>).<note n="4"
            >This policy was heavily criticised by Cervantes in the episode concerning the morisco
            Ricote in <title>Don Quijote</title>, Book II, chapter 54.</note> What Isabel was trying
          to achieve in Granada was the logical consequence of a series of measures which she and
          Ferdinand had already taken to strengthen the power of the Church. Isabel had been
          concerned that, not only were there obvious signs of laxity in several areas of public
          life, such as public security, the administration of justice and the collection of taxes,
          but the Church itself was clearly corrupt and in need of reform. Many years before these
          issues surfaced in northern Europe at the time of the Reformation, Isabel perceived
          widespread ignorance, venality, absenteeism and peculation among all levels of clergy; and
          superstitious, unorthodox and near heretical beliefs among the lay people. She and
          Ferdinand set about reforming the secular clergy and the religious orders, gained control
          of ecclesiastical appointments, and introduced the Holy Office of the Inquisition in
          Castile (1478) and Aragon (1487).</p>

        <p>But the war had to be paid for, and Ferdinand and Isabel could not meet the costs
          themselves. They relied on a tax granted by the Pope (the <foreign>cruzada</foreign> or
          'crusade') and on troops and supplies from the nobles. Isabel and Ferdinand thereby
          created a powerful alliance of religious and aristocratic interests around a crusading
          ideal which helped them to achieve several military, religious and political objectives.
          First, they significantly extended their territories by annexing the third great power
          block of the peninsula (the fourth, Portugal, would have to wait until 1580). Secondly, by
          giving the nobles a bigger stake in the crown's own success, Ferdinand and Isabel began to
          build a stronger alliance with them. They rewarded service, not by payment in cash, but by
          various kinds of patronage, including grants of land in the conquered territories, and
          exemption from direct taxation, one of the most important traditional privileges granted
          in exchange for personal service.<note n="5">Don Quixote strikes a similar bargain with
            Sancho. Quixote cannot afford to pay him a wage, so in exchange for Sancho's help and
            support in achieving his objectives, Quixote promises to reward him with the
            governorship of an island. Sancho is therefore bound to stick with Quixote throughout
            the novel: if he leaves his service at any time, he gives up any chance of ever getting
            a reward.</note> The disadvantage to the crown was the opportunity cost involved: no
          money changed hands, but the crown 'bought' the services it could not afford to pay for by
          foregoing future income from the land, and from direct taxation. The arrangement also
          transferred large stretches of land into private ownership, and the prosperity which
          resulted for a number of noble families began to change the long-term relationship between
          the nobles and the crown.</p>

        <p>Thirdly, and most significantly, the completion of the reconquest enabled Isabel to
          implement a policy of forced conversion or expulsion. The ending of religious pluralism
          strengthened the position of the Church and imposed a militant, white, Christian ideology
          to which every local political and cultural interest in the peninsula was
            subordinate.<note n="6">This ideology was expressed at its most powerful in the cult of
            the novels of chivalry, originating with <title>Amadís de Gaula</title> in 1508, and
            lasting for most of the sixteenth century. The protagonists of these novels, militant
            Christian knights in the classic crusading mould to which Don Quixote aspires, were
            icons of the prevailing ideology and were frequently illustrated as such on the title
            pages.</note> This ideology was increasingly underwritten by the growing supremacy of
          Castilian as the preferred language for government and education, recognised by the
          publication of the first grammar of Spanish, and of any European vernacular language, by
          the humanist Antonio de Nebrija in 1492. Ferdinand and Isabel gave a high priority to
          education at all levels, and this enabled them to develop an administrative cadre of
            <foreign>letrados</foreign>, selected and trained on a meritocratic basis, to support
          the crown in managing the complexities of early modern statecraft.</p>

        <p>Many of the achievements outlined above were to have very significant, and unforeseen,
          long-term disadvantages: the imposition of a single religion entailed the loss of a
          significant body of creative and entrepreneurial talent among the religious minorities who
          chose exile, and created two disaffected and marginalised ethnic minorities from among the
            <foreign>moriscos</foreign> and <foreign>conversos</foreign> who remained; and the
          concentration of land ownership in a small number of powerful families brought about
          long-term structural inequalities in the distribution of wealth. But there were also many
          benefits, including the priority given to education: some twenty universities were created
          in the peninsula by the end of the sixteenth century, and Spain became one of the most
          cultured and literate societies in early modern Europe. Without that readership, the work
          of Cervantes and his contemporaries would have been inconceivable.</p>

        <p>Within months of the conclusion of the reconquest of Granada, Isabel and Ferdinand's
          reign entered its third phase prompted by an event which could not have been planned, but
          which was also the logical consequence of the policies outlined above: the 'discovery' by
          Christopher Columbus of islands in the Atlantic at approximately the longitude at which
          China and Japan were thought to be located. Isabel had agreed to permit, and partly to
          fund, a speculative voyage to investigate the feasibility of a westerly, transatlantic
          route to the Far East. As Columbus made clear in the prologue to the account he presented
          to the monarchs in 1493, there were four principal objectives to the voyage: scientific,
          economic, diplomatic and religious. As far as Columbus was concerned, the 1492 voyage was
          designed to strengthen Christian alliances against Islam, facilitate the recapture of
          Jerusalem and generate sufficient income for the enterprise to pay its own way.</p>

        <p>From the moment that Columbus claimed the first small island in the Bahamas, Castile
          began to acquire extensive transatlantic possessions and Spain graduated almost overnight
          from embryonic nation state to emergent world empire.The crown and its advisors quickly
          assessed the true significance of Columbus's discoveries and staked an early territorial
          claim against the rival Portuguese. The resulting treaty of Tordesillas (1494) paved the
          way for future Spanish domination of the Caribbean, Mexico and the greater part of the
          South American continent, and by 1503 the Casa de Contratación had been established in
          Seville to regulate trade with the New World, which was soon being run as a fully-fledged
          offshore company. Seville would grow rapidly throughout the sixteenth century, fuelled by
          the trading opportunities offered by the New World. There were rich pickings to be had,
          and one fifth of all income went to the crown.</p>

        <p>The discovery of large native populations who appeared to have no religion of their own
          gave plenty of scope for the salvation of souls. Spain had been granted sovereignty over
          the new territories by Pope Alexander VI in 1493, but this 'donation' was not without
          conditions. Ferdinand and Isabel were expected to use their sovereignty to advance the
          cause of Christianity, and in 1496, Alexander gave them the title '<title>
            <foreign>Reyes Católicos</foreign>
          </title>' (Catholic Monarchs) in recognition of their support for the Church in Granada
          and the New World. When Isabel died in 1504 she could look back on a productive reign with
          a clear conscience that she had fulfilled the duties of a Christian monarch. But the
          burdens of empire were to become much greater with the passage of time, and the
          acquisition of an overseas empire was to prove a mixed blessing.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>III</head>

        <p>The reign of the Catholic Monarchs began with a succession crisis and ended with one. On
          Isabel's death, Ferdinand remained king of Aragon, but not of Castile, to which the
          succession was problematic. Isabel and Ferdinand had arranged marriages for each of their
          four children to strengthen alliances with Portugal, England and Burgundy. But their
          efforts to secure the future of the union were frustrated when their only son John died in
          1497, his sister Isabella died the following year, and the nominated successor Joanna
          ('Juana la Loca') was judged mentally unstable and unfit to rule. When Joanna's husband,
          Philip of Burgundy, also died unexpectedly in 1506, Ferdinand became regent of Castile on
          behalf of Joanna and her infant son Charles of Ghent (born in 1500). When Ferdinand died
          in 1516, Charles acquired a three-fold inheritance: in his person the two crowns of
          Castile and Aragon were finally united, together with the reconquered territories in the
          peninsula, the Atlantic, the New World, the Mediterranean (including Naples, recaptured by
          Ferdinand from the French in 1504), and North Africa; and to these territories he also
          added the Burgundian inheritance of the Netherlands, Luxembourg and Franche Comté. When he
          was elected Holy Roman Emperor in 1519, the same year in which the first Spaniards reached
          Mexico, a fourth group of territories were added to the monarchy: the Habsburg lands in
          Germany, Poland, Austria and Hungary. Within a three-year period, King Charles I of Spain
          -the Emperor Charles V- became the most powerful man the world had ever seen.</p>

        <p>Charles's accession established the Habsburg dynasty in Spain and ushered in the second
          great cycle of development for Spain and the empire. In many ways, this second cycle
          replays on a grander scale the central themes of the first. Like the Catholic Monarchs,
          the Habsburg kings of Spain had to grapple with problems of imposing and maintaining their
          authority on a politically diverse and geographically widespread collection of
          territories; they had to defend the territorial integrity of the empire; they took very
          seriously their responsibilities as defenders of the Christian faith; and they needed to
          raise large sums of money to do so. Charles adopted many of the solutions devised by the
          Catholic Monarchs -he became a skilful diplomat, travelled a great deal, led from the
          front and imposed his authority through the power of his personality while keeping the
          powerful elites on his side. But initially he had a number of disadvantages: he was a
          foreigner, a French-speaking Fleming, and he got off to a bad start by sidelining native
          Spaniards and appointing Burgundians to senior positions, while giving the impression that
          he intended to strip the assets of Castile and Aragon to fund his imperial ambitions.</p>

        <p>The early years of Charles's reign were marked by suspicion and resentment which boiled
          over in a series of revolts by the <foreign>comuneros</foreign> and the
          <foreign>germanía</foreign> (1520-1521). In Castile, a number of towns experienced serious
          disturbances fuelled by resentment at the conspicuous presence of Burgundians in
          influential positions, the King's hasty departure from Spain on imperial business, and
          various long-standing complaints about the privileges of the aristocracy. In Valencia, the
          grievances were against the Muslims as well as the nobles. Both revolts had the effect of
          rallying the nobles in support of the royal cause, and were quickly suppressed. The rebels
          had made their point, nevertheless, and Charles spent most of the 1520s making amends for
          his high-handedness and for having taken the Spaniards and the regional parliaments
            (<foreign>Cortes</foreign>) for granted. 1522-1529 was the longest continuous period he
          ever spent in Spain; he made sure he learned the language and understood the local
          customs, and in 1526 he contracted a popular marriage with Isabella of Portugal, who gave
          him an heir, the future Philip II, the following year. Charles had put down roots in Spain
          and won the hearts of Spaniards, and more important, their political and financial support
          in defending the faith and the territories outside the peninsula.</p>

        <p>Charles was at pains to make clear that he had no intention of extending the empire in
          Europe by conquest. But, equally, he would not contemplate surrendering territory on any
          front. There were three main troublespots: in the south and the east there was the old
          enmity with Islam, and the need to maintain naval power across the long and difficult
          frontier in the Mediterranean and North Africa, and along the Danube. Across the centre of
          the empire, and effectively dividing it in two, lay France. In the north, the greatest
          threat of all came from the rise of Protestantism. What began as a religious movement
          quickly took a political turn as secular leaders throughout northern Europe turned the
          mood of rebellion to their own advantage. Charles accepted that there was corruption and
          abuse among the clergy and the religious orders which needed to be dealt with, and
          encouraged a Catholic Counter-Reformation in response. But as the secular guardian of the
          church, the Emperor became increasingly alarmed at the political threat of the German
          princes, and the way in which perfectly justified calls for moral reform were causing
          widespread civil unrest and rebellion against the authority of the Pope. It was Charles's
          confrontation with Luther in 1521 which led him to pledge his 'kingdoms, dominions and
          friends, body and blood, soul and life' in defence of Christendom. With that pledge he
          committed Spain and the Spaniards to more than a century of conflict throughout Europe and
          the Mediterranean, and with it vast amounts of resource, both human and financial.</p>

        <p>Charles was in a better position than Ferdinand and Isabel had been to afford a religious
          war on such a scale, but the cost to Castile in particular was high. Imperial armies
          depended on Spanish manpower and military expertise, but they had to be paid and the
          Emperor had increasing recourse to the <foreign>cruzada</foreign>, to general taxation,
          and to international sources of capital. The nobles were exempt from direct taxation, and
          constant recourse to grants and taxes to meet imperial commitments made the tax system
          more and more regressive as the burden fell increasingly on those least able to pay.
          Charles's greatest asset, however, was the ability to raise loans. By the early 1530s,
          when imports of silver bullion began to flow in large quantities, it was becoming clear
          that the economic potential of America was enormous. But the impact on Spain proved much
          less favourable than it might have been, and on balance was sharply negative.</p>

        <p>Charles could raise large loans from German and Italian bankers to fight his wars in
          Europe because he could use imported silver from Peru as collateral. As a result, income
          was mortgaged for years in advance, and when the loans could not be paid, the crown was
          regularly bankrupt. Far from being a benefit to Spain, America proved a triumph for
          international venture capitalism: for the Genoese who underwrote much of the cost of the
          discoveries and then cashed in on the trading opportunities, and for the Italian and
          German bankers who saw Charles, and later Philip, struggling to hold back an unstoppable
          tide of social change by throwing huge sums of money at it, and were happy to feed their
          habit because their credit was good. Vast quantities of money flowed into the royal
          exchequer from America, but none of it stuck, and the Spaniards became net contributors to
          the cost of sustaining the empire.</p>

        <p>The struggle to maintain control over such a large and turbulent empire eventually began
          to take its toll. Quite apart from the effort of securing the empire on several fronts in
          Europe, Charles also had to contend with a range of other important issues. The bad press
          which Spain was receiving about the conquests in South America and the abuse of the native
          populations by the conquerors and settlers, led to a high-profile enquiry into the
          legitimacy of conquest and brought about changes in the law governing the rights of
          Indians and the responsibilities of settlers. The growing pressure for reform of the
          church from within the Catholic sector, coupled with the increasing incidence of heretical
          belief was met by higher levels of activity from the Inquisition, tougher censorship, and
          the final suppression of Islam in Aragon in 1526. And the need to ensure that adequate
          systems of government were in place in Spain during his frequent absences abroad brought
          about an extension of the system of councils -early examples of modern government
          departments- and placed more power in the hands of the civil servants. By the 1550s
          Charles had concluded that his vast multinational conglomerate was too large to be
          manageable and he planned a phased abdication and demerger: he split the empire into two
          parts, handed on the original Holy Roman Empire inherited from the Austrian Habsburgs to
          his brother Ferdinand, and left the Castilian, Aragonese and Burgundian inheritances to
          his son Philip. Charles himself retired to a monastery at Yuste, in Extremadura.</p>

        <p>The accession of Philip II in 1556 brought about a change of style but not of substance.
          Philip had been groomed to be king from an early age, and he regarded being king as a job
          to be taken seriously. He learned the lessons of his father's reign and was determined
          that he would not spend his life travelling from pillar to post. He established a capital
          in Madrid, built a headquarters at the Escorial and ran the empire from a tiny office with
          the help of a small group of trusted advisors. Where his father had been a general, he
          preferred the role of chief executive. On the domestic front, Philip remained unswervingly
          loyal to the Catholic cause, and cracked down even more strictly on the merest suspicion
          of unorthodoxy, using a range of repressive measures -the Inquisition and the
            <foreign>auto de fe</foreign>, the index of prohibited books and a ban on Spaniards
          studying abroad- to reinforce the prevailing orthodoxy. In the 1560s he decided that he
          needed to intensify the assimilation of the moriscos and reduce the security threat posed
          by a substantial ethnic minority in the east and south of the peninsula. In the face of a
          series of prohibitions against speaking Arabic, reading Arabic literature, and wearing
          traditional dress, the <foreign>moriscos</foreign> rebelled in 1568 and after a savage
          two-year conflict, the rebellion was crushed and the <foreign>moriscos</foreign> were
          forcibly dispersed throughout the peninsula.</p>

        <p>Philip's regime was more centralist, more absolutist and more repressive than his
          father's, but the major foreign policy issues remained unchanged, and there was no let-up
          in the associated cost. Charles's division of the empire no doubt made good sense, but it
          left Philip two principal hot- spots to deal with: the on-going Islamic threat in the
          Mediterranean and the political and religious conflict in the Netherlands. Fighting on
          both these fronts continued to be ruinously expensive, and proved impossible to direct
          from an office in central Castile. Even a defensive policy in the Mediterranean needed a
          large, well-equipped navy. The Spanish fleet scored a number of successes in the 1560s in
          defence of Oran and Malta, and in the 1570s as part of the Holy League with Italy in
          defence of Cyprus. In 1571, at Lepanto, off the coast of Greece, the combined Christian
          fleet under the command of Philip's half-brother, Don John of Austria, inflicted a
          decisive defeat on the Turkish fleet, the battle in which Cervantes took part and in which
          he took such pride. But Philip's efforts to defend Spanish possessions in North Africa and
          in the Mediterranean were compromised by the need to deal simultaneously with a serious
          revolt in the Netherlands.</p>

        <p>Unrest in the Netherlands was brought about by a cocktail of interrelated factors:
          resentment that the political centre of gravity of the empire had shifted to Spain; the
          virulence of the local brand of protestant religious thought (Calvinism); separatist
          movements in the northern provinces led by William of Orange; and Spanish
          heavy-handedness, including a conspicuous military presence and unsubtle attempts to gain
          control of local affairs. Had Philip spent more time in the area he might have been able
          to respond more sensitively to the changing mood. But after Calvinists rioted and
          desecrated Catholic churches in 1566, Philip sent the Duke of Alba to investigate. Alba
          sentenced more than a thousand people to death and imposed a draconian tax to pay for the
          army. By the early 1570s, virtually the whole of the Netherlands was in revolt, supported
          by protestant allies in Germany, France and England.</p>

        <p>In 1585, England signed a treaty agreeing to aid the rebels, and Philip decided that,
          unless he could stop English involvement, he would never recapture the United Provinces.
          The result was the attempted attack on London by the 'Invincible Armada' in 1588. The
          invasion was doomed to failure by lack of surprise, poor communication between the navy in
          the English Channel and the army in Flanders, bad weather and the fact that the
          commander-in-chief was directing operations from Madrid. The failure of the Armada cost
          hundreds of lives, was a massive waste of money, and caused a serious loss of confidence
          among Spaniards. Philip's reputation never fully recovered. The debacle was widely
          interpreted as a punishment for over-weaning pride. In fact it was a classic case of
          over-commitment on too many fronts, but there is no evidence that the lessons were learned
          in Philip's lifetime. He went on taxing and borrowing, and when he died in 1598, the crown
          was in debt for eight times its annual revenue.</p>

        <p>The Netherlands were an insoluble problem, but Philip's decisive annexation of Portugal
          in 1580 finally brought the whole peninsula within a single monarchy, and added another
          overseas empire (Brazil, parts of Africa, India and the far east) to the growing extent of
          Spain's possessions in the New World. Philip III succeeded his father in 1598, and the
          turn of the century brought mixed fortunes; Spanish influence on the world stage had never
          been greater, but the mood at home was more sombre. A serious outbreak of plague weakened
          an already overstretched populace and a bout of national introspection gave rise to a
          wide-ranging review of international strategy. The new regime moved quickly to address the
          balance of payments crisis by concluding treaties and cease-fire agreements with England
          and the United Provinces, and by trying to control the import of manufactured luxury goods
          such as textiles.</p>

        <p>Philip III has often been perceived as a weak king, largely because he delegated much of
          his executive authority to a 'favourite' or first minister, the Duke of Lerma, and
          dedicated himself to more regal pursuits such as hunting and collecting works of art.
          Lerma was undoubtedly the wrong choice in the long term: his most serious error of
          judgment came with the expulsion of the moriscos in 1609, and over time he allowed power
          to corrupt him absolutely. But Philip's decision to share the burdens of office with a
          first minister was sensible, and Lerma's initial assessment of the problem was undoubtedly
          correct: Spain was over-committed and under-resourced for the role it was attempting to
          play, and a period of retrenchment was essential if the structural weaknesses in the
          Spanish economy were ever to be corrected.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>IV</head>

        <p>All forms of historical narrative are misleading, and in the case of Spain and the empire
          the risks are particularly great. A narrative of growth, overreach and exhaustion can
          easily become, as it did for the Spaniards of Cervantes's time, a providentialist account
          in which pride goes before a fall. Yet the process by which the empire, particularly the
          empire in Europe, grew by leaps and bounds with each successive generation, was as much
          the result of accident as design. The union of the crowns of Castile and Aragon was only
          one of a number of possible outcomes from the turbulence of the 1470s, and Charles's
          succession in 1516 was an endgame which few could have foreseen when Isabel died over a
          decade earlier. Even Charles's attempt to downsize the unruly empire in the 1550s was
          thwarted by Philip's decisive assertion of his claim to the throne of Portugal in 1580.
          And all the while, the astonishing extent of the discoveries in the New World regularly
          added thousands upon thousands of square kilometres to the sum of Spanish possessions -and
          of Spanish responsibilities- overseas. But it would be foolish to ignore the recurring
          themes which dominate the successive cycles of growth and development, and which help to
          explain the social complexity of Spain at the turn of the seventeenth century: the gradual
          but inexorable emergence of an absolutist monarchy and a normative culture; the changing
          dynamic between the crown and the other power bases within society, particularly the
          nobility, the church and the urban elites; the importance of religion as an ideological
          driver; and the role of America in sustaining imperial ambitions abroad and widening the
          wealth gap at home.</p>

        <p>Although in many ways Spain at the end of the sixteenth century was more cohesive, both
          in concept and reality, than it had been a century earlier, the Spaniards then, as now,
          defined themselves in terms of a range of distinctions: differences of region, class,
          wealth, ethnicity, religion, culture, language and sex. Distinctions of these kinds are
          inherent in all societies, but what makes them particularly important in early modern
          Spain was the shifting nature of certain established correlations, especially changes in
          the distribution of wealth, the relationship between wealth and rank, and the balance of
          religion, ethnicity and culture.</p>

        <p>Wealth is the key to understanding these changes and divisions. Taken as a whole, Spain
          was an extremely prosperous country in the early modern period, but the gap between the
          rich and the poor grew steadily wider throughout the sixteenth century. At the same time,
          the traditional correlation between social class and economic circumstances came under
          significant strain. New routes to wealth were open to all classes and ethnic groups, and
          no class was immune from poverty. The result was to reverse the polarity between wealth
          and status: where once membership of the ruling class would almost inevitably bring
          prosperity, in the changing circumstances, wealth was increasingly used to buy rank. There
          were three major factors driving these changes: demographic stability and growth, major
          shifts in land use and tenure, and the new commercial opportunities offered by the New
          World. </p>

        <p>With very few exceptions (the revolts of the <foreign>comuneros</foreign> and the
            <foreign>germanía</foreign> in the early 1520s, and the rebellion of the
            <foreign>moriscos</foreign> in the 1560s) Spaniards enjoyed over a century of peace and
          stability within the peninsula itself. By exporting military conflict to America and other
          parts of Europe, the conditions were created for sustained net growth of the population
          until well into the 1580s. This growth was not uniform, however, and some significant
          changes took place in its shape and distribution. Emigration caused by forced expulsions,
          the demands of conquest and colonisation in America, and wars in Europe was balanced by
          the immigration of Catholic refugees from the religious wars and merchants attracted by
          the investment potential of New World trade. The outflow of able-bodied men opened the way
          for women of all classes to take a more active role in society, a significant social
          change which is reflected in the prominence given to women in Cervantes's fiction and on
          the contemporary stage. At the same time, there was a pronounced shift in the economic
          centre of gravity of the peninsula from north to south, and from the countryside to the
          towns. Both trends account for the emergence of Seville as a major commercial and cultural
          centre during the sixteenth century, a role reflected in several of Cervantes's
            <title>Novelas ejemplares</title>.<note n="7"><title>Rinconete y Cortadillo</title>,
              <title>La española inglesa</title>, <title>El celoso extremeño</title>, <title>La
              ilustre fregona</title>.</note></p>

        <p>The Spanish economy depended on agriculture, and the political stability and population
          growth of the sixteenth century favoured both livestock and farming. Sheep farming was
          particularly successful. The mountainous terrain of much of the country made sheep and
          goats the only viable industry, the fine wool of the merino sheep fetched good prices
          among weavers in northern Europe, keeping sheep was not labour- or capital-intensive, and
          it was compatible with the long-standing aversion of the upper classes to manual labour.
          Sheep farming was also extremely well organised by a powerful guild, the Mesta, which
          enjoyed political support from the crown. Despite growing competition from silk and
          cotton, wool continued to be a major industry throughout the sixteenth century, and would
          undoubtedly have made a greater contribution to the economy had the domestic textile
          industry been developed in parallel. As it was, the export of wool did not cover the cost
          of importing finished cloth, of which Spain was a net importer.</p>

        <p>Farming also flourished in response to stability and growth, and large amounts of
          additional land were brought into cultivation. The reluctance of emigrants to the New
          World to adjust to local conditions and diet created a strong export market for
          foodstuffs, wine and olive oil, as well as manufacted goods, and Spain remained a net
          importer of food. With favourable political and economic conditions and wealth of natural
          resources, Spain could have done a good deal better had more American silver been used for
          investment and less for conspicuous consumption. Nevertheless, it was possible to make a
          good living from farming and many people did. We have only to look beyond the surface
          rural poverty of <title>Don Quijote</title> to see how many prosperous gentlemen farmers
          there are in the subtext. Note, for example, the precision with which Cervantes fills in
          the family background of Grisóstomo and Marcela, the two protagonists of the pastoral
          episode in Book I, chapters 11-14, both of whom have inherited wealth from parents who
          worked hard and did well from farming.<note n="8">There are other examples, such as Don
            Diego de Miranda (Book II, chapter 18), another gentleman farmer, who worries because
            his son writes poetry in Castilian rather than Latin or Greek, or Camacho, the 'labrador
            rico' whose wedding is spoiled by the theft of his bride in Book II, chapters 20-22, but
            has the consolation of knowing that his wealth will soon attract another girl.</note></p>

        <p>But the real beneficiaries of a strong agricultural economy were the large
            landowners.<note n="9">This category applies to large corporations, including the church
            and the orders of chivalry, as well as to private individuals.</note> Land is a finite
          resource, and a primary source and repository of wealth. We have already seen how the
          Catholic Monarchs bought political and military service from the nobles by making grants
          of land and associated income in conquered territories, and this process continued in
          different forms under the Habsburg kings, with large areas of crown lands being granted to
          a rapidly growing aristocracy, or sold into private ownership to raise capital for
          military expenditure. Many of these disposals were of <foreign>baldíos</foreign>, crown
          lands in common use, and the privatisation of ownership often brought severe hardship to
          common people whose traditional rights of access and use were denied. As more land was
          granted or purchased, large estates were accumulated by families who took legal steps to
          ensure that they could not be alienated and would be transferred intact to subsequent
            generations.<note n="10">The legal instrument was called <foreign>mayorazgo</foreign>,
            and provided for succession to the eldest son (primogeniture) as opposed to the more
            traditional model of equal inheritance by all children, male or female.</note> The 'land
          grab' by the Spanish nobility in the sixteenth century undoubtedly helps to explain the
          growing obsession with lineage, the association of identity with place, and the importance
          given to legitimate, patrilineal, succession and the sexual integrity of women: rich,
          powerful men do not want their carefully accumulated assets accidentally transferred to
          another man's son.</p>

        <p>The benefits of land ownership were also open to members of other classes, including
          those on both sides of the Atlantic who got rich from trade.<note n="11">Carrizales, the
            protagonist of <title>El celoso extremeño</title> is a prime example of the
              <foreign>indiano</foreign>, the emigrant who makes his fortune in the New World and
            returns home to Spain, in this case to find a wife to give him an heir.</note> There was
          no monopoly of class or ethnic group, and the aristocracy, the urban middle classes and
          the <foreign>conversos</foreign> were all represented among the successful merchant class.
          Large fortunes were made from American bullion: for every 20% that went to the crown, 80%
          went into private pockets and ultimately had to be banked, invested or traded for another
          asset. Many of the 'new rich' preferred to invest in status rather than trade or industry.
          A crown which was desperate for cash was more than willing to sell patents of nobility,
          with the associated tax-exempt status, in exchange for large, up-front contributions to
          the imperial revenue account. The emergence of a 'new rich' concentrated in the southern
          half of the peninsula and including descendants of religious minorities caused
          considerable concern among the nobility and gentry of Old Castile, many of whom had missed
          out on the prosperity brought by reconquest at home and conquest abroad. In the face of
          influential new money, the old Christian ruling classes closed ranks and hit back with the
          one thing money cannot buy: blood.<note n="12">The two conflicting views of status -the
              <foreign>hidalgo</foreign> versus the self-made man ( hijo de sus obras)- intersect in
            Don Quixote's discussion of Dulcinea's lineage (Book I, chapter 8) where the emphasis on
            lineage in chivalric literature conflicts with Dulcinea's parvenue status: her lineage
            is in the future rather than the past.</note></p>

        <p>Long-standing discrimination against <foreign>conversos</foreign> became
          institutionalised in Toledo during the 1540s, and took the form of statutes of
            <foreign>limpieza de sangre</foreign>, which restricted access to a wide range of
          ecclestiastical and secular posts and privileges to those who could demonstrate that their
          blood was of pure Christian origin. Philip II ratified this practice in 1556 and it came
          into common use. Purity of blood was a social and economic issue as much as a religious
          one. In practice, and over time, the importance attached to purity of blood also
          reinforced the claims of low-born old Christians to enhanced social status: a humble,
          'blue-blooded' peasant might have a greater claim to be considered honourable than a
          social superior of less immaculate racial origin. The blood factor added a further
          dimension of confusion to a social order which had already been rendered fluid by money.
          No-one could be certain which was the true indicator of status: inherited wealth, new
          money or Christian blood.<note n="13">Grisóstomo and Marcela are carefully distinguished
            in terms of social and economic rank: he is the son of a rich farmer, but described as
            an 'hijodalgo rico' and heir to a sizeable estate; she is the daughter of 'Guillermo el
            rico...un labrador aún más rico que el padre de Grisóstomo'. He appears to have greater
            rank (he is an <foreign>hidalgo</foreign>), but her father is richer, even though he is
            a peasant. Note also the family circumstances of the prospective husband and the lover
            of Feliciana de la Voz in <title>Persiles y Sigismunda</title>, Book III, chapter 3: her
            parents are 'nobles mucho más que ricos'; her lover is the son of an 'hidalgo
            riquísimo...caballero en la opinión de las gentes' and he is described as heir to an
            'hacienda infinita'; the prospective husband's family is, like her parents, more noble
            than rich and lives in 'honrada medianía'. She falls for the rich one and has his baby,
            but her father and brother eventually come to terms with the dishonour.</note></p>

        <p>But the wealth of the few was gained at the expense of the majority. For every farmer or
          merchant who made good there were many more who barely lived above subsistence level. Over
          and above the daily vicissitudes of early modern rural life -low life expectancy,
          malnourishment, disease, infant and early male mortality- the Spanish peasantry had to
          contend with two devastating consequences of imperial ambition: inflation caused by
          American bullion and the resulting excess liquidity in the European economy, and high
          taxation needed to meet the costs of religious wars abroad. Ground down by these two
          millstones, many agricultural workers deserted the countryside, flocked to the towns and
          joined the ranks of the urban poor. The lucky ones were able to scrape a hand-to-mouth
          existence from casual labour in manufacturing or service; many had recourse to begging,
          prostitution or organised crime. The urban underclass which grew up in the shadow of the
          conspicuous prosperity of early modern Spain is featured in Cervantes's short fiction, in
          the picaresque novels of the early seventeenth century, and in the visual art of painters
          like Velázquez and Murillo.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>V</head>

        <p>Cervantes was a shrewd observer of the world around him, but the literary realism which
          is such a feature of his fiction is not primarily documentary in nature. The world he
          depicts is clearly recognisable as his own, but he does not write simply to record the
          fact. Cervantes's world was complex and full of conflict, and writers of fiction need
          conflict to generate plot and character. His genius consists in allowing the
          circumstantial evidence of his own society to act as testimony to a much wider range of
          issues. This may be why readers and critics of Cervantes have found it difficult to detect
          what he really thinks about his material. Very occasionally, as in the Ricote episode of
            <title>Don Quijote</title> where he is outspoken about the expulsion of the
            <foreign>moriscos</foreign>, we can detect genuine anguish in the writing. More often,
          he comes across as a wryly detached, non-committal ironist who can see both sides of the
          question. Does he really think that Quixote is a fool, or does he secretly admire his
          misplaced idealism?</p>

        <p>Cervantes is much more an analyst and observer than a policy-maker, but he clearly had
          strong views about many of the political and social issues which preoccupied his age. He
          took a close interest in the complexities of class, wealth and status and developed many
          permutations of these themes in his work. His religious views appear to be orthodox,
          notwithstanding the occasional touch of anticlerical satire; divine providence is a
          frequent driving force behind the construction of plots in which vicissitudes turn out for
          the best and hidden truths must be revealed; and the overtly Catholic agenda of his prose
          romance <title>Persiles y Sigismunda</title> is only conceivably open to question on the
          grounds that it protests too much. Cervantes is often discreetly critical of divisiveness
          and intolerance in his own society by indirect reference to societies outside Spain:
            <title>La española inglesa</title> and <title>El amante liberal</title> are both set in
          worlds -one protestant, the other Islamic- where religious and cultural diversity is shown
          to be rather more tolerantly managed than it was within the peninsula. He was a brilliant
          observer of regional and linguistic diversity, urban life and manners, and he clearly had
          strong views about the sexual basis of the honour code.</p>

        <p>Spanish society in Cervantes's time was a complex weave of many potentially contradictory
          strands. Traditional structures were under strain: the ruling class was becoming
          increasingly segmented; the grandees were growing in number and wealth but had been
          effectively emasculated by prosperity; many of the gentry had fallen on hard times, while
          the 'new rich' were rising up to take their place. Alonso Quijano was clearly
          dysfunctional in this context. While all around him the land-owning classes were enlarging
          their estates and begetting heirs, he was allowing his estate to decline, selling off land
          to buy books which encapsulated an outworn ideology, living with his niece and
          housekeeper, unmarried and childless. And when he reinvents himself as Don Quixote in a
          desperate attempt to put the clock back to the frontier society of the fifteenth century,
          he rides out into a world in which rich farmers put their sons through university and
          Dukes and Duchesses have transformed their castles into chateaux where they pass the time
          playing effete masquerades. The old ethos of service has disappeared, along with the
          respect due to the chivalric ideal; everyone now wants to be paid -innkeepers, his squire
          Sancho, even his lady-love Dulcinea tries to touch him for the loan of six
          <foreign>reales</foreign>. </p>

        <p>Although Spain remained largely free of political and military conflict for most of
          Cervantes's lifetime, the internal boundaries between regions, languages, classes and
          castes, were all too apparent. The towns and cities, Seville above all, were a potent
          melting pot in which rich and poor, criminals and polite society, Old Christians and new,
          lived side by side. Rinconete and Cortadillo both experience the permeability of these
          boundaries and the way in which large parts of Spanish society moved to the margins. The
          world of organised crime centred on Monipodio's headquarters mimicks the self-deluding
          order of conventional respectability, but Cervantes does not treat the criminal underworld
          and polite society as worlds apart. Cervantes's characters are continually crossing
          geographical, political, cultural and religious boundaries, negotiating and testing the
          sometimes artificial distinctions between the different spheres. Preciosa (<title>La
            gitanilla</title>), Isabel (<title>La española inglesa</title>), Costanza (<title>La
            ilustre fregona</title>) are all exiled into other worlds, to be redeemed by the power
          of integrity, truth and love. It is difficult not to look for the origins of this
          recurrent narrative structure in Cervantes's own experience of captivity and redemption in
          Algiers during the late 1570s.</p>

        <p>Each of these three female characters is rescued from some form of internal or external
          exile back into their rightful place within the ruling class, but Cervantes is not foolish
          enough to believe that virtue and nobility are linked: he is merely using conventional
          measures of distinction associated with literary romance -youth, beauty, ability,
          breeding, blonde hair and a pretty dress- to indicate other more significant forms of
          distinctiveness and value. But there is one manifestation of exile which Cervantes treats
          more literally: the untouchable status of the violated woman. Cervantes clearly had no
          problem with female sexuality: his works are full of feisty women who are prepared to make
          the first move as well as those who allow themselves to be seduced and live to regret it.
          But rape is another matter, and <foreign>La fuerza de la sangre</foreign> plays out the
          vivid drama of violent sex and retributive marriage which dominated the Spanish stage for
          over fifty years. Amid all the fluidity of Spanish society, Cervantes seems to argue,
          there are some things that never change. The violated woman has no value in the sexual
          economy of the time, and she can only be redeemed by marriage to the rapist, however
          implausibly this is brought about. Once her virginity is lost, or her faithfulness
          compromised, she cannot provide that essential guarantee that a man's children are his
          own, or that his property will pass to his heir. In a society obsessed with lineage and
          with an abhorrence of miscegenation, honour and status are reduced to a simple biological
          fact: blood is the most powerful delineator of all.</p>
      </div>

      <div type="reading">

        <head>Further Reading</head>


        <bibl>James Casey, <title>Early Modern Spain. A Social History</title> (London and New York:
          Routledge, 1999).</bibl>
        <bibl>Marcelin Defourneaux (trans. Newton Branch), <title>Daily Life in Spain in the Golden
            Age</title> (Stanford, California: Stanford University Press, 1970).</bibl>
        <bibl>John Edwards, <title>The Spain of the Catholic Monarchs 1474-1520</title> (Oxford and
          Malden Mass.: Blackwell, 2000).</bibl>
        <bibl>J.H. Elliott, <title>Imperial Spain 1469-1716</title> (London: Arnold, 1963).</bibl>
        <bibl>J.H. Elliott, <title>Spain and its World, 1500-1700</title> (New Haven and London:
          Yale University Press, 1989).</bibl>
        <bibl>Carroll B. Johnson, <title>Cervantes and the Material World</title> (Urbana and
          Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 2000).</bibl>
        <bibl>Henry Kamen, <title>Spain 1469-1714. A Society of Conflict</title> (London and New
          York: Longman, 1983).</bibl>
        <bibl>John Lynch, <title>Spain 1516-1598. From National State to World Empire</title>
          (Oxford UK and Cambridge Mass.: Blackwell, 1991).</bibl>
        <bibl>John Lynch, <title>The Hispanic World in Crisis and Change 1598-1700</title> (Oxford
          UK and Cambridge Mass.: Blackwell, 1992).</bibl>




      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
