<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p2_4">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>English Woman’s Journal (1858-1864)</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-31</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>The <title>English Woman’s Journal</title></head>
                <p>The <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> was both a mid-priced miscellaneous
                    monthly magazine and the textual manifestation of a number of political and
                    social organizations. It appeared from March 1858 until August 1864, spanning
                    the period between the failed attempt to reform legislation that prevented
                    married women holding property in 1857 and the equally unsuccessful attempt to
                    win female suffrage in 1867. During this period the <title>English Woman’s
                        Journal</title> was at the forefront of both campaigns but, rather than see
                    them as separate movements, stressed that they were connected and part of a
                    wider attempt to improve the position of women in society. This breadth of
                    focus, representing diverse activities as part of the same common cause,
                    characterized both the political contents of the <title>English Woman’s
                    Journal</title> and the various other components that made up each monthly
                    issue. With its mix of literary, political and social contents as well as its
                    reports of its own related activities, the <title>English Woman’s
                    Journal</title> both published material by women, represented women as exemplars
                    in history and in the present, and demonstrated the potential for women to play
                    a full part in nineteenth-century society.</p>
                <p>Its founders, Barbara Leigh Smith (from 1857 Barbara Leigh Smith Bodichon) and
                    Bessie Rayner Parkes (from 1867 Bessie Rayner Belloc), were from from similar
                    dissenting backgrounds and both of their families were involved in radical
                    politics. Smith was the illegitimate daughter of the radical MP Benjamin Smith.
                    He ensured his daughter received an education and, on reaching her majority, a
                    portfolio of investments that secured her financial independence. Likewise,
                    Parkes’s father was the radical Joseph Parkes and her mother, Elizabeth, was the
                    granddaughter of Joseph Priestley (Shattock 2004). It was this shared
                    progressive, dissenting background that permitted the two families to meet in
                    Hastings in 1847. The girls became close friends, even embarking on an
                    unchaparoned trip across Europe in 1850 to visit some friends who were training
                    to be artists in Munich. Prior to launching the <title>English Woman’s
                    Journal</title> in 1858, both Parkes and Smith were active in various social
                    causes. In 1854 Parkes published <title>Remarks on the Instruction of Girls
                    </title>and Bodichon <title>A brief summary of the laws in England concerning
                        women</title>. Bodichon’s pamphlet was widely read and, after much lobbying
                    (for which both Parkes and Bodichon were central figures), prompted the
                    unsuccessful attempt to introduce the Married Women’s Property Act in 1857. </p>
                <p>The <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>was conceived as part of this
                    political activity, yet it operated more as a medium of intercommunication
                    rather than a campaigning publication its own right. This is partly because of
                    its disparate interests. The journal was published by the English Woman’s
                    Journal Company, a private limited company in which Smith held (via her sister)
                    the most shares. The company, and the journal it was set up to publish, had its
                    roots in a previous publication, the <title>Waverley Journal</title>. This was a
                    fortnightly newspaper, published in Edinburgh and written and published by
                    women. On a visit to Edinburgh Smith and Parkes began to contribute to the
                        <title>Waverley Journal</title>, ultimately taking it over (in what would be
                    a familiar arrangement, Smith provided the money and Parkes was the editor) in
                    May 1857. They ran the journal from London, with Hays contributing poetry. Isa
                    Craig, who Smith and Parkes had met in Edinburgh, also became a contributor when
                    she came to London to be assistant secretary for the National Association for
                    the Promotion of Social Science (NAPSS). However, the <title>Waverley
                    </title>was not conceived as an end in itself: rather, it was to be produced
                    from offices that would also double as a reading room and centre for
                    co-ordinating other activities. These were set up on Princes Street, off
                    Cavendish Square and, when negotiations to buy the <title>Waverley
                    </title>outright failed early in 1858, they decided to start again with a
                    journal of their own (Rendall, 1987).</p>
                <p>The company was registered on 13 February 1858 with £1000 capital in 200 shares.
                    Parkes and Hays took five shares each, and Maria Rye – who had been secretary of
                    the committee formed by Smith and Parkes to reform the Married Women’s Property
                    Acts in 1855 – also took one. Three men also took shares: Samuel Curtailed and
                    James Vaughan took four each; and William Cookson – who also served as chairman
                    – took five. By November 1858 the Company had expanded, with more interest from
                    various representatives of the Unitarian community (W.J. Fox, former editor and
                    proprietor of the <xref type="internal" from="p2_1"><title>Monthly Repository</title></xref> served as
                    auditor) and, significantly, Helena Comtesse de Noailles, who took a further
                    sixty shares. </p>
                <p>Officially the editors of the journal were Parkes and Hays, but Smith remained a
                    very active presence. Once the enterprise had begun, they quickly began to
                    attract further contributors. In November 1858 Emily Faithfull, a clergyman’s
                    daughter, began work for the journal. The following June, Jessie Boucherett,
                    after seeing the journal on a railway bookstall, came to London and joined as a
                    contributor. With the poet Adelaide Proctor – a friend of Parkes – she
                    established the Society for Promoting the Employment of Women with Faithfull
                    acting as secretary. In the same year Emily Davies, who had met Smith in Algiers
                    in 1858, came to London and began to contribute, eventually settling in London
                    in 1862. The reading rooms in Princes Street acted as a focus for all these
                    writers, providing a space to meet and read, as well as room for the various
                    political and social enterprises they were each engaged upon. In December 1859
                    Theodosia Lady Monson, widow of a Tory peer and friend of Matilda Hays, took
                    more spacious rooms on behalf of the Company at 14 Langham Place: the address
                    from which they acquired their name, the Langham Place Group (Rendall 2005).</p>
                <p>The first issue of the <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> appeared in March
                    1858 and it established many of the consistent features of the title. Each
                    monthly issue of the <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> consisted of 72
                    pages that contained about eight articles. The first article tended to engage
                    with contemporary political or social issues, and was usually written by Parkes.
                    There were three regular departments that could be found in each issue: ‘Open
                    Council’, ‘Notices of Books’, and ‘Passing Events’. ‘Open Council’, which
                    appeared from the second issue, was a department of correspondence. Its title is
                    the same as the correspondence column of the <title>Leader</title>, and it was –
                    like the <title>Leader </title>– ostensibly free from editorial interference.
                    Unlike some titles, the <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>did not insist
                    upon signature in its correspondence department and the descriptive pseudonyms
                    (for instance ‘A Polite Letter Writer’, ‘A West End House Keeper’, ‘An Old
                    Fashioned Country Reader’) signalled a diverse and predominantly feminine
                    readership. ‘Notices of Books’ was a department of reviews and is similar in
                    format to reviews in other titles such as the <title>Leader</title>. They were
                    often unsigned, with the first review being much more thorough than those that
                    followed it. The reviews made great use of quotation, providing readers with
                    lengthy extracts from which they too could judge the works under discussion. A
                    broad range of publications were noticed, from Coventry Patmore’s <title>The
                        Angel of the House </title>in the first issue to novels, scientific
                    treaties, lives, travel writing, and political pamphlets. Occasionally the
                    department was broken up with sub-headings. In 1858 ‘Foreign Literature’ appears
                    intermittently, but foreign works were usually reviewed alongside those
                    published in Britain. From October 1861 until October 1863 a ‘Books of the
                    Month’ section appears that surveyed recent publications and allowed readers to
                    keep abreast of what was being published. ‘Passing Events’ was a similar section
                    as the ‘Books of the Month’, but focused instead on public affairs. This
                    department was the last to appear in each issue, and was only a few pages long.
                    Its brevity meant that it largely summarized events in note form, and did not
                    provide readers with much analysis. However, it does indicate the importance
                    that the journal placed on what might otherwise appear to be masculine affairs
                    and provided the means for its readers to find out more about them.</p>
                <p>Another regular department, although not named as such, was the poetry that was
                    published in each issue. These occurred in the middle of each issue, usually the
                    fourth or fifth article, and tended to by lyrics of about thirty lines that
                    covered a range of subjects including social issues, but were most frequently on
                    religious themes. The most frequent contributors of verse were Adelaide Proctor
                    and Isa Craig, but Parkes also published extensively in the journal. Poetry was
                    accorded a high status, appearing consistently in the same place and frequently
                    under review in ‘Notices of Books’. Unlike poetry, fiction appeared
                    infrequently. When it did appear, it tended to be as short stories or short
                    serials over a couple of issues that described acts of oppression or charity in
                    a largely sentimental mode. However, there are other genres of writing within
                    the <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>that are explicitly literary. The
                    frequent pieces of travel writing, even when apparently concerned with social
                    conditions abroad, are often presented in a compelling narrative style; and the
                    same is true of many of the biographical portraits of notable women.</p>
                <p>Despite the presence of these regular features, all the articles within the
                        <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>are represented in the same
                    typographical format. There is no distinction between an essay that only appears
                    in that particular issue, a serial article that stretches across two issues, or
                    a department that appears within all the issues. All articles are numbered with
                    roman numerals in a sequence that runs throughout the volume, locating them
                    within a series that transcends the boundaries of the single issue. This
                    sequence is reproduced in the front matter that was issued to be bound at the
                    front of each volume. Whereas this presents the articles as an unbroken run
                    throughout the volume, the front matter also notes where each issue begins by
                    displaying the month in which it was published. The front matter is thus a
                    hybrid document: the numerals set out the content as an unbroken unit that
                    corresponds to the volume as a whole; but the recurrence of certain departments
                    and the insertion of the month retain its identity as a set of individual
                    issues.</p>
                <p>The <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>was not a mass circulation periodical.
                    In January 1859, mid-way through volume two, it had 400 annual subscribers but
                    received a further 57. It was also selling 250 copies monthly. This circulation
                    of around 700 was sustained throughout 1859 but, by January 1860, the Company
                    was printing 1250 copies a month (250 to be kept as back issues). This increase
                    was partly due to the activities of the National Association for the Promotion
                    of Social Science, an organization closely connected to the Company through its
                    secretary, Isa Craig, and a significant overlap of interests. The <title>English
                        Woman’s Journal </title>became the official organ of the Association, and
                    Parkes used its Annual Conventions as a means of gaining subscribers (Rendall
                    1987). By April 1862 circulation was still around a thousand copies a month but
                    there are signs that it was running into financial trouble. Early in 1862 Anne
                    Leigh Smith, who represented her sister, Barbara, on the board, had to lend £200
                    to the journal in order to pay its contributors. When Emily Davies took over the
                    editorship in September 1862 she predicted that subscriptions would fall to 624
                    by the following September. Based on this figure, there would only be £48 with
                    which to pay contributors. Even if the better contributors were only offered 10s
                    a page, and the weaker contributors 4s, Davies estimated she would still need to
                    find unpaid contributions to fill between 30-40 pages a month (Rendall 1987).
                    When Parkes resumed the editorship in May 1863, there was discussion as to
                    whether it should be permitted to continue. After only 376 of 1200 shares were
                    taken up after a reissue of the Company's stock in May 1864, the management of
                    the <title>Journal</title> was passed to Parkes. It survived until August 1864
                    with Elizabeth Elioart as editor, but was merged with the <title>Alexandra
                        Magazine </title>in September to become the <title>Alexandra Magazine and
                        Englishwoman’s Journal</title>. In 1865 Jessie Boucherett acquired the title
                    and, as the <title>Englishwoman’s Review</title>, it lasted until 1910 (Rendall
                    1987).</p>
                <p>The <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> was interested in the position of all
                    women in society, but was largely concerned with the practical fate of women of
                    its own class. The opening article, <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=EWJ%2F1858%2F03%2F01&amp;page=13&amp;entityid=Ar00103&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘The Profession of the Teacher’</xref>, articulates the politics of the
                    journal while also demonstrating how it was connected to the wider activities of
                    the Langham Place Group. The article identifies teaching as of interest to the
                    journal’s readers as it is the only profession open to ‘an educated woman of
                    average ability.’ The 1851 census had revealed that there were half a million
                    more women than men in Britain; for contemporary feminists this pointed to the
                    absurdity of assuming marriage was an adequate profession for women; as Parkes
                    put it in an article in the <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>in <xref
                        type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=EWJ%2F1860%2F03%2F01&amp;page=6&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
                        >March 1860</xref>, there was little point educating women in the profession
                    of marriage when there were not enough positions for them to fill. This
                    shortfall, which could be established statistically, meant that there was an
                    economic imperative to train women to support themselves. Smith had written on
                    this subject for the <title>Waverley </title>and republished her essays as
                        <title>Women and Work </title>in 1857. The article laments the condition
                    many governesses found themselves in but, after detailing what the Governess’s
                    Benevolent Fund (an organization connected to the Langham Place group that
                    advertised through the journal) and other related organizations did to ease
                    their suffering, pointed out that the poor conditions arose because the
                    profession was over-populated. Rather than become governesses, the article
                    pleads that ‘sensible’ women undertake some other form of paid employment. In
                    order to counter the suggestion that seeking work is somehow demeaning for
                    women, the case was made with a combination of dispassionate statistics and
                    emotive anecdotes. The possibility of sending middle class women out to work was
                    presented as a rational necessity and then the conditions in which some
                    governesses found themselves was advanced as a reason for following other forms
                    of labour. Most crucially was the way the article exhorted married women –
                    ‘those who are technically called “ladies”’ – to shield single women workers
                    from the slander and gossip they might encounter as a result of having to go to
                    work. By appealing to married women here, the journal argued that alternative
                    professions are more respectable than governessing because, if too many women
                    become governesses, there was a real risk that they would become destitute and,
                    ultimately, resort to prostitution. The article, in other words, played upon
                    middle class propriety in order to advocate an otherwise radical solution.</p>
                <p>A crucial component of the way the <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>argued
                    its politics was through the way it complemented its essays with examples of
                    action drawn from the activities of the Langham Place group. For instance, ‘The
                    Profession of Teacher’ was buttressed by the Group’s employment agency,
                    administered by Proctor and Boucherett’s Society for Promoting the Employment of
                    Women. This agency was run from the offices of the <title>English Woman’s
                        Journal</title> and used its wrappers to advertise vacancies and those
                    looking for work. The Society also organized three other ventures: a
                    book-keeping school; a telegraph school; and a Law Engrossing Office at
                    Lincoln’s Inn (see <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=EWJ%2F1860%2F08%2F01&amp;page=36&amp;entityid=Ar02803&amp;view=entity"
                        >here</xref> for further details). The most successful, however,
                    was Emily Faithfull’s Victoria Press, established in Feb 1860. Initiated at
                    Coram’s Fields with £50 from the English Woman’s Journal Company, the press
                    employed 16 female compositors, around half of whom were apprenticed by the
                    Society after hearing about the scheme via its register. The Victoria Press
                    became the printer of the <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> from its
                    foundation in 1860 until 1863. The Langham Place Group – who were necessarily
                    vigilant about remaining free from scandal – distanced themselves from Faithfull
                    after she was named in a notorious, queer divorce scandal (Vicinus, 2004,
                    69–79). From volume 12 it was printed by Jarrold and Sons, who also joined the
                    Company as publishers. The Victoria Press was taken over in 1865 by William
                    Wilfred Head, who continued to run it as an employment opportunity for women
                    until 1881.</p>
                <p>Although the <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> did not reach a large
                    audience, it remains an important publication in social and feminist history. It
                    combined detailed analysis of issues of concern to women in a distinctly
                    feminine discourse that combined liberal politics, non-demonational religious
                    sentiment, affecting anecdote, and engagement with high culture. As part of a
                    wider set of activities from the Langham Place group, the journal complemented
                    its textual representations of notable figures with coverage of the actual
                    activities of politically-engaged women. Although articulated from a particular
                    class perspective, the explicitly gendered text of the journal offers a contrast
                    to the predominantly masculinist print culture of the nineteenth century. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> in ncse </head>
                <p>The run of the <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> in the edition is derived
                    from the hard copies held at the Women’s Library at London Metropolitan
                    University. The British Library run lacks volumes 4-13, which were destroyed in
                    the Second World War. There is a run at the Bodleian that is marked as being
                    Barbara Leigh Smith’s own: however, aside from one pencil annotation, it is
                    otherwise unremarkable. The <title>English Woman’s Journal </title>was published
                    with an advertising wrapper. Although we have not been able to recover any
                    issues with this intact, the Women’s Library run contains an ‘<title>English
                        Woman’s Journal</title> Advertiser’. As this run was therefore the most
                    complete, we approached the Women’s Library to ask if we could produce new film
                    from their hard copy. We are grateful to both the Women’s Library and the
                    British Library for their cooperation in producing these images. </p></div>
                <div>
                    <head> Works Cited</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Dredge, Sarah (2005), ‘Opportunism and Accommodation: The English
                            Woman's Journal and the British Mid-Nineteenth-Century Women's
                            Movement’, <title>Women's Studies</title>, 34,  133-157.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hirsch, Pam (2004), ‘Bodichon, Barbara Leigh Smith (1827–1891)’,
                                <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title> (Oxford
                            University Press); online edn, May 2007 [<xref type="external"
                                url="http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/2755"
                                >http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/2755</xref>, accessed 6 May
                            2008]</bibl>
                        <bibl>Rendall, Jane (1987), "'A Moral Engine': Feminism, Liberalism and
                                <title>The Englishwoman's Journal</title>", in <title>Equal or
                                Different: Women's Politics 1800-1914</title>, ed. by Jane Rendall
                            (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1987), pp. 112-38.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Rendall, Jane (2005), ‘Langham Place group (<title>act.
                            </title>1857–1866)’, <title>Oxford Dictionary of National
                            Biography</title> (Oxford University Press); online edn, Jan 2008 [<xref
                                type="external" url="http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/theme/93708"
                                >http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/theme/93708</xref>, accessed 6 May
                            2008]</bibl>
                        <bibl>Shattock, Joanne, 2004, ‘Parkes [Belloc], Elizabeth Rayner [Bessie]
                            (1829–1925)’, <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>
                            (Oxford University Press); [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/41193,
                            accessed 9 May 2008]</bibl>
                        <bibl>Vicinus, Martha (2004), <title>Intimate Friends: Women Who Loved Women
                                1778-1928</title> (Chicago).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p>Jim Mussell</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
