<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p2_3">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Leader (1850-1859)</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-31</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <q>On the public advertising placards of the <title>Leader</title> now going about,
                    the names of the following contributors…appear: -- Foxton, Larken, Kingsley,
                    Dawson, Neale, Owen, Froude, Thornton Hunt, Holyoake, Landor, Marotti,
                    Martineau, Manzini, Newman and others, ‘whose names are reserved for special
                    reasons.’ Should any of these gentleman object to the mention of their names in
                    this place --- we can only say that this is no <title>publication</title> of
                    them; they are public already, placarded at every railway station, for anybody
                    to see who likes. The paper is announced in obtrusively large letters as a
                    ‘first class family newspaper,’ and as intended to ‘develop the utmost freedom
                    of intellect, energy of production, popular power, and in the political and
                    social relation of all the classes the paramount influence of natural affection.
                    (‘The Social Regeneration School’, [Church] <title>Guardian</title>, 5 Nov 1851.
                    Cited in Brick 1957, 137) <note> Earlier in the year, In January, the
                            <title>Leader</title> had been attacked by another part of the
                        Establishment, the Whig/Liberal quarterly, the <title>Edinburgh
                        Review</title>.</note></q>
            </p>
            <p>As indicated by this <title>Guardian</title> editorial early in the
                <title>Leader</title>’s run, the new paper managed to harbour a spectrum of
                radicals, from Republicans to Christian Socialists in a fragile and contested weekly
                space. The <title>Leader</title> was a mid-century, six pence weekly of 24 pages
                which began as a radical and pervasively political paper <note>There are two
                    excellent and informative sources on the <title>Leader</title> in addition to
                    the journal itself, one accessible, pithy, and relatively brief and the other
                    inaccessible, usefully detailed, and lengthy. These are respectively by
                    Christopher Kent in (Sullivan 1984), and by Allan Brick whose Yale dissertation
                    on the <title>Leader</title> submitted in 1957 is available on microfilm (Brick
                    1957). Readers may glean a profile of the paper from Kent’s entry in Sullivan.
                    In this piece I have tried to write an account that reflects our work on the
                    title in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>.</note>, with its ‘master principle’ ‘the
                right of every opinion to its own free utterance’. Dedicated to publication of
                ‘actual opinion’ rather than policed, acceptable views, it vowed to offer ‘free
                utterance to the most advanced opinion’ in its <xref type="external"
                    url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1850%2F03%2F30&amp;page=22&amp;entityid=Ar02201&amp;view=entity"
                    >manifesto</xref> (22). In the same document it identified itself as ‘A Weekly
                Newspaper’ and, although in July 1855 its subtitle became <title>A Political and
                    Literary Review</title> (1855-1858)<title>,</title> it was only under new titles
                in 1860, that it renounced its newspaper status and became a full-fledged
                    Review<note>In an advertisement in the issue for <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1859%2F12%2F31&amp;page=13&amp;entityid=Ar01306&amp;view=entity"
                        >31 December 1859</xref> they claim it ‘will consist entirely of original
                    articles […] the character of a newspaper will be so far abandoned that nothing
                    will be admitted but a specially written analysis and record of all the
                    political, literary, scientific, and artistic accounts of the week’.</note> Its
                three titles after 1858 – the <title>Leader: A Political, Literary, Commercial and
                    Family Weekly Newspaper, and Record of Joint Stock Companies</title> (Jan-Dec
                1859), the <title>Leader and Saturday Analyst</title> (January-June 1860) and the
                    <title>Saturday Analyst and Leader</title> (July-December 1860) indicate its
                struggle to survive. This transformation within a decade is perhaps the most extreme
                testimony of the dynamics of change that characterised the <title>Leader</title>’s
                run, a pattern which may be seen as typical in the nineteenth-century of many and
                possibly most serial titles when they are scrutinised closely. An example of
                stability and longevity such as the <title>Spectator</title>, achieved by the
                unusual tenure of its editors<note>Its first editor, Robert Rintoul, who was also a
                    founder served 30 years, 1828-1858, and then from 1861 to 1897 Meredith Townsend
                    and R H Hutton presided for over 35 years, as Political and Literary Editor
                    respectively.</note> is the exception rather than the rule. </p>
            <p>As for the <title>Leader,</title> within ten years it had five (possibly six)
                editors, five titles, five printers and four publishers. While there are a number of
                explanations for its rocky fortunes, they tend to be historical or generic, and not
                applicable to the <title>Leader</title> alone. They include the peculiar tensions of
                radical papers, such as internal ideological disagreements, dearth of advertising
                and a paucity of financial backers. At its launch, the moment seemed auspicious for
                new directions in the radical press. At the tail end of Chartism<note>The
                        <title>Northern Star</title>, the Chartist weekly, endureduntil 1852, and
                    its overlap with the <title>Leader</title> affords an interesting view of the
                    old guard and the new; Thornton Hunt and George Holyoake, two of the founders of
                    the <title>Leader</title> knew each other from the Chartist Committee, on which
                    they both still served when the <title>Leader</title> began.</note>, the
                    <title>Leader</title> could stage fresh campaigns for suffrage, universal
                education, and working class rights. However, the Crimean War (1853 / 54-1856) gave
                an impetus to the <title>daily</title> press, with its new technology of ‘instant’
                reporting, the telegraph. Unstamped ‘War Telegraph’ newspapers appeared in a number
                of British cities, including one published by G. J. Holyoake, a founder of the
                    <title>Leader,</title> and daily or thrice weekly news sheets pipped the
                weeklies in feeding the appetite for ‘news’. The other function of the weeklies,
                    <title>interpretation</title> of the news might well suffer under the pressure
                for hard news of a society at war. This problem of the incursion of the
                proliferation of dailies on the functions of the weeklies did not disappear with the
                cessation of the war, and eventually was the basis for the remodelling of the
                    <title>Leader</title> in 1860. </p>
            <p>Half way through its run, the <title>Leader</title> also coincided with a significant
                upheaval in the market induced by the repeal of the Stamp Duty in June1855. This
                resulted not only in a cheaper press, but a proliferation of weekly papers in
                general. Specifically for the <title>Leader</title>, two new, cheap, repeal-related
                rivals appeared. The two pence (and quickly one penny) <title>Daily Telegraph
                </title> was edited at first by Thornton Hunt, a former founder / editor of the
                    <title>Leader</title>. The cheeky, splenetic Tory<title> Saturday Review</title>
                set its ambitions high, seeking to invigorate the genre, become the <title>Times
                </title> of the weeklies, and capture the bulk of this niche market – and it
                succeeded in all three. While the cost of the <title>Leader</title> went down after
                repeal, from 6d stamped to 5d unstamped, the novelty and liveliness of the two new
                titles were powerful attractions. Both overlapped with the coverage of the
                    <title>Leader,</title> with Hunt taking care to add art and literary coverage to
                the new daily paper, and the <title>Saturday</title> specifically stating that it
                was a <title>Review of Politics, Literature, Science and Art,</title> a sub-title
                that mapped directly onto the subjects of the <title>Leader</title>.</p>
            <p>In March 1850, with its three ruled columns and folio format, its appearance was
                unmistakably newspaper-like, and at least from 13 April1850 – and probably from the
                beginning, it articulated its strong link to news and orientation to the newspaper
                press with respect to time by publishing more than one edition of each weekly issue<note>
                    <p>[footnote 6 text] Although there is no second edition for issue three of the
                            <title>Leader</title> in the British Library (and so it is also absent
                        from <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>), a second edition of issue threee is
                        referred to in issue four, 20 April, just below the <xref
                            url="http://137.73.123.44/KingsCollege/Default.htm?href=CLD%2F1850%2F04%2F20&amp;page=10&amp;entityid=Ar01001&amp;view=entity"
                            >Postscript</xref> heading (p. 82).</p>
                </note>. As a newspaper carrying news before the disappearance of the Newspaper
                Stamp Duty, it was stamped, which offers us insight into its circulation figures
                until repeal<note>Mitchell’s Newspaper Press Directory 1855 for 1856 includes stamp
                    returns for the Leader as follows: 1851: 115, 000; 1852: 98,000; 1853
                120,000.</note>. Like a newspaper it had no cover and its masthead topped page one,
                with its number, date and price below. However, unlike many newspapers of the day,
                until 1859 it confined its advertising to the back pages, and the masthead and date
                line were followed by a list of the contents in tabular form with pagination.
                Immediately below the table was the first department; again, newspaper-like, it was
                news-oriented: the ‘News of the Week’ was rounded off by a ‘Stop Press’ column
                called ‘Postscript’, and this tended to be followed by ‘Public Affairs’, a more
                interpretative space and the second major department in the front half of the
                journal. Other newspaper elements, at the back of the journal, included commercial
                news and prices from the exchanges, and ‘Register’ information of births, marriage
                and deaths. Although these persistent elements of the <title>Leader</title> may
                appear alien to our present-day notions of weeklies, they are instances of types of
                information – the <title>news</title> of the latest prices and the <title>record
                </title> of parish facts – associated with the earliest contents of
                    newspapers<note>The presence of these sections seems particularly vulnerable to
                    change over the run, ranging as it does from minimal traces to highly developed
                    departments. A study of these variations and their relation to the vision and
                    fortunes of the paper over the decade might prove very interesting.</note>.</p>
            <p>In 1850, at the same time as promulgating its <title>bona fide</title> newspaper
                identity, its coverage was dual, including aspects of contemporary culture such as
                the arts, science and social science as well as political news. Imitating the
                structure of its primary rival at the time, the <title>Spectator</title>, the
                    <title>Leader</title> divided its 24 pages roughly in the middle, with the front
                half politics and much of the back half review. This was already a conventional
                format, evident in Leigh Hunt’s <title>Examiner</title> (1808 ff) as well as the
                    <title>Spectator</title>, and one adopted by its future rival<title>,</title>
                the <title>Saturday Review</title> (1855ff). Such weeklies were hybrids, as the
                usage of the words ‘review’ and ‘newspaper’ in the <title>Leader’s</title> own
                descriptors implies. This genre of weekly publication combines an orientation to
                politics and the past week that links it generically to newspapers,
                <title>and</title> coverage of current books, performance and science that links it
                to (monthly or quarterly) unstamped Reviews, but also to a weekly such as the
                unstamped <title>Athenaeum</title>, which eschewed politics and exclusively covered
                contemporary culture. Interestingly, the <title>Leader</title> formally signalled
                its links to the reviews in its back half by its page layout and typography.
                Initially only the innovative ‘Portfolio’ department, devoted to poetry, fiction,
                and essays<note>Its contents were selected by George Henry Lewes during his tenure
                    as Literary Editor at the journal, 1850-1854.</note>, was printed in a
                review-like two columns rather than three, but from 14 Feb 1852, this format was
                also adopted for the rest of the arts coverage, reverting to three columns for the
                Commercial news and adverts. The other significant variation of format between the
                two parts of the paper is the size of the font: that the font of the political half
                is larger than that of the culture half suggests, again conventionally for the
                newspaper press at the time, a hierarchy of significance, with political news taking
                precedence over all other types of copy. Nevertheless, as the manifesto and
                subsequent adverts state, the founders and editors of the <title>Leader</title> were
                as interested in the cultural half of the journal and its quality as they were in
                the avowedly political front, and their initial organisation of the conduct of the
                paper attests to this: it involved two editors, a political editor (Thornton Hunt)
                and a literary editor (G H Lewes).</p>
            <p>Despite the division of labour, the <title>Leader</title> was a radical paper from
                its beginning to its demise<note>Its commitment to reform is evident, for example,
                    in the tone and subject matter of two anonymous pieces in 1860, its attack on
                    the new <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1860%2F01%2F07&amp;page=18&amp;entityid=Ar01801&amp;view=entity">
                        <title>Cornhill Magazine</title>
                    </xref>, and its vehement critique of a pamphlet on the perils of life
                    insurance, in a <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=SLDR%2F1860%2F04%2F14&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >supplement</xref> devoted to this topic in April. An advert in the
                    Supplement for ‘An Essay on Life Insurance’ by one H. W. Porter, B.A. may
                    indicate the author of the Supplement piece.</note>, and its politics pervaded
                the whole. The bleeding of the politics of the front half into the back was
                indicated in the Department that was located from 1850 at the point of transition
                between the two parts and, for a few years was indicated graphically by a woodcut of
                a <xref type="external"
                    url="http://137.73.123.44/KingsCollege/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1850%2F03%2F30&amp;page=12&amp;entityid=Ar01208&amp;view=entity"
                    >winged lion</xref> (not a griffin), possibly an ornament to hand of the
                printers, Palmer and Clayton. Called ‘Open Council’, it was prefaced with an
                epigraph from Milton’s ‘Of True Religion, Heresy, Schism, Toleration’ that made the
                argument for free expression of contrary opinions. It also echoed, silently, a
                principle of more recent radical journalism, whereby John Stuart Mill and his
                fellows in the <title>London Review</title> in 1835, advocated signature in an
                effort to reveal the variety of opinion that the editorial ‘we’ of the earlier
                    <title>Westminster Review</title> denied. Returning the compliment, John
                Chapman, who became the proprietor-editor of the <title>Westminster</title> soon
                after the <title>Leader</title> was launched, replicated the <title>Leader</title>’s
                version of this tradition and introduced into his new property an ‘Independent
                Section’, which appeared sparsely and intermittently from 1852 to 1854, and again
                after 1867. The <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> also followed the
                    <title>Leader,</title> by adopting the title ‘Open Council’ for its
                Correspondence columns in 1858. The point here is the continuity of the radical
                tradition in the press, in which the <title>Leader</title> placed itself,
                reflexively, and in which it was seen by others. That said, the extent and nature of
                this department changed over the run of the <title>Leader</title>, from a platform
                for signed mini-essays, which were treated as serious contributions, equal to staff
                pieces, in the early years, to its diminution, shorn of its graphic logo from
                October 1853, and confined to short letters to the editor. In 1850 the editors took
                care to get this feature right, and successive <xref type="external"
                    url="http://137.73.123.44/KingsCollege/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1850%2F04%2F13&amp;page=12&amp;entityid=Ar01202&amp;view=entity"
                    >notes to correspondents</xref> appear adjacent to the column, addressed to
                future contributors in general, and to present hopefuls often with admonitions: ‘To
                the letter signed “B” we have given insertion, although the length made us hesitate.
                So able a writer might have made it shorter […].’ </p>
            <p>As for readership, the 1850 manifesto identified it as ‘All classes, the People’, an
                aspiration that matched its radical orientation. However, by early 1851 its
                untenable claim in Mitchell’s <title>Newspaper Press Directory</title> to comprise
                ‘A Complete, First-class Family Newspaper’ bears out Brick’s suggestion that by this
                date the <title>Leader</title> was in financial trouble (Brick 1957, 203). This bid
                to increase circulation and to widen its advertising base also seems calculated to
                try and address more generally its growing reputation as a wildly radical journal,
                as seen in the epigraph from the <title>Guardian</title> above. This desire (and
                perhaps the necessity) to assure advertisers and readers survived through 1855 when,
                again in Mitchell’s, it assures its advertiser-readers that the <title>Leader
                </title> ‘excludes all objectionable Advertisements; and its condensation of Police
                cases and Criminal Records carefully expunges all offensive details’ (Mitchell 1855,
                    93)<note>It invites the unexpected comparison of the Leader with the
                        <title>Cornhill Magazine</title> (1860ff) which, under the direction of
                    Thackeray in 1860, geared its contents from the outset to the alleged
                    sensibilities of women and children. In fact, the Leader’s stance in the
                    advertising directories causes us to reconsider the overlap of contributors
                    between the two titles, notably G.H. Lewes.</note>. While the back half of the
                journal with its arts coverage and original literary pieces in ‘Portfolio’ might be
                expected to attract women readers – thus explaining this boast of self-censorship
                and respectability – the concomitant politics of the journal would have functioned
                as a barrier to most women who, deprived of the vote and holding of any office, saw
                domestic politics as alien and unengaging. So, although Harriet Martineau and Marian
                Evans contributed to the journal (anonymously), the <title>Leader</title> probably
                had few women readers. </p>
            <p>Another attempt to broaden its readership to a different constituency and to enhance
                its circulation more generally is detectable in advertisements of 1855, in which the
                    <title>Leader</title> recommends itself to journalists and editors for ‘scissors
                and paste’ journalism, commonplace at the time. This involves the (invisible)
                incorporation of copy from one title into another, and <title>Leader</title> texts
                are touted as reliable and easily customised<note>The advert for the
                    <title>Leader</title> in Mitchell’s <title>Newspaper Press Directory</title>
                    explains ‘the particular mode of compiling the news offers great facility for
                    expanding such portions as may be most interesting, while no matter
                    indispensable to completeness is omitted’ (Mitchell 1855, 93).</note>. As a
                rising and burgeoning profession, journalism was relatively reflexive in this
                period, especially after 1855, and the <title>Leader’s</title> address to fellow
                journalists both as readers and potential disseminators of its message is part of
                this wider self-consciousness. </p>
            <p>As a paper of reform written by radicals the <title>Leader</title> comes to this
                discourse with the 1830s call for universal education and ‘the march of intellect’
                still clearly in view, for which print culture is the medium. The campaign against
                newspaper taxes, which were called ‘taxes on knowledge’ in this discourse was a
                cause that fuelled the paper up to 1855, to which numerous articles, reports, and
                adverts on these subjects in the <title>Leader</title> testify<note>The Committee
                    for Repeal is ubiquitous in its pages, which become understandable when it is
                    realised that Thornton Hunt was among its founders.</note>. Its regular
                deployment of quotations or mottos, in the masthead, and attached to departments
                like ‘Public Affairs’, ‘Open Council’ and ‘Literature’ likewise stems its intent to
                educate its readers on the model of the <title>Examiner</title>, as well as from its
                self-conscious identification with politics or ‘positions’. Like
                <title>Chambers</title>’ <title>Edinburgh Journal</title> (1832ff), it also informs
                its readers self-consciously of certain in-house developments such as change of
                format, publishers, titles, etc. This is of great interest to students of the press,
                and in a publication of this sort, one can often connect formal changes in the
                journal with its commercial or editorial history. Here, for example, the date of the
                re-formatting of the second half of the paper on 14 February 1852 may be linked with
                the contents of its note ‘To Our Subscribers and Agents’ on <xref type="external"
                    url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1852%2F02%2F07&amp;page=24&amp;entityid=Ad02418&amp;view=entity"
                    >7 February</xref>, in which the sacking of its deputy publisher Mr John Clayton
                due to irregularities in delivery is announced, along with the advent of new paper
                and new type in the next issue. </p>
            <p>A glimpse of the potential reach of the readership, the location of reading, and a
                profile of the industry in 1850 may be caught in an advertisement for a newsagent
                that appeared in the first number of the <title>Leader.</title> Under the heading
                    <xref
                    url="http://137.73.123.44/KingsCollege/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1850%2F03%2F30&amp;page=24&amp;entityid=Ad02410&amp;view=entity"
                    >‘The Earliest Newspaper Office’</xref> appears the following, for A. Dyson,
                agent for the <title>Leader</title>: </p>
            <p>
                <q>To Gentleman, Merchants, Professional and Commercial Men, Publicans,
                    Beer-sellers….All the Daily, Weekly and other Newspapers, the Cheap Editions of
                    Standard Works in all Departments of Literature, the Magazines, Reviews,
                    Medical, Scientific, and Political Journals, Railway Guides, and all other
                    productions of the press punctually supplied immediately on publication [….]
                        <title>The Leader</title> [<hi rend="italic">…</hi>] particularly adopted
                    for Coffee and Reading-Rooms, and for Family Reading. (24)</q>
            </p>
            <p>Notable for its identification of London-based communal reading locations such as
                public houses, Coffee and Reading-Rooms, and Beer Halls as potential reading
                locations for the <title>Leader,</title> the advert is also indicative that the
                    <title>Leader’s</title> aim for family readership was present from the start.</p>
            <p>One opportunity for enhancing its readership was probably not pursued sufficiently,
                and that was its readership outside London. We know from several sources that Lewes
                was delegated to travel to the North during the period of the formation of the
                journal to raise capital for its launch. This he duly did, and the question arises
                how this element of the readership was served during the <title>Leader</title>’srun.
                As early as 1 February 1851 G.J. Holyoake began to contribute ‘Letters to
                Chartists’, a series of critical if conversational articles to the <title>Leader’s
                </title> ‘Democratic Intelligence’ department, under the pseudonym of Ion, which he
                had transferred from his former paper, the <title>Spirit of the Age</title>.
                Disapproval from the <title>Northern Star</title> ensued, as Holyoake (and the
                    <title>Leader</title>'s editor Thornton Hunt), still sat on the Chartist
                Executive, and readers in the North were alerted. So, there were ideological
                problems between the <title>Leader</title> and a spokesman of the North, as well as
                the issue of the <title>Leader</title>'s distribution.</p>
            <p>We have surmised that from 1850 two editions for each date appeared, an early
                edition, called a Country edition from January 1851 to 5 February 1853, which made
                the Friday trains for shipping to regional newsagents so that it could be delivered
                and read on the date on its masthead, and a later edition published at 1:30 pm
                Saturday, called the Town Edition, in existence for the same period as the ‘Country
                Edition’, which was intended for circulation in London, where the <title>Leader
                </title> was printed. But distribution seemed imperfect from the start, as a note
                    <xref
                    url="http://137.73.123.44/KingsCollege/Default.htm?href=CLD%2F1850%2F05%2F25&amp;page=9&amp;entityid=Ar00903&amp;view=entity"
                    >‘To Correspondents’</xref> in issue 9 states, and a note of 6 December 1851
                reiterates, setting out the advantages and disadvantages of each edition and asking
                readers to <title>choose</title>. Early in 1852, its printer (Clayton) was sacked in
                part for distribution problems and irregularities. This series of iterations of
                distribution problems finally results in a note to subscribers in the issue of 5
                February 1853 giving testy notice of the <title>cancellation</title> of the two
                editions, and their amalgamation into one, to be printed on Saturday. So ‘Country’
                readers have the choice made for them: they will get the full week’s news, but two
                days late. The <title>Leader</title>’s solutions to its distribution problems at
                every turn endorsed the dominance of the metropolitan centre with its timely access
                to news and the distance from the centre and <title>its</title> news of the
                ‘Country’. For more on the multiple editions, click <xref type="internal"
                    from="p5_6">here</xref>.</p>
            <p>Tacitly dictated by financial problems, the disappearance of the two editions is
                publicly attributed to the weight of the disadvantages over the advantages, without
                stating in detail what they were. They were various and complex. 1852 had proved a
                difficult year for the <title>Leader</title> financially and ideologically.
                Financial problems had arisen as early as June 1851 and many of its Northern backers
                had withdrawn late that year, due to the financial risk. At the same time Edward F.
                S. Pigott, a man of 27, to whom the first concept of the <title>Leader</title> has
                been attributed<note>Kichel (1933, 64) attributes ‘the actual formulation of the
                    scheme’ to Pigott, ‘an Oxford man […] well known in journalistic circles.’ His
                    idea was to found a paper based on <title>Galignani’s Messenger</title>, with
                    ‘no special reports of particular events, merely combining in its articles and
                    paragraphs some information with considerable critical comment.’</note> salvaged
                the paper by purchasing a controlling share. In January 1852 he took over the
                editorship from Hunt; by 19 June he was forced to reduce all salaries of
                    <title>Leader</title> staff (Brick, 1957, 203–4). In April Holyoake went north
                to lecture. Public and private quarrels among the radicals arose that summer, with
                George J. Harney in July, W.J. Linton, and even Thornton Hunt, now no longer the
                editor, objecting in September to the <title>Leader’s</title> attack on the
                    <title>Red Republican</title>. Brick judges that these ideological battles cost
                the <title>Leader</title> more of its Northern readers (1957, 219).</p>
            <p>Change and turmoil at the centre continued, as soon afterward, in October 1852 Pigott
                introduced into the <title>Leader</title>'s columns a talented parliamentary
                reporter, Edward Whitty who, by 21 July 1853 was installed as editor. Lasting just
                under a year, until spring 1854, Whitty was not popular with staff: his conservative
                politics and Catholic orientation alienated Holyoake, and prompted Harriet Martineau
                and Francis Newman to withdraw support. Whitty having left ignominiously<note>Whitty
                    published a novel, <title>Friends of Bohemia, or Phases of London Life</title>
                    in 1857. Its acerbic account of the Leader in chapter 23 earned an angry review
                    in the Leader on <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1857%2F03%2F07&amp;page=19&amp;entityid=Ar01900&amp;view=entity"
                        >7 Mar 1857</xref>, and a more favourable piece in the Athenaeum on the same
                    date.</note>, Pigott was back in harness by 22 March. Movement of key figures
                from the centre continued: Lewes left in July 1854 for Germany with Marian Evans,
                and by 1855 Thornton Hunt was editing a new daily. Beset by the left, by the
                    Liberals<note>In an article in the January 1851 issue of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>,
                    W.R. Greg attacked in a piece, ‘English socialism and communistic assosications’
                    (Anonymous [W.R. Greg] 1851, 1-33).</note>, and the right, the
                position of the <title>Leader</title> was never easy. </p>
            <p>The staff, founders, and backers of the <title>Leader</title> were for the most part
                experienced journalists from different facets of the radical camp. Thornton Hunt,
                son of Leigh Hunt, editor of the <title>Examiner</title> (1808-1821) and latterly of
                the <title>Monthly Repository</title> (1837-1838) had spent years in prison with his
                father as a child; he came to the <title>Leader</title> as an experienced journalist
                from the <title>Spectator,</title> seeking a space offering freedom of expression.
                Hunt was also socially radical, living in a succession of communes in which
                free-union was advocated by some residents. G J Holyoake, a co-founder, had been
                jailed for blasphemy in 1842 as an atheist, and had edited short-lived, radical
                newspapers, such as <title>Cause of the People</title> (1848) with W.J. Linton (a
                Republican and another of the <title>Leader</title> founders), <title>Spirit of the
                    Age</title> (1849), and <title>People’s Review</title> (1850). One of the
                    <title>Leader</title>'s principal backers was a radical clergyman, Edmund
                Larken, who had translated George Sand. Among the minor shareholders were George
                Dawson, a radical preacher and Republican orator, Richard Congreve, a Comtian
                clergyman, and several printers, including Palmer and Clayton, printers of the
                    <title>Leader</title> who also printed the <title>Spectator</title>. G.H. Lewes
                came to the <title>Leader</title> as an experienced journalist of ten years’
                duration, mentored by J.S. Mill and a longstanding friend of Thornton Hunt. Author
                of a history of philosophy published by Charles Knight and of two novels, Lewes’s
                diverse areas of interest were continental philosophy including Comte, German
                literature, drama, and science. Not only did the staff of the <title>Leader</title>
                have diverse antecedents which tied them to earlier print titles and political
                movements, but many of them went on from the <title>Leader</title> in this central
                decade of the century to important roles in other well-known press titles: Hunt to
                edit the <title>Daily Telegraph</title> and the <title>Spectator,</title> Lewes to
                contribute to the <title>Westminster Review</title>, to contribute to and help edit
                the <title>Cornhill</title>, and to found and edit the <title>Fortnighly</title>.
                From 1874 Pigott became an unpopular Examiner of Plays, who disliked Ibsen and was
                in turn disdained by Shaw and Wilde. </p>
            <p>Pigott’s tenure as editor (and proprietor) of the <title>Leader,</title> 1852-July
                1853, March 1854-May 1858 makes him its most stable and long-lived associate, who
                only sold the title in 1858 because he could no longer sustain the losses. Among his
                changes of policy was to relax the anonymity, which had been the rule in its first
                two years; the youthful Wilkie Collins had his first regular employment from Pigott;
                other renowned contributors over the run include Marian Evans, Harriet Martineau,
                Francis Newman, and Herbert Spencer. Much of Lewes’s best work appears here.
                However, it is reductive to view, much less assess the <title>Leader</title> through
                the filter of individuals, whether they are editors, proprietors or contributors.
                While sales reveal the verdicts of readers of the day, subject as they are to
                rivals, war, politics, and economic factors, later students of the press should not
                be beguiled by others’ judgments of the ‘strength’ of the journal in its first,
                radical years, its ‘falling off’ under Pigott, etc. We need to look at the whole
                run, and diverse sources of meaning which, for us, is differently defined and from a
                different perspective than that of the original readers. With respect to its
                ‘contents’, it does have a variety of strengths – detailed commentary from radical
                perspectives of day-to-day national, international and local (London) politics;
                regular coverage of and intermittently dedicated departments for science, foreign
                literature, and social science; high quality and appreciative reviews of Anglophone
                literature, for example, <title>Wuthering Heights, Moby Dick, In Memoriam, </title>
                Thackeray’s fiction, Jane Austen, and a critique of Dickens’s bad science in
                    <title>Bleak House</title>; and an assiduous coverage of the London theatre,
                especially 1850-1854, when Lewes, writing as ‘Vivian’, was reviewing it. Other
                particular series of articles, or columns are similarly outstanding, such as
                Holyoake’s letters to Chartists, and the concomitant ‘Letters to Unitarians’.</p>
            <p>Conventionally defined ‘contents’ remain only part of its meaning. Paratextual
                material such as the wrappers, the adverts, the mastheads, the imprints, the timing
                of Supplements, the mottoes, the ‘Notes to Subscribers’, the ‘Tables of Contents’,
                the multiple editions, and the indexes are all of moment. The advertising in the
                    <title>Leader</title> is not only remarkably robust, but <title>its </title>
                contents is richly informative about the intellectual and political context of the
                paper, as well as its financial status. The shakier the funding, the more adverts
                for patent medicines; but adverts are also closely linked with other forms of copy,
                and affiliations of the current staff. For example, Thornton Hunt was the founder of
                the Committee for Repeal of the Newspaper Taxes which advertises frequently in the
                period up to 1855.</p>
            <p>The <title>Leader’s</title> annual indexes offer both a detailed account
                <title>and</title> digestible oversight of the structure and weighting of the paper
                in the last 12 months, but also a review of the political and cultural year, keyed
                in to commentary on it, geared to journalists at the time, and also of use to later
                scholars and historians such as ourselves. The internal structure and organisation
                mapped in the Index also repays further investigation over the run: the evolving
                vision of the whole; changing departments (their appearance and disappearance, and
                the waxing and waning of those that survive); the weighting of different elements of
                the weekly; how the absence, departure or arrival of individuals – contributors,
                editors, proprietors – affects contents and policy; and the influence on them of
                changing finances. Given the richness of the archive with respect to the
                    <title>Leader</title>,the title is open to this type of complex analysis, as
                Brick’s invaluable work indicates. </p>
            <p>The endgame of the <title>Leader</title> is also of real interest. This was
                    <title>not</title> a merger; there was no former existence of the
                    <title>Saturday Analyst</title> before this title was appended to the original
                and well-known trade mark, initially as a sub-title, and then as the main title.
                Brick suggeststhat the final vision of the <title>Leader</title> is its successful
                rival, the new title invoking the <title>Saturday Review</title>, with which by this
                time Pigott was editorially connected (1857, 258). In a final effort to survive, the
                Tomlins (the new proprietors of the <title>Leader</title>),reject the function of a
                weekly paper to disseminate news that was originally adopted in 1850. Arguing that
                weekly <title>news</title>papersare old-fashioned and no longer viable, an
                explanatory <xref
                    url="http://137.73.123.44/KingsCollege/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1859%2F12%2F31&amp;page=13&amp;entityid=Ar01306&amp;view=entity"
                    >note to subscribers and agents</xref>
                in 1859 points to the rapid dissemination of news by the proliferating dailies and
                the telegraph, which combine to render weekly news sheets redundant. Rather,
                weeklies should be reviews, it concludes,adopting the case and the model of the
                    <title>Saturday Review,</title> which in 1855 had itself self-consciously set
                out to re-invigorate and rethink the weekly as a form. The <title>Leader </title>
                from start to finish seems imbricated in nineteenth-century journalism and, given
                its origins in one journal, <title>Galignani’s</title>, it is appropriate to find
                its demise modelled on another. </p>
            <div>
                <head>The <title>Leader</title> in ncse</head>
                <p>This edition of the <title>Leader</title> is sourced from the hard copy located
                    in the British Library’s newspaper collections at Colindale. Initially, we were
                    going to draw on extant microfilm at the British Library for March 1850–July
                    1854, and then create new film for 1855-1860. However, on reviewing the tiff
                    images that were produced from the microfilm, we found that some of the multiple
                    editions had not been included. With the cooperation of the Biritsh Library we
                    created new microfilm from the hard copy for 1850-1854. The only exception to
                    this was the first half (January-June) of 1854. We were unable to locate the
                    volume for 1854, and so had to use the existing microfilm for the first portion
                    of the year. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Works Cited</head>
                <listBibl><bibl>Anonymous [W.R. Greg], 1851, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 1–33.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brick, Allan, 1957, ‘The <title>Leader</title>: Organ of Radicalism’, unpublished
                    PhD thesis (Yale University).</bibl>
                <bibl>Kichel, Anna T., (1933), <title>George Lewes and George Eliot. A Review of the
                        Records</title>, (New York: John Day Co.).</bibl>
                <bibl>McCabe, Joseph, 1908, <title>The Life and Letters of G J.Holyoake</title>,
                    (London: Watt and Co.).</bibl>
                <bibl>Mitchell, Charles, ed., 1855, <title>Mitchell’s Newspaper Press Directory</title>
                    (London)</bibl>
                <bibl>Sullivan, Alvin, ed., 1983, <title>British Literary Magazines</title>, 4 vols
                    (Wesport, Connecticut: Greenwood).</bibl>
                <bibl>Collins, W., 2005, <title>The Public Face of Wilkie Collins. Collected Letters,
                    </title> ed. by W. Baker, Andrew Gasson, G. Law, and Paul Lewis, 4 vols (London:
                    Pickering and Chatto).</bibl>
                <bibl>Kent, Christopher, 1984, ‘The Leader’, in <title>British Literary Magazines,
                    </title> ed. by A Sullivan, vol. 3, ‘The Victorian and Edwardian Age, 1837-1914’
                    (Westport, CT: Greenwood), 185-189.</bibl>
                <bibl>Whitty, Edward, 1857, <title>Friends of Bohemia, or Phases of London Life</title>
                    (London: Smith, Elder and Co.)</bibl></listBibl>


               
                <p>Laurel Brake</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
