<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p2_1">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Monthly Repository (1806-1838)</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-31</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>The Monthly Repository and Unitarian Chronicle</head>
                <p>In its thirty two-year span of existence, only four editors presided over the
                        <title>Monthly Repository</title>. Its founding editor, Robert Aspland,
                    established the journal as the foremost Unitarian monthly, and was its dedicated
                    editor for twenty years, from 1806 to 1826. Aspland’s affiliations with
                    philosophical Benthamism confirmed the Unitarians as the intellectuals among the
                    dissenting community in England. In 1826 the recently formed British and Foreign
                    Unitarian Association bought out Aspland, and the Second Series was initiated in
                    1827, continuing until 1837. After a short period of committee editorship,
                    William Johnson Fox became editor of the journal. Fox became owner and
                    proprietor of the <title>Monthly Repository</title> in 1831, and the first
                    volume under his sole editorship, in 1832, initiated a policy of active
                    political engagement that extended the journal’s (and Unitarianism’s)
                    intellectual and cultural reach, making it an avant garde production often far
                    ahead of its time, promulgating in the 1830s what only became current in the
                    1860s. The short life of the <title>Unitarian Chronicle</title>, price three
                    pence, is connected to Fox’s editorship. When he took over, the magazine’s
                    customary section on ‘Unitarian Intelligence’ was formed into this new
                    supplement in order to make way for larger articles while still maintaining that
                    ‘acquaintance with one another’s condition’ and the ‘contemporary history of our
                    churches’, as the ‘Address’ in the first issue explains. But the supplement
                    lasted for only six months. Richard Hengist Horne succeeded Fox as editor in
                    1836 but relinquished the role in 1837. Under Leigh Hunt, who became editor
                    briefly from 1837-38, the format changed to two columns and the page span was
                    lengthened. The Enlarged Series of the magazine went into two volumes before the
                        <title>Repository’s</title> life terminated. The journal lost its direction
                    after Fox’s editorship. After 1832 when, at least ostensibly, democratic
                    objectives, however limited, had been achieved, reform politics, too,
                    temporarily lost their bearings. The efforts of both Horne and Hunt to shift the
                        <title>Repository’s</title> agenda and to create a new kind of content are
                    symptomatic of a wider hesitation or check on radical thought.</p>
                <p>Throughout its life the price of the <title>Monthly Repository</title> varied
                    little, between one shilling and one shilling and six pence (raised in 1811),
                    just as its page span varied little between 56 and 80 pages. The format adopted
                    was the double column until 1827, when single page format became the norm for
                    the ten years before Hunt’s editorship. The price was well within reach of the
                    educated middle class dissenting community active in Unitarian circles. The
                    journal’s circulation, however, according to F. E. Mineka, the outstanding
                    historian of the journal, seems to have rarely gone beyond 1,250 copies, and
                    though Fox expanded the circulation, it fluctuated as he mounted controversial
                    articles on religion, poetry, politics, female emancipation, and education
                    (Mineka 1944, 167). It has to be remembered, though, that periodicals were read
                    aloud to families and companions, and were borrowed and passed round groups of
                    friends and acquaintances at this time. It is thus highly likely that the
                    journal was read and discussed by many more people than its circulation
                    suggests. Dissenting and Unitarian networks were close knit.</p>
                <p> It is inevitable that the glorious years of the magazine appear to be those
                    under the editorship of Fox, from 1827 to 1836. Aspland’s foundational work was
                    supremely important, however. If the key word of Fox’s <title>Repository</title>
                    was ‘community’, those of the Aspland era were ‘bigotry’, ‘persecution’,
                    ‘fanaticism’. The shift in policy that these words represent is less a move from
                    sectarian religion to politics than a redefinition of the purposes of
                    Unitarianism and a new understanding of the political. ‘Community’ is a
                    political word with a Unitarian subtext: ‘bigotry’ is a Unitarian term with a
                    political subtext.</p>
                <p>By the time he came to edit, at twenty four, <title>The Monthly Repository of
                        Theology and General Literature</title> (the long title was shortened when
                    Fox took over), Aspland had passed through Calvinism and the Arian Baptists to
                    Unitarianism, and had succeeded the eminent figures of Unitarian thought –
                    Thomas Belsham, Richard Price, and above all Joseph Priestley – as Pastor at the
                    Gravel Pit Chapel, Hackney. Unitarianism’s core beliefs were in Christ’s simple
                    humanity (not, as in Arianism, Christ’s quasi divinity), one God, and a
                    corresponding rejection of the Trinity (views on adult baptism and varying
                    interpretations of the resurrection of the body in non literal terms were often
                    associated with Unitarian thought). Unitarians believed they had returned to the
                    primal principles of early Christianity. Yet the <title>Monthly
                    Repository</title> was not founded simply to proselytise these principles alone.
                    And though Aspland clearly saw the journal as a way of consolidating the
                    Unitarians, who were without a central organisation, as a group, just as he set
                    up the Unitarian Fund (1806) and the Christian Tract Society (1809), established
                    the Unitarian Hymnal (1810), and founded the Non-Con Club (1817), the aims of
                    the journal transcended these organizational objectives. </p>
                <p>The <title>Repository’s</title> deliberate recall of the title of Joseph
                    Priestley’s earlier periodical, the <title>Theological Repository</title>,
                    indicates the reach of the journal. Priestley’s name is ubiquitous in it. Until
                    he left to live in America in 1794, Priestley – polymath scientist, theologian,
                    historian, aesthetician, philosopher, and preacher, whose house and laboratory
                    had been destroyed by a Church and King riot in 1791 – continued to argue for
                    freedom of thought, rational investigation and above all critical analysis of
                    belief and morality even when, particularly when, these are turned upon
                    Unitarian beliefs themselves. Unitarianism in his hands was an anti-sectarian
                    form of dissent that was inherently dialogical. Intolerance was anathema to it.
                    The <title>Repository</title> was set up as an exemplary form of Unitarian
                    practice, to extend and disseminate the debates of the formation beyond the
                    pulpit and pamphlet into print culture and to extend the rational Christian
                        <title>principle</title> of debate itself into the public sphere. It began
                    its life as a forum for debate, a debate constituted by readers themselves as
                    much as by the editor. Letters and correspondence, as we shall see, were a major
                    structural part of the magazine. It was literally a republic of
                    <title>letters</title>. </p>
                <p>Its anti-authoritarianism placed it in sympathy with Utilitarian thought.
                    Benthamite and Unitarian thought were not necessarily homologous: but both were
                    driven by a demythologizing tendency, by rationality, by belief in philosophical
                    analysis, by a thrust towards republicanism and belief in the effectiveness of
                    democratic inspection of opinions and institutions. As Mineka points out, the
                    social and political philosophy of the periodical was ‘modified by religious
                    prepossessions that did not ordinarily affect the leading Benthamites’ (1944,
                    102). Nevertheless, the First Series of the <title>Monthly Repository</title>
                    used words from Jeremy Bentham’s <title>Fragment on Government</title> as a
                    motto. Bentham warns against sacrificing independent judgement to the ‘shackles
                    of authority’, on being deceived by ‘shewy’ language, and against allowing the
                    imagination to falsify experience (cited in Mineka 1944, 101). The prospectus
                    for the new journal fused Benthamite and Unitarian values. It claimed to ‘blend
                    literature with theology, and to make theology rational and literature popular’,
                    to sustain ‘Protestant’ liberty of conscience, to promote religious
                    investigation and to admit all writers of ability, ‘whatever their peculiar
                    opinions’ (cited in Mineka, 1944, 03). In the <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=FMRP%2F1806%2F12%2F02&amp;page=7&amp;entityid=Ar00500&amp;view=entity"
                        >Preface</xref> at the end of the <title>Repository’s</title> first year,
                    asking for contributions from ‘men of learning and talents’ (v), Aspland claimed
                    that the principle of ‘public examination’ and ‘Free Inquiry’ was paramount:
                    ‘its being the only periodical publication which is open to FREE AND IMPARTIAL
                    THEOLOGICAL INQUIRY AND DISCUSSION’ (vi). The political subtext is clear. This
                    was the counterrevolutionary age of extreme repression in England under the Pitt
                    administration and subsequent Tory ministries lasting from Pitt’s death in 1806
                    to 1830 – treason trials, paid spies, prosecution and arbitrary imprisonment.
                    Aged twelve, Aspland had seen the state prisoners incarcerated for political
                    belief in the Tower of London, Thomas Hardy and Horne Tooke. The early years of
                    the <title>Repository</title> were concurrent with the French wars, with the
                    post war backlash against sedition, and with economic hardship and oppression
                    that induced popular discontent.</p>
                <p>By the second volume of the journal, in 1807, Aspland had gained confidence and
                    established the pattern of the magazine. A look at the <title>Repository</title>
                    at ten year intervals, the January issues of 1807, 1817, and 1827, together with
                    Fox’s first fully independent issue of January 1832, suggests how the journal
                    evolved. Fox’s subsequent editorial policy grew out of his early commitments. </p>
                <p>In 1807 the magazine listed eleven Departments or genres of discussion. These
                    were ‘Biography’, ‘Miscellaneous Communications’, ‘Biblical Criticism’,
                    ‘Poetry’, ‘Review’, ‘Obituary’, ‘Religious, Literary, and Politico-Religious
                    Intelligence’, ‘Correspondence’, and ‘New Publications’. But this is a deceptive
                    taxonomy. The privileged categories are actually biography and the letter,
                    followed closely by the brief review, where controversial publications from
                    opposite points of view were juxtaposed. ‘Biblical Criticism’, for example,
                    consists of a series of epistolary contributions, and is hardly to be
                    distinguished from the ‘Miscellaneous Communications’ that precede it.
                    Similarly, though the lead <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00104&amp;view=entity"
                        >biographical section </xref> (1-6) is a memorial to the life of Dr James
                    Foster, who died in 1752, it reads like an obituary, and the <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=41&amp;entityid=Ar04104&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Obituary’</xref> (41-4), of the Duke of Richmond, grandson of one of the
                    illegitimate sons of Charles the Second, reads like a biography. Indeed, these
                    two biographical-memorial studies flank the dialogical content of the central
                    parts of the issue. They are not so much records as, respectively, religious and
                    political narratives of the lives of significant figures who
                    <title>lived</title> their religion and politics. They are exemplary stories
                    that bring the abstract ideals of Unitarianism into everyday possibility. The
                    pattern of Foster’s life follows closely the Unitarian trajectory traced in
                    Volume One, exemplified by the biography of <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1806%2F01%2F02&amp;page=7&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
                        >Edward Evanson</xref>. The narrative describes a training in orthodoxy, an
                    agonistic moment of recognition, as the doctrine of the Trinity is rejected on
                    rational grounds, a decision to make a public acknowledgement of this discovery,
                    and the turn to Unitarianism, often involving very considerable material
                    sacrifice and financial hardship. </p>
                <p>These are everyday martyrs, conversion narratives that chart practical choices,
                    but they are also about the fate of public debate itself. In Evanson’s case, who
                    left the Church of England in 1777, ‘I soon found that the system of religion,
                    called Orthodox . . . was so far from being taught by the apostles . . . that it
                    was the very apostacy from it’ (3). Interestingly, his departure was
                    precipitated not by an attack on his Unitarian principles but by an offence
                    against Unitarian respect for liberal principles against bigotry. The Bishop of
                    Litchfield preached that the Church of Rome was ‘<title>exclusively</title>
                    anti-christ’ (5). Foster, like Evanson, ‘began to waver in his belief of the
                    received doctrine of the Trinity’ (2), and was persecuted by members of his
                    church: ‘Thus Protestant Dissenter[s], forgetting their own principles,
                    attempted to introduce other standards of faith than the Holy Scriptures’ (2).
                    The Duke of Richmond’s obituary is a direct critique of the Pitt years, which
                    had only just ended. ‘The Duke of Richmond’s political notions were very liberal
                    indeed, which, if, like Pitt, when in administration he ceased to profess, he
                    never ventured like him openly to retract; still less to persecute those among
                    whom he had imbibed them’ (43). In fact, Richmond refused to make restitution
                    for the beheading of Charles 1. He ‘believed his ancestor suffered most justly’
                    (42). He resisted the American war of Independence. He was a member of the
                    Revolution Society: ‘I am more and more convinced, that the restoring of the
                    right of voting universally to every man not incapacitated by nature, for want
                    of reason, or by law, for the commission of crimes, together with annual
                    election, is the only reform that can be effectual and permanent’ (43). An
                    obituary is a difficult document to prosecute for sedition. As if to indicate
                    the openness of the <title>Repository</title>, this obituary is followed by one
                    on the <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=46&amp;entityid=Ar04400&amp;view=entity"
                        >Rev. P. Good</xref>, a dissenting Trinitarian, friend of Roman Catholics
                    and an opponent of the repeal of the Test Acts (45).</p>
                <p>The six letters included under <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=25&amp;entityid=Ar02502&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Biblical Criticism’</xref> (which include a letter of Priestley’s, sent in
                    by a correspondent) again indicate Aspland’s liberal principles (6-28). An
                    allegorical interpretation of the Scriptures sits side by side (11-14) with ‘A
                    Catholic’s Appeal against the Orthodox’ (10-11), which is preceded by an account
                    of conversion from Catholicism (pp. 7-10). The poem, ‘The Orphan’, that follows
                    this Biblical Criticism, was sent in by letter. The six reviews that follow this
                    poem almost invariably document controversies. The genealogy of bigotry and
                    persecution that they constitute is exemplified in the review of Richard
                    Wright’s life of <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=39&amp;entityid=Ar03403&amp;view=entity"
                        >Michael Servetus </xref> (34-9: ‘being designed to eradicate bigotry’)
                    condemned to death by Calvin and ‘ecclesiastical tyrants’. <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=41&amp;entityid=Ar03904&amp;view=entity"
                        >Article V </xref> analyses the ‘inflammatory, mob-adapted style’ and
                    ‘ludicrous ignorance’ (40) of Robert Dickinson’s funeral oration on the Bishop
                    of St. Asaph. Dickinson describes Priestley as ‘the prince of heretics’,
                    attempting, like a vulture, to tear away ‘the very vitals of Christianity’. Even
                    a review of <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=54&amp;entityid=Ar05203&amp;view=entity"
                        >lighthouse technology</xref> in ‘Religious, Literary and Politico-Religious
                    Intelligence’ begins with a critique of Roman power. ‘Rome, in the plenitude of
                    power, enriched with the plunder of conquered provinces’ left ‘ostentatious
                    monuments of unbounded ambition’ that left behind ‘a wide scene of ruin and
                    desolation’ (52). The principle of utility embodied in the lighthouse now
                    preserves life. The excitement of this poetics of rational controversy is the
                    driving impulse of the <title>Repository’s</title> rhetoric. Though it makes
                    space to notice the religious affairs of various societies and Unitarian bodies
                    under ‘Religious [….] Intelligence’, and to document a number of technological
                    advances, including inoculation for <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1807%2F01%2F02&amp;page=50&amp;entityid=Ar05001&amp;view=entity"
                        >Smallpox</xref> (49-52) – a typical science-directed, ‘greatest happiness’,
                    Utilitarian preoccupation – it has little time for literary production.
                    Aspland’s list of new publications includes Charlotte Smith’s <title>Beachy
                        Head, and Other Poems</title> next to G. Ogs’s <title>Admonition. A Poem. On
                        the Fashionable Modes of Female Dress</title>. </p>
                <p>The January issue of Volume 12 of the <title>Monthly Repository</title> for 1817
                    displays much the same loose categorical structure, with an abundance of
                    epistolary contributions, headed by <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1817%2F01%2F02&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00104&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Biography’</xref> (presented as a letter to the Editor), a section which
                    consists, in fact, not of historical figures but of two obituaries (again, the
                    genre of biography and obituary is fused) of major figures in the Unitarian
                    community, William Vidler and Benjamin Carpenter (1-7). Vidler had edited the
                        <title>Universalist’s Miscellany</title> from 1797, which went through a
                    number of title changes before Aspland bought it out to found the
                        <title>Repository</title>. The ten departments are listed as ‘History and
                    Biography’, ‘Original Letters’, ‘Extracts’, ‘Miscellaneous Communications’,
                    ‘Gleanings […] in a course of General Reading’, ‘Review’, ‘Poetry’, ‘Obituary’,
                    ‘Monthly Retrospect of Public Affairs’, ‘New Publications in Theology and
                    General Literature’. The ‘Extracts’, which consist of letters of Benjamin
                    Franklin to Priestley, are not distinguishable generically from the Original
                    Letters. Many of the ‘Miscellaneous Communications’ are in the form of letters.
                    A ‘Believer in Miracles’ submitted a careful critique of Hume’s <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1817%2F01%2F02&amp;page=20&amp;entityid=Ar01701&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Objection to Miracles’</xref> (17-20), and William Johnson Fox wrote
                    eloquently on the <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1817%2F01%2F02&amp;page=34&amp;entityid=Ar03300&amp;view=entity"
                        >resurrection of the body</xref> (33-4). As in 1807 the Review section
                    documented controversies that raised issues of intolerance and free inquiry.
                    Richard Price’s <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1817%2F01%2F02&amp;page=48&amp;entityid=Ar04302&amp;view=entity">
                        <title>Sermons on Various Subjects</title>
                    </xref>, was reviewed at some length (43-8). ‘ “Is it visionary”, asks this
                    eloquent preacher, “to expect a better world? […] This is what some tell us.
                    Such infidelity is the greatest misfortune” […]’ </p>
                <p>There is one notable difference between 1817 and 1807: <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1817%2F01%2F02&amp;page=63&amp;entityid=Ar06101&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘The Christian’s Survey of the Political World’</xref> (61-3), in the
                    ‘Monthly Retrospect of Public Affairs’, is an unequivocal attack on the corrupt
                    state of the House of Commons: ‘The great question at issue is the reform of the
                    House of Commons, and it is argued that this House no longer answers the end for
                    which it was established, namely, the interference of the people in the affairs
                    of government: for the voice of the people, it is said, has not its due weight
                    in that House, being overwhelmed by that of the oligarchists, or the proprietors
                    of rotten boroughs’ (61). The article considers universal suffrage – it is an
                    article and not a letter – and defends the Spa Fields gatherings of the previous
                    year, when a riot occurred, arguing that the mass of the 30–40,000 people
                    present were gathered peacefully. This is a policy document that does not have
                    its parallel in the <title>Repository</title> until a much later date. It shows
                    the extent of Aspland’s political seriousness, and marks a moment when the
                    conventions of his journalism were changing. Open debate began to be defined not
                    as the dialogic juxtaposition of discrete positions, an anthology of different
                    theological views, but a sustained and coherent development of an argued case on
                    several fronts. It was deliberately opinion-forming and promotional, arguing a
                    radical case. Democratic debate in the public sphere comes to be defined as the
                    development of policies that extend to all areas of the culture, where print
                    culture is consciously used as an agent of persuasion to formulate and
                    disseminate policies. Aspland’s <title>Repository</title> stood for the
                    principle of participatory debate and controversy within the Unitarian
                    formation: what mattered was the debate <title>form.</title> It performed a
                    rational politics. Later volumes of the journal stressed <title>content</title>.
                    It developed a rhetoric that persuaded its readers to accept a new view of
                    intellectual culture and civil society.</p>
                <p>A striking change is evident in Volume I of the New Series for January 1827. The
                    journal is now titled <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=1&amp;view=document">
                        <title>The Monthly Repository and Review</title>
                    </xref>. The departmental categories have been pruned: ‘Review’, ‘Critical
                    Notices’, ‘Obituary’, ‘Intelligence’, ‘Correspondence’, survive. Elements of the
                    earlier scheme remain in the <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=62&amp;entityid=Ar06203&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Critical Notices’</xref>, which mount controversy – on the British and
                    Foreign Bible Society (63), on John Mitford’s choice of religious poems in an
                    anthology of sacred verse (64-5), on the character of Unitarianism (65).
                    ‘Biography’ and ‘History’, those markers of Unitarian experience that were the
                    lead articles of earlier issues, have entirely disappeared. Instead the review
                    begins with and virtually consists of, a series of ten articles, some relatively
                    brief (<xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=21&amp;entityid=Ar01702&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Thoughts on Christian Charity’</xref>, 17-21; the issue of <xref
                        type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=61&amp;entityid=Ar06101&amp;view=entity"
                        >imprisonment for debt</xref>, 61), but most substantial. Their theological
                    character is strong (for example, a <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=32&amp;entityid=Ar02501&amp;view=entity"
                        >discussion of the Corporation and Test Acts</xref>, defining religious
                    persecution as injury inflicted for religious belief, 25-32), but the lead
                    article, <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=-1&amp;entityid=Ar00101&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘On the State of Religious Parties in England’</xref> (1-9), reads like an
                    editorial. It argues that since 1688 all subsequent national events have been
                    nearly or remotely connected with religious opinions and feelings’ (1). It is a
                    theological and sociological analysis of the different factions and class
                    composition of the Church of England, from High Church to Evangelical. It is
                    scathing about the emotionalism of Evangelical preaching: ‘Some read
                    well-written and not over-long sermons; others deliver themselves extempore and
                    let the hour-glass fairly run out . . . [they] are to be seen at prayer
                    meetings, expounding meetings, experience meetings, if not at camp meetings’
                    (7). It deprecates the lazy quietude of the established church, where ‘the
                    possession of power’ must ‘satiate the desire of change’ (8). This discussion
                    falls between a religious discourse with a political subtext and the political
                    discourse with a religious subtext that was to supersede it. A sophisticated
                    account of Frederick Schliermacher’s <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=-1&amp;entityid=Ar03301&amp;view=entity">
                        <title>A Critical essay on the Gospel of St Luke</title>
                    </xref> (33-48), bringing speculative continental philosophy into the journal
                    for the first time, looks forward to the Fox era. It is thoroughly at home with
                    the notion of a fragmented, multi-authored biblical text. Most surprising of
                    all, the section headed <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1827%2F01%2F02&amp;page=80&amp;entityid=Ar08002&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Correspondence’</xref> is actually a sharp request to readers
                    <title>not</title> to correspond. It curtails a correspondence on the Baptismal
                    Controversy and brings it firmly to an end. Significantly, the short obituaries
                    now include women.</p>
                <p>The <title>Monthly Repository</title> for January 1832 (New Series, Volume 6) was
                    the first wholly edited by Fox in his capacity of owner-editor. It represents
                    the birth of what we think of as a modern periodical. Mineka describes it as in
                    ‘transition from a religious to a secular magazine’ (1944, 249), and, ‘Once the
                    predominance of clerical contributors had been broken, the
                    <title>Repository</title> progressively substituted literary, aesthetic, social,
                    and political subjects for religious’ (1944, 250). As evidence for a
                    transitional phase followed by a secular phase, Mineka points to the relatively
                    unchanged roster of contributors in the early months of Fox’s journal, that were
                    superseded by others as the proportion of religious articles declined. Fox added
                    John Stuart Mill to his early contingent of reviewers, but Harriet Taylor, John
                    Beard, and Harriet Martineau continued for a time to contribute. Likewise John
                    Johns, J.J. Tayler, Emily Taylor, Jane Roscoe, William Turner, John Bowring,
                    John Moggridge, and Crab Robinson. Sarah Flower, her husband, William Bridges
                    Adams, Ebenezer Elliot, Mary Leman Grimstone, W.T. Hayley and James Martineau
                    were later contributors, as were Robert Browning, R.H. Horne, Caroline Southwood
                    Smith, and William and Mary Howitt (1944, 249-50). [footnote 1]</p>
                <p>Yet most of these contributors were Unitarians or Unitarian sympathisers, and all
                    were dissenting intellectuals. The extraordinary flowering of the magazine in
                    the 1830s suggests that Unitarianism, or some currents of it, began to flow in
                    different directions. Rather than abandoning Unitarian principles Fox and his
                    contributors were redefining them. The revolution in culture and society that
                    Fox envisaged was founded on religious passion. The ‘secular’ character of the
                    magazine was the result of religious energy directed into re-shaping society and
                    the very idea of civil society. Without having the word available in the modern
                    sense, the Fox circle was engaged with inventing the meaning of a common
                    ‘culture’. And to do so, again without having the term available, they had to
                    become an avant garde group. </p>
                <p>Fox’s <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=11&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
                        >leading article</xref> in 1832 is a campaigning editorial. It is a
                    manifesto for the periodical and an agenda for civil society that goes far
                    beyond what was achieved later in the year with the 1832 reform act. ‘We ‘are in
                    a state of transition’, he argued, ‘and old things are passing away’ (2).
                    Society ‘is in the very act’ of ‘assuming a new form’. Its forms no longer
                    ‘realized the desires of the community’. He predicted throes and convulsion, but
                    revolution is not his object: he saw the Bristol riots of the previous year as
                    the tragic result of the monopoly of government by the privileged (p.10): he
                    itemised the ‘extensive changes’ that would have to come about as a corollary of
                    peaceful reform and democratic representation; indeed reform was merely the
                    catalyst that would bring about wider and deeper transformations in society. In
                    a series of rhetorical anaphora, he listed each of the institutions that ‘cannot
                    remain as it is. The Church ‘cannot remain as it is’: it was no longer a
                    national Church (the corollary was disestablishment): the obfuscations and
                    oppressions of the Law cannot remain; they must be swept away; Education must be
                    changed – ‘the poor must be educated, though it be at the public expense’, and
                    knowledge must be changed with the introduction of a scientific curriculum that
                    entertained ethics as well as the classics ( this would also impact on the
                    training of the medical profession); the Press must be reformed with the
                    abolition of the ‘taxes on knowledge’ that prohibited the free circulation of
                    opinion. Print culture was crucial in a democracy. He might have added other
                    things that were part of the radical programme of the journal, the reform of the
                    divorce laws and a sexual politics that saw women as equals, and a belief in the
                    emancipatory power of art, of poetry in particular. An internationalism that
                    transcended the boundaries of the nation state was also, he claimed, an ideal of
                    Unitarianism, and he followed the great traditions of Aspland by condemning
                    fanaticism (9). </p>
                <p>One can see these ideas already altering the taxonomy of the departments in the
                    first issue of 1832. After a series of speculative articles the sections are
                    listed as ‘Critical Notices’, ‘History and Science’ (tellingly, science rather
                    than biography), ‘Miscellaneous’, ‘Religious Intelligence’, ‘Obituary’. The
                    reviews include, not only <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=66&amp;entityid=Ar06101&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Luther’s Table Talk’</xref> (61-7), but also Charles Knight’s <xref
                        type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=59&amp;entityid=Ar05802&amp;view=entity">
                        <title>The Working-Man’s Companion. Rights of Industry. Capital and
                        Labour</title>
                    </xref>, 1831, a sharp critique that indicate Fox’s interest in working class
                    politics (58). The speculative articles include a powerfully argued <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=23&amp;entityid=Ar01502&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘The Rise and progress of the Doctrine of the Trinity’</xref> (15-23), by
                    John Relly Beard. But the first section also included Harriet Martineau’s brisk
                        <xref
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=34&amp;entityid=Ar02402&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘On the Duty of Studying Political Economy’</xref> (24-34). A utilitarian
                    argument against the arbitraryness of charity, it argued for a scientifically
                    organised economy that understands distribution and consumption. It is
                    thoroughly Benthamite in its rationalist optimism and belief that economic laws
                    properly understood eradicate poverty and crime, so that utility is beauty. John
                    James Tayler contributed <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=34&amp;entityid=Ar03402&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Herder’s Thoughts on the Philosophy of the History of Mankind’</xref>
                    (34-42), the first of four articles that argue for Herder’s unique, holistic
                    reading of history and society. The connection of the solar system and ‘the most
                    delicate fabric of the spider’s web’ (37), argue for an integrated reading of
                    history that brings together natural and civil history, physical geography and
                    the history of societies. Herder’s belief that art and society are organically
                    linked and that the spirit of a particular literature derives from a particular
                    condition of society (one of the earliest formulations of the idea of ideology
                    and popular culture) introduces the article: ‘He thought with Bacon that a
                    ballad or a legend more faithfully indicated the current of popular feeling’
                    than ‘graver productions’ (36). Emily Taylor contributed her translation of the
                    striking, boldly idealist <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=42&amp;entityid=Ar04201&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘The Visible and the Invisible’</xref> (42-61), by the Pastor of Nismes, S.
                    Vincent. Vincent distinguishes between the sensoria that bring the visible into
                    being and the invisible nature of mind. This, rather than a transcendental
                    being, is spirit, he argues. The movement towards continental thought here is
                    arresting, and indicates Fox’s willingness to move across national boundaries
                    beyond a narrowly British focus (the 1832 volume lists a Parisian distributor).
                    It can be no accident, also, that women play such a strong part in this first
                    issue of the year. Taking all these contributions together, this is
                    intellectually a revolutionary issue.</p>
                <p>Though the Fox group did not have the word ‘culture’ in their vocabulary, they
                    did possess a Benthamite word that indicated the scope of their social vision –
                    ‘community’. Fox used it more than once in <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F01%2F02&amp;page=11&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
                        >his editorial</xref>, ‘the desires of the community’ (3), ‘the state of the
                    community’ (7). In 1832 Fox reprinted <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F07%2F02&amp;page=26&amp;entityid=Ar01800&amp;view=entity"
                        >Southwood Smith’s oration</xref> (450-1) after the dissection of Bentham’s
                    body (he attended the dissection): ‘the only comprehensive and only right and
                    proper end of the social union, or of the aggregate of individual men which
                    constitutes a community, is the greatest happiness of all members of the
                    community’. Even the issue of January 1832 shows how far he and his circle went
                    in imagining this community. The titles of articles even in the early volume of
                    1832 indicate the extent of Fox’s project. ‘On the Parliamentary Pledges to be
                    Required of Candidates at the Ensuing Elections’ (Fox – Parliamentary Reform);
                    ‘The Irish Tithe Question’, ‘Religion Without Taxation’ (R.W.Hinks, Fox – Church
                    reform); ‘Prison Discipline’ (Harriet Martineau – Law Reform); ‘Sunday School
                    Education’, ‘National Education’(John Relly Beard, Harriet Martineau –
                    Educational reform); ‘Taxes on Knowledge’ (Fox – Reform of the Press); ‘Domestic
                    Manners of the Americans’, ‘Notices of France’(Harriet Taylor, John Moggridge –
                    internationalism); ‘Rise of Unitarianism in America’, ‘On the Character and
                    Philosophy of the late Jeremy Bentham’ (John Relly Beard, Fox – the entwining of
                    Unitarianism and Utilitarianism in continuity with the Aspland’s
                        <title>Repository</title>); ‘The Poor and their Poetry’, ‘Goethe’s Works’,
                    ‘Connection between Poetry and Religion’ (Fox, Crabb Robinson, John Johns – the
                    uses of the aesthetic). There was still an important component of theological
                    writing, such as William Turner’s ‘Thoughts on Power, and on the Universal
                    Agency of the Deity’, and the extent of the deep connection of theology with
                    social analysis can be gauged by the same writer’s later <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1833%2F10%2F02&amp;page=72&amp;entityid=Ar06601&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘On the Relation of the Wealthy and Educated Classes to the Poor’</xref>
                    (Vol. 7, 726-32). This list does not, of course, do justice to the energy and
                    intensity of the writing. We might take as an example Fox’s<xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F03%2F02&amp;page=9&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘The Fast Day and the Cholera’</xref>, a satire on the government edict for
                    a day of fasting and prayer in the face of the Cholera epidemic, a mixture of
                    medical ignorance and superstition. ‘The fast day will come, and people will
                    leave of working, but nobody will fast’: it will be a national holiday, though
                    it was to be hoped that charity will not withhold the soup distributed to the
                    poor, who fast involuntarily, soup distributed to prevent cholera itself from
                    decimating them (p. 146). </p>
                <p>The above is a brief indication of the changing nature of a middle-class
                    dissenting radical periodical of the 1830s. Mineka’s great history describes in
                    detail the writings of the Fox era. Though an extraordinary period in the
                    history of print culture, it was brief. It foundered when reform politics
                    searched for new directions. But it also foundered on Fox’s own policies. In
                    1833 he wrote supporting divorce (Vol. 7, 145-53), and seems to have lived out
                    his beliefs. James Martineau, who was nevertheless loyal to him, called his
                    circle a ‘free-thinking and free-living clique’ (Webb, 2008). His commitment to
                    divorce, his formal separation from his wife, and his liaison with Eliza Flower
                    the composer, his ward, and eventually the head of his household, daughter of
                    another powerful reforming editor, Benjamin Flower (who had edited the
                        <title>Cambridge Intelligencer</title> (1793-1800)), caused upheaval among
                    his congregation and undoubtedly dissipated his energies. His beliefs, though,
                    lived on when he became MP for Oldham in 1846. Even his feminism was recognised.
                    When the <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> reviewed an <xref
                        type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=EWJ
                    %2F1858%2F05%2F01&amp;page=64&amp;entityid=Ar06400&amp;view=entity"
                        >exhibition of women painters</xref>, a portrait of Fox by his
                    daughter received special mention. ‘Miss Fox sends a large oil portrait of her
                    father, the member for Oldham, whose noble sense of justice to women has been
                    marked at every stage of his public and parliamentary career’ (208).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Monthly Repository in ncse</head>
                <p>This edition of the <title>Monthly Repository </title>was sourced form the hard
                    copy held at the British Library at St Pancras. It includes its supplement, the
                        <title>Unitarian Chronicle</title>, which is held separately in the library.
                    There is one volume – Second Series, Volume 1, 1827 – missing from the British
                    Library run. This was generously provided by the Bodleian.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Works Cited</head>
                <listBibl><bibl>Mineka, Francis E., 1944, <title>The Dissidence of Dissent. The Monthly
                        Repository, 1806-1838</title> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina
                    Press).</bibl>
                <bibl>Webb, K., 2008, ‘Fox, William Johnson (1786–1864)’, <title>Oxford Dictionary of
                        National Biography</title>, Oxford University Press, Sept 2004; online edn,
                    Jan 2008 [<xref type="external" url="http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/10047">http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/10047</xref>, accessed 8 May 2008]</bibl>
                <bibl>[text for footnote 1] Mineka (1944, 395–400) identifies the contributions of a
                    number of prominent contributors to the First Series, though as no key exists
                    for this series, the sources (see 394-5), are scattered and not wholly reliable.
                    For the Second Series (1830-37) a detailed though incomplete key is available,
                    held by the British Library. Mineka lists the ‘essential information’ of this
                    key (400-28). </bibl></listBibl>
                <p>Isobel Armstrong</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
