<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p2_2">
  <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Northern Star (1837-1852)</title>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
        <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc default="NO">
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2008-03-31</date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>EL</name>
        </respStmt>
        <item>created file</item>
      </change>


    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>

      <div>
        <head>The <title>Northern Star</title></head>
        <p>The first issue of the <title>Northern Star</title> appeared on the 18 November 1837.
          Over the next fifteen years the paper played a crucial role in cohering Chartism as a mass
          radical movement and ensured that its proprietor, Feargus O’Connor, became one of its most
          recognizable leaders. It also became one of the most successful newspapers of the early
          nineteenth century, with a regular circulation of 80,000 copies a week in 1839. This
          edition, which for the first time brings together the issues, multiple editions, and
          supplementary portraits, is one of the most complete in the world, offering users an
          unparalleled resource for early nineteenth-century social history and the print culture
          that shaped it.</p>
        <p>The <title>Star</title> was established by Feargus O’Connor in 1837 in co-operation with
          the printer and publisher Josiah Hobson. Hobson was a veteran of the radical press, whose
            <title>Voice of the West Riding </title>had been one of the most successful unstamped
          publications of the 1830s (Chase 2007). The location of his shop on Briggate in Leeds
          provided a geographical identity for the title that was reproduced in its mastheads (its
          full title was the <title>Northern Star and Leeds General Advertiser</title>) and imprint.
          Leeds was by far the centre of the Yorkshire press, its three weekly papers – the
          radical-liberal <title>Leeds Times</title>, Tory <title>Leeds Intelligencer</title> and
          Whig <title>Leeds Mercury </title>– all having higher circulations than any others in the
          region. From its earliest issues the <title>Star</title> was a large (41 x 59cm)
          broadsheet weekly newspaper with six columns of closely printed type. It cost four and a
          half pence a week – a relatively high price for a paper aimed at a working class radical
          readership – and it was published in an initial edition of 3000. Its price was necessary
          to cover the newspaper duty of a penny per issue and brought the <title>Star </title>into
          line with the other papers in the region. Its masthead, as Aled Jones notes, was typical
          of many Victorian newspapers, and the format of the <title>Star</title> also did not
          distinguish it from its rivals (Jones, 2005, 4). For instance, all three Leeds papers were
          the same price as the <title>Star </title>and had the same number of pages and columns.
          Yet within eleven issues the <title>Star </title>could claim that it had surpassed the
          weekly sales of the <title>Intelligencer </title>by almost 6000 copies and was within 187
          copies a week of the <title>Mercury</title>, a paper that boasted that it had the highest
          weekly circulation of any regional paper in the country. When the weekly averages for the
          18 weeks up to the 31 March 1838 were calculated from the number of stamps bought, the
            <title>Intelligencer</title> averaged 3,333; the <title>Times</title> 2666; the
            <title>Northern Star</title> 9822; and the <title>Mercury</title> 9002. The paper with
          the next highest weekly average in the region was the <title>Doncaster </title>
          <title>Gazette</title> with 2000 and the paper with the highest weekly sales outside of
          London was the <title>Stamford and Lincoln Mercury </title>with 7683 (anonymous, 1838, 4).</p>
        <p>Although the <title>Leeds Mercury</title> sought to dismiss the circulation of the
            <title>Star</title> by claiming that its circulation was artificially inflated by its
          policy of issuing portraits every six weeks, it had clearly reached a large audience very
          rapidly on the basis of its radical politics despite its relatively high price. As its
          sales increased week on week, Hobson had to invest in a new two horse power steam engine
          in order to meet the demand (click <xref type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1838%2F03%2F31&amp;page=4&amp;entityid=Ar00409&amp;view=entity"
            >here</xref> for further details). The <title>Mercury</title> also claimed that the
            <title>Star’s </title>circulation seemed large as it included large numbers of readers
          in Lancashire. In a way, these readers, geographically distant from the <title>Star’s
          </title>offices in Leeds, were made possible by the price of the paper. The postal
          concessions that were included in the cost of the stamp allowed O’Connor and Hobson to
          take advantage of the postal network and so link up those readers who might otherwise
          believe they were unconnected (Thompson, 1984, 49). Jones acknowledges that it was
          probably the paper’s politics that accounted for its popularity, but also notes that it
          captured ‘a new kind of reader and a new kind of print’ (Jones, 2005, 19). The <title>Star
          </title>was edited by William Hill, a former handloom weaver and now Swedenborgian
          minister. The text he and Hobson put together combined reports of local news, often sent
          in my contributors or culled from other newspapers, with leading articles that addressed
          more general political issues. The news reports tended to focus on sensational accounts of
          crimes culled from magistrates courts and accounts of fires and other noteworthy events.
          These reports were mixed with (and sometimes used to fill space at the bottom of columns)
          accounts of meetings and other political activities usually sent in by the secretaries of
          local associations. The descriptions of meetings were lengthy, detailed accounts that
          contained the contents of speeches and the reactions of the audience. Drawing these
          disparate accounts together allowed the <title>Star </title>to demonstrate the continuity
          of the movement, with issues and speakers reappearing from place to place and sharing
          platforms with those better known locally. The leading article, ‘The Northern Star’, was
          located – as was typical for weeklies – in the middle of the paper, usually on page three
          or four. It was accompanied by a regular ‘To Readers &amp; Correspondents’ column that
          acknowledged and replied to its readers. This column makes lively reading, and gestures
          towards the wider circulation of texts that underpinned the production of the paper. It
          also permitted the readers of the <title>Star </title>to see the dialogue between Hill in
          Leeds and its contributors distributed around the North of England and Scotland,
          establishing a sense of communal ownership of the paper and the reports that it contained.
          Whereas its politics undoubtedly helped establish it as a regional paper that could
          transcend its local readerships, the way local politics were presented alongside readers’
          contributions and general news stories allowed its readers to see themselves as a body of
          people with a similar set of interests regardless of where they lived and what they did.</p>
        <p>This mixture of the local and national – a format that the <title>Star</title> shared
          with most other regional papers – was also prevalent in its advertisements. Until the
          summer of 1839, the first page and a half of the <title>Star </title>was given over to
          advertisements. Some of these were for other radical publishers and titles, but many were
          drawn from local businesses, often located a few doors down from the <title>Northern Star
          </title>offices on Briggate in Leeds. However, as the <title>Northern Star</title>’s
          circulation soared with the agitation that led to the presentation of the Charter in May
          1839, Hill increasingly devoted the front page to news, trusting to the rise in
          circulation to compensate for the loss of advertising revenue. In March 1839 the
            <title>Star </title>was purchasing over 40,000 stamps per issue and, claiming it was
          read by seven people for every purchaser, proposed a readership of almost 300,000. After
          the Newport Rising and the Bull Ring riots in Birmingham the <title>Star </title>found
          itself under extreme scrutiny. In March 1840 Hobson was accused of avoiding the newspaper
          stamp on another of his publications, the <title>New Moral World</title>, but was
          acquitted after it was proved that the title was exempt. Hobson, like O’Connor, was a wily
          operator who knew how far to go both in terms of printing radical sentiments and evading
          the stamp tax. However, this experience was not enough to save O’Connor from imprisonment
          in May 1840 for a libel that appeared in the <title>Northern Star </title>on <xref
            type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1839%2F07%2F20&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
            >20 July 1839</xref>. The libellous passage appeared in an account of a speech by
          Bronterre O’Brien, another veteran of the unstamped press and, at that point, ally of
          O’Connor and the <title>Star</title>. In his defence, O’Connor claimed that the offending
          passage only appeared in the first edition of the <title>Star</title> and, as this was the
          smallest of the three (it was an edition of 3000; the second and third editions were of
          37,000 each), had not caused much harm. However, the first edition of the
          <title>Star</title>, which was part-printed on Wednesday and completed on Thursday for
          distribution to places furthest from Leeds, also happened to be the London edition (for
          more on multiple editions, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_6">here</xref>). O’Connor accounted for
          the difference in editions as an accident resulting from his missing the printing of the
          first edition due to his attendance at another trial at York. As the proprietor and the
          author of the report that contained the libellous speeches of others, the jury found him
          guilty and sentenced him to eighteen months in prison. The summing up and sentencing was
          reported in the <title>Star</title> for <xref type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1840%2F05%2F16&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00101&amp;view=entity"
            >16 May 1840</xref>.</p>
        <p>The impact of its proprietor’s imprisonment on the fortunes of the paper were limited.
          His letters, printed as the first column on the front page and written in a style that
          encouraged their reading aloud, still appeared regularly. By the end of 1841, the
            <title>Star</title> saw itself very much as a national paper. A rather grumpy column by
          Hill ‘To Readers and Correspondents’ published in the issue for <xref type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1841%2F10%2F02&amp;page=4&amp;entityid=Ar00407&amp;view=entity"
            >2 October 1841</xref> made this plain while also giving a tantalizing glimpse of the
          working practices in the office. Hill’s complaint was that contributors, aware that the
          paper went to press on Thursday evening, sent in contributions by the Wednesday evening
          and Thursday morning posts. Hill explained that his staff began to set the paper on
          Monday, with the intention of having it more or less complete by Wednesday evening. This
          meant that if contributions arrived by the Wednesday or Thursday posts it was unlikely
          that there would be room for their inclusion and that space would instead be filled with
          police reports and items culled from other publications. The article demonstrated the
          pressures of time on the production of a weekly newspaper, particularly the way the time
          that it takes to set the paper had to be balanced against the value of contributions that
          arrived close to going to press. It also demonstrated the pressures that Hill was under to
          be responsive to his readers / contributors. The column ends, ‘Our anxious desire is to
          make the <title>Star </title>a truly national organ, equally representing
          <title>all</title>. But we cannot do this unless the country will aid us rightly in the
          sending of their matters of communication.’ Although the <title>Star </title>employed paid
          contributors (there were seven in 1842, including George Harney in Sheffield prior to his
          becoming sub-editor in 1843), it relied upon its readers for copy. As these readers were
          also necessary to finance the paper, Hill, Hobson and O’Connor were doubly indebted to
          them. The effective use of readers’ contributions would produce a timely text that
          flattered its contributors and so was more likely to sustain its readership; however, such
          readers were beyond the control of those who set the paper and distributed from Leeds.</p>
        <p>There was a change of editorship of the <title>Northern Star </title>in 1843 prompted by
          a combination of declining circulation and an increasing rift between Hill and O’Connor.
          At the end of 1842 the circulation was a respectable 12,500; however, in 1843 there was a
          sharp fall to around 8,700, a figure below that of the early issues of the
          <title>Star</title>. O’Connor’s long cherished London daily, the <title>Evening Star
          </title>had been established in 1842 (his projected <title>Morning Star </title>had come
          to nothing in 1840) and, even though it was running at a loss, provided competition for
          the <title>Northern Star</title>. As Chase argues, 1843 was a difficult time for the
          radical press generally: the <title>British Statesman</title>,<title> London Chartist
            Magazine</title>, <title>Poor Man’s Guardian and Repealer’s Friend</title>, and
            <title>English Charter Circular </title>all folded, leaving only five Chartist
          publications: <title>Aberdeen Review</title>, <title>Carlisle Patriot</title>,
            <title>Edinburgh Weekly Register</title>, <title>Scotch Reformers’ Gazette</title>, and
          the <title>Northern Star </title>(Chase, 2007). Hill was finally removed from the
          editorship in July 1843, and O’Connor, taking decisive action, terminated the
            <title>Evening Star</title> and appointed Hobson stood as editor, bringing George Harney
          onto the staff as sub-editor. </p>
        <p>As the energies of Chartism stagnated, so did the fortunes of the <title>Star</title>.
          O’Connor, recognizing that the resurgent Trade Union movement might lead to an increase in
          readers, aligned the <title>Star</title> with the trades and, in the process, relocated it
          in London. This was more convenient for O’Connor, who lived in London, and for Harney, a
          Londoner with connections to radical groups in Europe. From the 30 November 1844 the
            <title>Star </title>replaced its subtitle ‘Leeds General Advertiser’ with ‘National
          Trades’ Journal’ and, when the National Association of United Trades for the Protection of
          Labour was formed in July 1845, Hobson was elected to its executive. The <title>Star’s
          </title>new metropolitan location reconfigured its relationship with both its readers and
          the news. Rather than being located near its core readership in the Northern manufacturing
          districts and so able to respond reasonably quickly to their news, the <title>Star</title>
          was now two journeys away: one for the news to reach London, and one to send copies of the
          paper back again. The expansion of the railway made distribution more rapid than it had
          been in 1838, but the location of the <title>Star </title>in London meant that it was
          oriented toward London news networks. For O’Connor’s justification to his readers for the
          move, as well as the increase in price to five pence that accompanied it, see the front
          page of the issue for <xref type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1844%2F11%2F23&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
            >23 November 1844</xref>.</p>
        <p>From 1843 O’Connor’s energies were increasingly devoted towards the Chartist land scheme.
          In 1845 the National Charter Association launched the Chartist Cooperative Land Society
          and the first Chartist village opened in 1846. The <title>Star </title>functioned as
          record keeper for the scheme as well as performing its more familiar role of cohering a
          movement that consisted of subscribers distributed across the country. However, the
          relationship between O’Connor and Hobson was becoming increasingly strained, leading to
          the removal of Hobson from the editorship of the <title>Star </title>in November 1846.
          Although this prompted a bitter law suit from Hobson over breach of contract and
          accusations that O’Connor was misappropriating funds from the land scheme, the change in
          staff, coupled with the momentum accrued by the land scheme and interest in the election
          of 1847 (O’Connor was elected MP for Nottingham) raised the circulation of the <title>Star
          </title>from a lowly 6000 a week in 1846 to something like 1842 levels. </p>
        <p>Hobson was replaced by Harney as editor and he saw the <title>Star </title>through the
          revolutions in Europe and the final presentation of the Charter in 1848. Sales, however,
          went into decline, falling to a low of 5000 by 1848. Harney, who clashed with O’Connor
          over his emphasis on foreign news (see Thompson, 1986, 53; Chase 2007), left the
            <title>Star</title> in 1850. The editorship was formally assumed by his successor,
          George Flemming, in the Spring of 1851, who quickly set about altering the format of the
            <title>Star </title>for the coming Parliamentary session. In the issue dated <xref
            type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1851%2F02%2F01&amp;page=4&amp;entityid=Ar00410&amp;view=entity"
            >1 February 1851</xref> he proposed abolishing the Scottish edition and delaying the
          first edition until Friday evening so as to ‘place the Star on an equality with the other
          metropolitan journals published on the same day, as regards the lateness and variety of
          its news’. The extension of the railways would make it possible for Scottish readers to
          get this edition with other readers from outside of London, bringing them within a day of
          London news. This edition would be complemented by a Saturday edition for London and the
          home counties. He also announced that he would use more small type, increasing the content
          but making the paper harder to read. In a comment in the <xref type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1851%2F02%2F08&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
            >following issue</xref> he also announced a new department, ‘Our Weekly Mirror’, that
          would survey the week’s events. This department would be so ‘terse and complete’ that
          those who bound the <title>Star </title>would find it a ‘useful condensation of the
          Political and Social History of the year’. Fleming attempted to sever the link with local
          news and instead offer the <title>Star </title>as radical record of Parliamentary affairs:
          rather than encourage contributions, he asked that they be kept short so that more
          coverage of parliamentary business to be included. </p>
        <p>This movement was completed when Harney bought the <title>Star </title>in April 1852 and
          resumed the editorship. Despite Fleming’s alterations, the format of the <title>Star
          </title>had remained relatively stable since 1838. However, it was clearly a paper in
          decline and Harney proposed some radical alterations. In the issue for the <xref
            type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1852%2F04%2F17&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
            >17 April 1852</xref> Harney announced that the following week the <title>Star
          </title>would be known as the <title>Star of Freedom </title>(it had become the
            <title>Star and National Trades Journal</title> on the 20 March 1852) and merged it with
          his <title>Friend of the People</title>. Harney also reduced the price to four and a half
          pence a week but claimed that further reductions were impossible. A Chartist paper, he
          argued, limited to its own class for its readership, would need to be half the size to
          survive at three pence. If the <title>Star </title>was to remain at its present size but
          be reduced to three pence, it would need to contain more police news and obtain a
          circulation of 30,000. Despite appointing Gerald Massay as literary editor, and securing
          W.J. Linton, Samuel M. Kydd and Alexander Bell as contributors, the <title>Star
          </title>was not a success. On the 14 August the <title>Star of Freedom</title> was
          relaunched, in new type, as a three column, 16 page weekly with a smaller page size of
          around 29 x 41cm. One advantage to this new format was that each department could be
          allocated a separate page. In a note explaining this change in the issue for <xref
            type="external"
            url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1852%2F08%2F07&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
            >7 August 1852</xref>, Harney suggested that ‘its more compact form will be
          with many an additional inducement to preserve each consecutive number for binding in
          half-yearly volumes’. This shift in format marked the final stage in the transition of the
            <title>Northern Star </title>into a London weekly periodical. Its two editions, now
          marked ‘town’ and ‘country’ signalled Harney’s privileging of the metropolis, and his
          remarks about binding severed the title’s link with the passing events of the news. In
          this form the <title>Star </title>survived until 27 November 1852 before Harney moved on
          to his next project, the <title>Vanguard</title>. In the same year Feargus O’Connor was
          committed to an asylum where he died in 1855.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The <title>Northern Star</title> in ncse </head>
        <p>The copy of the <title>Northern Star </title>used in <hi>ncse </hi>is held at the British
          Library. However, this resource – the copy text for many of the microfilm edition
          distributed around the world – is missing the first seven issues, beginning with issue
          eight, dated 6 January 1838. Earlier copies of the <title>Northern Star</title> are
          difficult to find. Issues three and five have been included from the National Archives,
          but we were unable to locate the others. However, the run of the <title>Star</title> is
          not just the 738 issues that were published from 18 November 1837 to the 20 November 1852:
          each regular issue was accompanied by a number of multiple editions. Many of these have
          not survived the archival practices of different institutions and, because of the problems
          that they cause subsequent editors, are often excluded from microfilm or digital editions.
          Our edition of the <title>Northern Star</title> includes every issue that we could find
          amongst the hard copy held by the British Library at Colindale. The Northern Star
          portraits (see below) were mostly obtained from the National Portrait Gallery. From August
          2006 to January 2007 they were exhibited at the Gallery and, with the cooperation of the
          curator, Rab MacGibbon, we produced digital images from them. Malcolm Chase, who found the
          portraits in the National Portrait Gallery’s collection, alerted us to those held by
          Dorothy Thompson. With her cooperation, we were able to obtain two more portraits,
          bringing the total in <hi>ncse</hi> to fifteen.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head> Northern Star Portraits</head>
        <p>The <title>Northern Star</title> issued thirty four engravings from its fifth issue in
          December 1837 until 1851. A full list is given in Chase 2005: below are the fifteen we
          managed to locate and film.</p>
        <p>Of these engravings, 27 were portraits of notable figures and all but five were still
          living. Half of the portraits were of Chartist leaders but others included the poet Andrew
          Marvell, the radical Henry Hunt, and the radical liberal MP for Leeds Sir William
          Molesworth. As Malcolm Chase argues, the portraits were significant in that they moved
          away from the satirical tradition to present a pantheon of notable figures and scenes that
          helped establish a sense of the movement (Chase, 2005, 26). The portraits were notable for
          the way in which they placed the figures in classical settings, associating them with a
          fine art tradition while insisting on the contemporary relevance of those depicted. Cheap
          periodicals such as the <title>Penny Magazine </title>(begun in 1832 by the Society for
          the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge) had already demonstrated both the market for images
          amongst a wide readership and the extant appetite for images that reproduced works of fine
          art. The portraits in the <title>Northern Star</title> were used to build up and maintain
          a base of subscribers. To produce the appropriate amount of copies it was necessary to use
          steel rather than copper engraving, but the process took substantially longer. O’Connor
          announced each portrait with much fanfare through the columns of the <title>Star</title>,
          but then often had to revise both the description of the forthcoming image and the
          estimated date it would be ready as it encountered difficulties in production. Although
          these repeated amendments to the promised image frustrated readers, they also contributed
          to a sense of anticipation. As only about 2000 images could be produced a week, it was
          necessary to distribute them by region, furthering the sense of occasion. As the paper’s
          circulation grew, O’Connor found himself committed to a scheme that was popular with
          readers and beneficial to both the paper and movement as a whole; however, as the numbers
          of readers wanting portraits increased, their demands became harder to fulfil, leading to
          protracted dialogue in the columns of the <title>Star</title>. As the circulation of the
          paper fell in 1842, O’Connor reduced the amounts of images that he offered. Between
          September 1841 and June 1846, only three were issued and these, Chase argues, were a
          reward for loyalty rather than a bid to boost circulation (Chase 2005, 42). In 1848 an
          attempt was made to resume issuing portraits and engravings of the Irish nationalists John
          Mitchell, William Smith O’Brien and T.F. Meagher were issued. Two more were scheduled to
          appear, but were replaced by engravings of the European revolutionaries Louis Blanc and
          Kossuth. The final set of portraits were issued in 1850-1 and featured Robert Peel, a
          group of the Presidents of the United States and two images of the Great Exhibition. For
          further details about the engravings, see Chase 2005.</p>
      </div>   <div>
        <list type="figure-thumb" rend="zoomify">
          <head>Portraits</head>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por13"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por10"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por9"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por11"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por5"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por2"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por12"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por1"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por6"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por3"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por4"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por7"/>
          </item>
          <item>
            <figure url="ns_por8"/>
          </item>
          
        </list>
      </div>
        <div><p>1. Feargus Edward O'Connor after an unknown artist, December 1837. Reproduced by
          permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>2. Henry Hunt, 320 x 260 mm, June 1838. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait
          Gallery.</p>
        <p> 3. William Cobbett, September 1838. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait
          Gallery.</p>
        <p>4. Thomas Attwood, 325 x 254 mm, November 1838. Reproduced by permission of the National
          Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>5. John Frost, 413mm x 281mm, by William Read after unknown artist, September-November
          1839. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>6. Joseph Rayner Stephens, by James Posselwhite after Benjamin, Garside 400mm x 293mm,
          November 1839. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>7. Richard Oastler, by James Posselwhite after Benjamin Garside, 495mm x 365mm, February
          1840. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>8. John Collins, probably by William Read, 414mm x 284mm, Autumn 1840. Reproduced by
          permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>9. Peter Murray McDouall, probably by William Read, 437mm x 314mm, Autumn 1840.
          Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>10. Feargus Edward O'Connor, 457mm x 317mm, December 1840. Reproduced by permission of
          the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>11. Robert Emmet, by William Read after a sketch by James Petrie, 519mm x 365mm, July
          1841. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>12. Thomas Slingsby Duncombe, George Stodart after John Childe, 504mm x 376mm, November
          1842. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait Gallery.</p>
        <p>13. W.P. Roberts, September 1843. Reproduced by permission of the National Portrait
          Gallery.</p>
      </div>
      
      <div>
        <head>Works cited</head>
        <listBibl><bibl>Anonymous, 1838, ‘Leeds, Saturday, May 19’,<title>The Leeds Mercury</title>, 19 May 1838,
          4.</bibl>
          <bibl>S. Roberts, 1995, ‘Who wrote to the Northern Star?’, <title level="m">Duty of Discontent: Essays
            for Dorothy Thompson</title>, ed. by Owen Ashton, Robert Fyson and Stephen Roberts
            (London: Mansell).</bibl>
            <bibl>Chase, M.S., 2005, ‘Building identity, building circulation: engraved portraiture and the
          Northern Star’, in <title>Papers for the People: A Study of the Chartist Press</title>,
              ed. by Joan Allen and Owen Ashton (Merlin Press), 3-24.</bibl>
              <bibl>Epstein, J. A., 1976, ‘Feargus O’Connor and the <title>Northern Star</title>’,
                <title>International Review of Social History</title>, 21, 51–97.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jones, Aled, 2005, ‘Chartist Journalism and Print Culture in Britain, 1830-1855’, in
            <title>Papers for the People: A Study of the Chartist Press</title>, ed. by Joan Allen
                  and Owen Ashton (Merlin Press), 3-24.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Thomspson, Dorothy, 1986, <title>The Chartists: Popular Politics in the Industrial
                    Revolution</title> (Aldershot: Wildwood House).</bibl></listBibl>
        <p>Jim Mussell</p>
      </div>
      












    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
