<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p2_6">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Publishers’ Circular (1837-1959; ncse:1880-1890)</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-31</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><title>Publishers’ Circular</title> and <title>General Record of British and
                        Foreign Literature</title>
                </head>



                <p>The <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>is a trade journal for the publishing
                    industry, and its comment on and display of the trade also provide a context for
                    the other titles in ncse. The <title>Circular was </title>first organised in
                    late 1836, and before the appearance of its official first, sixteen-page issue
                    the following October, two pilots were trialled in April and June 1837. In
                    relation to the span of ncse serials, its launch in 1837 coincides with the
                    demise of<title> </title>our earliest title and its run outlives (and records)
                    them all. However, unlike the contents of the other ncse titles, the content of
                    the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>is not primarily discursive. Its regular
                    issues consist largely of lists, tables, and advertisements that call to mind
                    the origin of serials in records of tide tables, international shipping
                    schedules and news, foreign and domestic fiscal information and the commercial
                    basis of the press. Its title words ‘Circular’, ‘Record’, ‘British’ and
                    ‘Foreign’ invoke this history. Its fortnightly list of current and immanent
                    publications is at the heart of each issue, and its principal orientation is to
                    books. In its 1837 manifesto it makes a distinction between the list which
                    covers all new works, and its adverts which are ‘Connected with Literature and
                    the Fine Arts’. Although Bennett cautions that it was ‘far from complete in
                    listing periodicals’ (25), it did include serials, which are regularly the
                    objects of advertisement (See for example 6 December 1880, 1276-1277, 1280)</p>
                <p>The relation of the <title>Circular </title>to commerce also distinguishes it
                    from the other titles. Its readership was initially primarily within the retail
                    trade and bulk buyers (Eliot and Sutherland 6), to whose members three-thousand
                    copies (the bulk of the print run) were distributed free 1837-1843, after which
                    this policy ended. These included 100 to American and German colleges, 100 to
                    Colonies and army depots, 900 to book societies and literary people, 1000 to
                    country booksellers, 550 to clergymen and Heads of Colleges, and 350 to London
                    booksellers (Eliot and Sutherland 6). The remainder of the print run was on
                    public sale, and available in bulk to retailers for distribution to their
                    customers at the cover price, initially 2d/ issue, but soon 3d.</p>
                <p>The new journal, then, was largely financed by its advertisements from the trade
                    for the trade rather than a combination of advertising revenue and cover price;
                    and, after a downward adjustment to the rates, advertising and revenue
                    flourished. Given that Sampson Low, the first publisher/editor did not own the
                    journal and was paid only by retaining the advertising revenue to set against
                    his costs, he could be expected to be a highly motivated salesman, keen to
                    succeed, and in this hope, his proprietors were not mistaken. Circulating useful
                    information to the trade, as well as to individual readers, the advertising
                    element of the title was from 1851 annually sold to the public at large on the
                    strength of its graphics in special Christmas issues. In December 1880, for
                    example, it contained 108 of the ‘choicest illustrations’ from the ‘Christmas
                    Gift and Presentation Books’, in addition to the usual display advertisements.
                    Not only did the <title>Circular </title>list and advertise potential gifts, but
                    it was itself packaged as a Christmas gift: a month in advance, on 1 November
                    1880, it was advertised as available to retail booksellers in bulk, with
                    ‘Ornamental Wrapper, with Name and Address; but these cannot be secured unless
                    ordered at once’. </p>
                <p>This orientation of the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>to advertising was
                    articulated in the layout of the front page of each issue, an emphasis that
                    remained throughout its nineteenth-century run, through several adjustments of
                    layout. Initially the cover was arranged in four horizontal slabs of type. The
                    identification of print with the dissemination of knowledge, reflecting the
                    trope of the March of Intellect from the 1830s when it was founded, explains the
                    cameo portrait of Francis Bacon which is part of the masthead in the top quarter
                    of this page, with the title of his work, <title>The Advancement of Learning
                    </title>around him, and the title of the publication above the cameo echoing its
                    curve. Below, prominently as the main item on the page, is the Table of
                    Contents. In an issue from 1870 (18 Jan) the Table of Contents includes the
                        <title>subject categories </title>of the works advertised in the same
                    sequence as discursive departments such as ‘Literary Intelligence’. So
                    ‘Classics’ in the Table of Contents refers to <title>Advertisements</title> for
                    classics publications. This representation of the departments of the journal
                    changes by 1880, suggesting a shift in the <title>concept</title> of the
                    publication, though the layout remains similar. Below the Departments, in three
                    columns and smaller type is an alphabetical list of Advertisers that supplements
                    the list of subjects above, and below that is a few lines of ‘Literary
                    Intelligence’ which draws the reader inside the issue. On occasion, this space
                    is instead filled with an address or notice to the trade by the editors, in
                    discursive or advertising form. The notice of the forthcoming Christmas number
                    is located here, for example, 1 November 1880. In the course of the decade,
                    first the bottom layer disappears by 1882, and when in 1887 another layer is
                    transferred inside, it is the Table of Contents, leaving the list of
                    Advertisements on the title page.</p>
                <p>In addition to the Christmas number, other special, seasonally-related, bumper
                    issues were dedicated to Education; they appeared twice a year from 1840 in
                    January and August. Neither the Christmas nor Education issues were Supplements,
                    but they did cost more than the ordinary issue for those dates, which they
                    supplanted. The <title>Circular </title>did publish actual Supplements; from
                    1842 it merged and edited the lists of new publications included in its
                    fortnightly issues in a separate volume published annually. It adopted the title
                    with which we know it, <title>The English Catalogue, </title>only in 1860;
                    beginning as a <title>Catalogue of Books Published in London, </title>it
                    expanded to <title>A Catalogue of Books Published in the United Kingdom</title>
                    in 1845<title>, </title>and to <title>The British Catalogue</title> in 1857.
                    This consolidated for the trade and interested institutions such as libraries a
                    salient portion of the fortnightly issues – the list -- in an annual overview of
                    published works that facilitated retrospective ready reference. Although sold
                    separately, as well in conjunction with the <title>Circular</title>, it is
                    interesting that in practice it is bound into the annual volumes of the serial
                    in British Library copies, the source of the ncse edition. Two other supplements
                    occur on either side of 1880-1890; one monthly addresses foreign literature, which
                    was a special area of interest in Sampson Low’s list (<title>Monthly Bulletin of
                        American, Colonial and Foreign Publications, </title>1869-1873), and the
                    other, also monthly, is dedicated to serials (<title>Publishers’ Circular
                        Newspaper, Magazine and Periodical Supplement, </title>which from issue 35
                    was re-titled <title>The Newsagent’s Chronicle, </title>16 February
                    1895-December 1897; from 1898 it was published by William Dawson and Sons, and
                    appeared independent of the <title>Publishers’ Circular</title>). Although the
                        <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>is represented in ncse by only a decade
                    of its sixty-three year run in the nineteenth century, this fragment occupies a
                    significant percentage of the ncse resource of nearly 100,000 pages. The
                    explanation is that as a bi-monthly it is relatively frequent, that by 1880 it
                    has a large annual supplement (of 108 pp)<title>, </title>and that
                    advertisements regularly swell pagination in special, seasonal issues. Between
                    1880 and 1890 pagination fluctuates from issue to issue, seemingly dependent on
                    the number of advertisements; increases in pagination are not confined to special
                    issues. </p>
                <p>The origins of the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>itself are similar to
                    those of the early proto newspapers in that it was launched and initially owned
                    by a group of interested parties in a single industry in order to foster
                    communication and the circulation of information among them. As Eliot and
                    Sutherland observe (5) not only was it an antidote to the dominant relationship
                    among the joint proprietors of rivalry, but its ‘conductor’/publisher, Sampson
                    Low, saw its potential benefits for workers in the trade, enabling them, for
                    example, to seek and find work. Specific if related interests also figured in
                    the launch of the title in 1837. Low involved the publication with the
                    Booksellers Provident Association founded in the same year, and a shared
                    interest in the policing of underselling united the fourteen proprietors, with
                    Low the Secretary of the Publishers Group they formed to combat this practice.
                    Perhaps it was this matrix of motives that accounts for the distinction between
                    the resultant publication, with its variety of features, and its predecessors,
                    which were primarily catalogues and Advertisers, such as <title>Bent’s</title>,
                    with which the founders of the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>were
                    dissatisfied (Boase).</p>
                <p>From early on the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>included obituaries, and
                    features of each issue well established by 1880 were added over the years,
                    including special issues for education from 1840, correspondence in 1841, annual
                    volumes of the English Catalogue in 1842, annual illustrated Christmas issues
                    from 1851, statistics in spring issues from 1854, and book reviews. (Eliot and
                    Sutherland, 5-6). The other incremental development was the discursive news
                    section of ‘Literary Intelligence’ which begins each number in the ncse edition;
                    ranging from news to gossip, it is a brief few paragraphs at its introduction in
                    1842 and up to seven pages in 1870, having been augmented after 1855 when the
                    repeal of Newspaper Stamp Duty resulted in the proliferation of weeklies (and
                    presumably more news) and then again in relation to the appearance of a rival,
                    the <title>Bookseller, </title>published by Joseph Whittaker in 1858. Sampson
                    Low who from 1837 had published and conducted the <title>Circular </title>for
                    its publisher proprietors, bought them out in 1867, and in 1875 Low retired, and
                    passed the title to the publishing firm Edward Marston, Searle, Rivington, and
                    Robert Marston. Edward Marston who had become Low’s partner in 1856 (E. M., 431)
                    now became its conductor, aided by George Stephen, Stuart J Reid and J A Steuart
                    as editors (Eliot and Sutherland 7/8). But Marston’s sway over the contents had
                    begun twenty years earlier, with the regular inclusion of a variety of
                    statistics in the mid 1850s due to Marston’s genius in this type of knowledge,
                    so popular in this period. Altick’s deployment of the <title>Publishers’
                        Circular </title>in <title>The English Common Reader (</title>108, 358)
                    tacitly acknowledges this aspect of the title, the statistics themselves, but
                    also the publication’s expertise in assessing them. </p>
                <p>By 1880 the front, discursive section of each issue had significantly expanded,
                    and on 2 Feb 1880 consisted of five departments, ‘Literary Intelligence’,
                    ‘Publishers’ Notices of Books Just Issued’ ‘American [News and] Notes’,
                    obituaries, and ‘Books Received’ [ie book reviews], which meant that it offered
                    a specialist focus in the kind of discourse that weeklies such as the
                        <title>Athenaeum</title> were offering to its readers weekly. It then goes
                    on to various types of lists – of Books Published in Great Britain in the
                    preceding fortnight, preceded by an Index to this list, showing those at the end
                    of the production process, now distributed and on the market; these are followed
                    by groups of adverts that calibrate and reveal the latter stages of the
                    production process: Books Now First Advertised as Published, and Books in the
                    Press; it moves to reprises and reprints: New Editions and Books Lately
                    published. ‘Miscellaneous’ includes advertisements for book binders and
                    printers. What follows indicates the status and nature of the trade, as seen in
                    ‘Businesses for Sale’, ‘Assistants Wanted’, and ‘Want Situations’. Finally,
                    there is a glimpse of the secondhand market, in ‘Books Wanted to Purchase’. </p>
                <p>For the decade of the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>included in ncse, the
                    statistics that appear fall into two categories, recurring sets and infrequent
                    sets. The first group includes subjects that are commonly updated over the
                    decade, if not annually: the German Book Trades, United Kingdom newspapers,
                    Import and export of raw and printed materials, and analytical tables of books
                    published in given years. These comprise the core information defined at this
                    time as important adjuncts to the fortnightly lists. Other topics treated
                    statistically more occasionally indicate the locus of the publishers’ world in
                    the decade. They refer to bulk buyers such as national, city and university
                    libraries at home and abroad, classes of books such as the religious book or
                    education texts, format of books, piracy, fine printing, and imports They
                    include the French National Library, publishing in Japan, Cambridge University
                    Library, Continental Libraries, Murray’s Annual Trade Sale, Royal Society of
                    Literature, the Foreign Bible Society, Swiss printing, Glasgow libraries, London
                    Library, USA book trade, Standard Book-size figures, Sale of pirate copies of
                    Ben Hur; Australian exports, American educational books, Imported books, UK
                    education, Publications of the Religious Tract Society and the British and
                    Foreign Bible Society (Eliot and Sutherland 22). These aspects of the market and
                    of production underlie the industry, and the print artefacts we read today. They
                    afford later readers such as ourselves a glimpse of the medium in which
                    nineteenth-century print was lodged, to which William St Clair in <title>The
                        Reading Nation in the Romantic Period </title>refers us, though without
                    taking the periodical press into account.</p>
                <p>By 1880, then, the title had recorded and kept up with the prospering trade,
                    having expanded its usefulness well beyond its fortnightly list. While the
                    presence of the list and the proliferation of advertisements may suggest that
                    the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>is broadly an Advertisers’ Directory
                    (Wiener, 155) and comparable to annual publications such as Mitchell’s, May’s,
                    Sell’s, or Willing’s press directories, its address and its functions in the
                    trade were quite different from the beginning. Book-oriented but inclusive of
                    serials, it was directed not at advertisers but retailers and even the reading
                    public. Its serial frequency ensured its topicality, a pronounced news element
                    up-dated fortnightly, not possible in annual publications. Its content
                    development by 1880, including letters to the editor, reviews of new books,
                    announcements and gossip confirm this serial modality, geared to micro aspects
                    of current events in the trade. On the anniversary of the 1000<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> number on 16 May 1879, Low himself had assessed
                    its history in the journal, giving us a full, timely estimate from which to view
                    the ncse decade. In the 1880s the <title>Circular’s </title>dismissal of John
                    Maxwell’s objections to the allocation of railway book stalls to one bookseller
                    (1 March 1882, 186) and their warm approval of the court case against Vizetelly
                    (1 Jun 1889, 654-655) and his publication of ‘the filthy light literature of
                    France’ [Zola] are indicative of the robust interventions of the editors on day
                    to day issues from their position as representatives of a powerful lobby of
                    businessmen and mainstream publishers. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><title>Publishers’ Circular</title> in ncse</head>
                <p>Sources of the <title>Publishers’ Circular</title> in the ncse edition derive
                    from St Pancras runs. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Works Cited</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Altick, Richard, 1957,<title>The English Common Reader. </title>Chicago:
                        University of Chicago Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bennett, Scott, 1978, ‘Trade Publications’, <title>Victorian Periodicals.
                            A Guide to Research, </title>ed. J. Don Vann and Rosemary T. VanArsdel,
                        New York: MLAA, 24-26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Boase, G. C., 2004, “Low, Sampson (1797–1886).” Rev. M. Clare
                        Loughlin-Chow. In <title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>,
                        edited by H. C. G. Matthew and Brian Harrison. Oxford: OUP.
                        http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/17075 (accessed May 11, 2008).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Eliot, Simon and John Sutherland, 1988, ‘The <title>Publishers’ Circular
                        </title>1837-1900. Guide to the Microfiche Edition’, Cambridge:
                        Chadwyck-Healey. </bibl>
                    <bibl>M., E. [Marston, Edward], ‘Sampson Low’, <title>Publishers’ Circular,
                        </title>1 May 1886, 431.</bibl>
                    <bibl>St Clair, William, 2004,<title>The Reading Nation in the Romantic Period,
                        </title>Cambridge: CUP. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Tye, J Reginald, 1989, ‘The Periodicals of the 1890s’, <title>Victorian
                            Periodicals</title>, ed J.Don Vann and Rosemary T. VanArsdel, Vol. 2,
                        New York: MLAA, 13-31.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wiener, Joel H., 1978, ‘Advertisers’ Directories’, <title>Victorian
                            Periodicals. A Guide to Research,</title> ed. J. Don Vann and Rosemary
                        T. VanArsdel, New York: MLAA, 154-155.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <p>Laurel Brake</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
