<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p2_5">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Tomahawk (1867-1870)</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-31</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>The <title>Tomahawk</title></head>
                <p>The <title>Tomahawk: A Saturday Journal of Satire</title> (1867-1870), founded by
                    Arthur William à Beckett in London, first appeared 11 May 1867, priced two
                    pence. The title of the journal tells us much of what we need to know about it.
                    This was a weekly paper and like most serials in the weekly cycle, it was
                    published on Saturdays, following the model of the popular <title>Saturday
                        Review</title>. The title ‘Tomahawk’ was borrowed from William Makepeace
                    Thackeray, the novelist, satirist, illustrator and editor whose spirit so
                    influenced the men behind <title>Tomahawk</title>; his 1852 novel <title>Men’s
                        Lives</title> describes a journal editor, Mr. Bludyer, ‘the brilliant and
                    accomplished wit, whose sallies in the Tomahawk delight us every Saturday’ and
                    who is known in particular for his savage ‘slasher journalism’, which gives a
                    good indication of the type of sharply barbed, satirical analysis à Beckett
                    sought for his new venture. The image of ‘Tomahawk,’ a noble savage Native
                    American – hatchet in hand, ready to scalp the politicians of the day – became
                    the symbolic, even iconic, mascot for this comic journal. An image of Tomahawk
                    paddling downriver accompanies the mock-heroic <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=FTTW%2F1867%2F05%2F11&amp;page=3&amp;entityid=Ar00300&amp;view=entity"
                        >Preface</xref> to volume one which encapsulates the tone of the serial:</p>
                <p>
                    <q> Through the land of Shams, by the shores of the Dishonest, by the Wigwams of
                        the Heartless and the Faithless. Never swerving from the main course; never
                        turning aside from the arrows of the enemy – from the attacks of the wicked.
                        Always the same. True to himself, just to his fellow creatures, TOMAHAWK,
                        during the First Year of his Mission, has pursued his way fearlessly and
                        honestly. … The coming year will merely reflect the past. Regardless of the
                        taunts of fools, liars, or snobs, he will continue to use his Hatchet has a
                        weapon for the protection of the weak, not (as the enemies would have the
                        world believe) as a knife for the slaughter of the innocent. </q>
                </p>
                <p>The year 1867, when <title>Tomahawk</title> launched in a competitive serials
                    market, was one of transition for Britain, a time ripe for satirical
                    intervention. The second Reform Bill, passed by a Tory government and which
                        <title>Tomahawk</title> supported, renewed hopes for the reform-minded as a
                    whole new class of votes was ushered in at a single stroke. The political map of
                    the country was redrawn instantly, giving a new power to most working class men
                    through the franchise. While not all reform movements of the 1860s met with such
                    success – the recently revitalized women’s suffrage movement, for example, met
                    with short shrift – there was widespread feeling that the passing of the second
                    Reform Bill was an indication of British progress. However, alongside this
                    optimism, there were also significant expressions of social anxiety. Take, for
                    example, Matthew Arnold’s series of articles attacking mid-Victorian
                    ‘Philistinism’ which appeared during the late 1860s in <title>Cornhill
                    Magazine</title>, before being collected as the polemical tract, <title>Culture
                        and Anarchy</title> (1869), whose title suggests the need to prevent social
                    disorder through the imposition of collective culture. Or, consider an article
                    in May 1867 (the same month that the first issue of the <title>Tomahawk</title>
                    was published) in <title>Macmillan’s Magazine</title>, ‘Social Disintegration’
                    by William Rathbone, which worried that the growing gap between rich and poor
                    was ‘an evil of ever-increasing magnitude in its influence on the lives and
                    characters, the moral and physical well-being, of each member of what should be
                    one body politic and religious.’ Ireland was in a state of almost constant
                    unrest about its future; gambling and general rakishness had afflicted the
                    aristocracy; social upheaval seemed once again likely on the continent; and the
                    Queen had seemingly abandoned the throne, still in mourning for the death of
                    Albert years before (indeed, <title>Tomahawk</title> was among the first and
                    loudest to urge the Queen publicly to return to her duty) – if not exactly a
                    turbulent period in British politics, it was certainly a lively and unsettled
                    one, just right for a satirical weekly like <title>Tomahawk</title> which
                    addressed all these subjects at length. As Christopher Kent suggests, ‘satire is
                    a humour of anxiety that is sensitive to symptoms of danger, particularly in
                    times of prosperity’, so the late 1860s was ripe for attack from
                    <title>Tomahawk</title>.</p>
                <p>The periodicals market in the 1850s-1860s was also in transition. After the
                    repeal of the last of the so-called ‘taxes on knowledge’ – taxes on advertising,
                    paper and the stamp duty that had hitherto kept the price of publishing
                    periodicals high – there was something of a periodicals boom in the 1860s, with
                    a particular increase in weeklies, monthly magazines and high-quality
                    illustrated serials. Among the plethora of new journals were family monthly
                    family magazines including the market-leading <title>Cornhill</title> and the
                    religious <title>Good Words</title> and innovative journals of opinion, such as
                    the bi-weekly (then monthly) <title>Fortnightly Review</title> and the daily,
                    evening <title>Pall Mall Gazette</title>. While the <title>Tomahawk</title> was
                    not in competition with these titles directly, the sheer amount of print culture
                    at newsstands vying for the reader’s two pence or shilling is an indication of
                    how fiercely competitive the marketplace for periodicals was.</p>
                <p>
                    <title>Tomahawk</title> was not, of course, the only satirical magazine of its
                    kind in the 1860s, and there was a whole genre with which it had to compete for
                    readers. The market leader and the most high-profile comic periodical was
                        <title>Punch</title>, launched in 1841 by Henry Mayhew and Mark Lemon, which
                    began life as a radical satirical journal, but which by the late 1860s was
                    solidly representing middle class values. Although the most well known to us
                    today, <title>Punch</title> was by no means alone; it spawned many rivals who
                    sought to knock it from its privileged place as the nation’s favourite comic
                    periodical. <title>Fun</title>, often considered the most significant comic
                    weekly after <title>Punch</title>, launched in September 1861; the
                    <title>Owl</title>, founded in 1864; <title>Judy, or London Serio-Comic
                    Journal</title>, launched in the same month as <title>Tomahawk</title>; and
                    there were numerous others, many of them short-lived, including
                    <title>Mirth</title>, <title>Toby</title>, <title>Iris</title>, and <title>Will
                        ‘o the Wisp</title>. <title>Tomahawk</title> not only gestured back to
                        <title>Punch</title>, it looked forward to a new type of journalism that
                    would emerge in the 1870s – society journalism – which focused on the comings
                    and goings of upper class society. ‘The “new” society journalism,’ Christopher
                    Kent reminds us, ‘was more indulgent in tone, detached and somewhat amused by
                    the misdeeds and foibles of the fortunate, tending more to the cynicism of
                    tolerance, than the anger and bitterness of satire.’ (Kent 1998, 85)
                        <title>Tomahawk</title> – with its keen interests in the moral state of the
                    Prince of Wales and n’er-do-well marquises and other aristocrats – suggests
                    something of the journalism that was to become so popular later in the century.</p>
                <p>Given the range of competition, it was important that the upstart
                    <title>Tomahawk</title> defined itself well, and one way of doing this was to
                    enlist a small group of likeminded writers who would broadly agree on the nature
                    of the attacks. As with the cultural formation of many periodicals, the young
                    Arthur à Beckett (only 21 years old when he founded the title) and co-editor
                    Matt Morgan (who also cartooned for <title>Fun</title>) came to rely on a
                    coterie of writers and illustrators, in this case, bohemian figures on the
                    literary scene, men much like themselves. According to Thomas Klemnitz, the
                    staff:</p>
                <p>
                    <q>consisted of talented young bohemian gentlemen, most of whom had been close
                        associates in previous comic weeklies, theatrical work, and the general
                        round of bohemian activities during the 1860’s. The first numbers of the
                            <title>Tomahawk</title> did not carry the name of the editor, and the
                        cartoons were signed only by a tomahawk in a lower corner. But within
                        months, Morgan was regularly signing the cartoons with his full signature,
                        and Arthur a’Beckett added his name to the masthead as editor in the course
                        of the third volume (Klemnitz 1975, 8).</q>
                </p>
                <p>Kent agrees that the men behind <title>Tomahawk</title> – à Beckett, Morgan, à
                    Beckett’s two brothers, Gilbert and Albert, Francis Albert Marshall, Alfred
                    Thompson, Thomas Gibson Bowles, T.H.S. Escott, Alfred Austin and others – were
                    gentleman, middle-class young men who had shared links through public school,
                    university, and the civil service, but also through their interests in art,
                    theatre, music and journalism. The young men of <title>Tomahawk</title> ‘were a
                    close-knit group with a distinct cast of mind, social and political’, broadly
                    conservative and monarchist (Kent 1998, 76). One of the ways they carved out
                    their own niche was by attacking other publications; the men at
                    <title>Tomahawk</title>, as at most satirical periodicals, enjoyed a scrap.
                    Frequently they attacked <title>The Times</title>, the leading organ of the
                    Establishment, for their coverage of Fenianism, but they also picked fights with
                    the conservative <title>Saturday Review</title> (see Matt Morgan’s cartoon, vol.
                    2, <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1868%2F04%2F04&amp;page=7&amp;entityid=Pc00701&amp;view=entity"
                        >4 April 1868</xref>) and the <title>Fortnightly Review</title> (see vol. 3,
                        <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1868%2F07%2F25&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00101&amp;view=entity"
                        >25 July 1868</xref>). These are examples of a larger phenomenon in
                    periodical print culture – that is, periodicals commenting on other periodicals,
                    and using articles elsewhere as springboards for their own discussion – but
                    satirical magazines do this more than most and are more biting in their public
                    exchanges.</p>
                <p>The playful editorial, <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1867%2F05%2F11&amp;page=4&amp;entityid=Ar00405&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Our Preliminary War-Whoop’</xref>, in the first issue doesn’t
                    do much to outline the precise targets for the publication, driven by the
                    essential conservatism of à Beckett and Morgan. Instead, it introduces its
                    satirical tone, with a general warning to all:</p>
                <q>
                    <q>
                        <p>We send abroad our TOMAHAWK as a duty which we cannot forbear. A small,
                            but united, band of Braves, we cannot no longer submit in silence to the
                            meanness, the injustice, and above all, to the humbug which civilised
                            society imposes upon us. We have, therefore, been compelled to dig up
                            the hatchet and send it round to all tribes, so that every true Brave
                            may know that we are out upon the war-path, and that we intend simply to
                            scalp everybody who does not agree with us. Being more or less logical,
                            and therefore pitiless, we spare neither age, sex, nor rank; and
                            whenever we find the pale-faced vices we abhor, we shall do our best to
                            exterminate them. If anybody wants to know our opinions, we may say
                            generally that we are bitter enemies of the whole tribe of Shams, and as
                            for particular application of them, we mean to scalp—</p>
                        <p>Any medicine man who persists in imposing upon us a Reform Bill, which
                            professes to do one thing but really does another.</p>
                        <p>Any demagogues who bring disgrace on the cause of the people by using it
                            for the promotion of their own small notoriety.</p>
                        <p>Any Home Secretary who goes out on the war-path, and then runs away.</p>
                        <p>Any play-wright who either invents or translates stale and unprofitable
                            nonsense.</p>
                        <p>Anybody who contradicts us.</p>
                        <p>And, in fact, everybody who invades our hunting-grounds with the
                            pale-face’s weapons of deceit and fraud.</p>
                    </q>
                </q>
                <p>As the journal hit its stride, its targets were more fixed and<title>
                    Tomahawk</title> distinguished itself from its rivals through greater attention
                    to social issues and foreign affairs and through a more emotional, less
                    party-political response to political issues. To take just one example, its
                    opinions on foreign affairs can be seen nicely in the <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=FTTW%2F1868%2F01%2F04&amp;page=4&amp;entityid=Ar00300&amp;view=entity"
                        >Preface</xref> to volume two (though often in Prefaces thereafter), in
                    which the figure of a witch-like Tomahawk rides across the sky with a long
                    tomahawk as his broomstick, surveying the world. He passes over Russia, ‘drunken
                    with the blood of Poland and thirsting for further territory,’ floats over
                    France where ‘the Usurper has risen like a dream,’ then to Spain, ‘land of
                    decay’ and Italy, ‘home of dishonesty’ and finally to Britain:</p>
                <q>
                    <p>Floating more quickly now—nay, flying, for TOMAHAWK is nearing his native
                        land,—he hovers over London. An empty Palace that should be full; a full
                        “House” that might well be empty. A retired Queen who should be among her
                        people; an active Statesman who should not refuse to retire into the bosom
                        of his family. “Place no patriotism:” Once more the sentiment forces itself
                        upon the mind of TOMAHAWK,--Oh, “Land of the Brave and the Free,” where
                        gross injustice is tolerated, and Society has a code of rules, which
                        manufactures chains for the hands and ruin for the soul!</p>
                    <p>A little further to the West, and TOMAHAWK passes over a spot of green. This
                        is the land of “Paddy”—poor, pig-headed, warm-hearted Paddy. See how pleased
                        he looks. He has just seen our dear Princess Alexandra—that accounts for his
                        smile and his loyalty. </p>
                </q>
                <p>The Prefaces were written at the end of a volume’s run but were used as front
                    matter to introduce and unify themes and contents, to serve as a fluid way of
                    summarizing the political views, foreign and domestic, contained in the volume.
                    As we see in the case of volume two, the primary concerns are various forms of
                    aggression, imperial and otherwise, at home and abroad.</p>
                <p>Among the most prominent topics of discussions relevant to politics at
                    Westminster that <title>Tomahawk</title> addressed was the Irish Question, a
                    cluster of issues related to Anglo-Irish politics relations which centred around
                    the disestablishment of the Irish Church, Irish Home Rule, and the rise in
                    nationalist, Fenian violence (alluded to at the end of the Preface to volume two
                    quoted above). Ireland takes up a great deal of the editorial space in volumes 2
                    and 3, though it haunts all the volumes. The tone in the leading article in the
                        <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1868%2F01%2F04&amp;page=1&amp;entityid=Ar00102&amp;view=entity"
                        >4 January 1868 issue</xref> is typical of <title>Tomahawk</title> manner in
                    addressing Fenian violence:</p>
                <q>
                    <p>No, you are far too great a coward to meet me face to face. However, if you
                        are <title>very</title> brave you will set my house on fire, if you are
                            <title>very</title> tipsy you will do your best to shoot at me from the
                        friendly shelter of a lamp-post. My sweet traitor, my charming ragamuffin, I
                        know you to be an arrant coward, a blustering bully. You have quite enough
                        pluck to murder a woman in cold blood, but you are not the man I take you to
                        be if you don’t turn very very pale when Calcraft gets at your neck at
                        Newgate!</p>
                    <p>And you pretend to be an Irishman!</p>
                    <p>An Irishman! A countryman of some of the greatest men the world has ever
                        seen. A countryman of heroic warriors, skilful statesmen, learned scholars.
                        A country of dear kind hearted Pat, with he ready wit and genial smile. Why
                        I’m proud of my Irish fellow-countrymen, and what do you imagine I think of
                        you? (p. 1)</p>
                </q>
                <p>Similarly disdainful editorial content appears a few pages later in <xref
                        type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1868%2F01%2F04&amp;page=5&amp;entityid=Ar00504&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘A Cure for Fenianism’</xref>, but the topic is most forcefully underscored
                    by Matt Morgan’s cartoon in the same issue – <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1868%2F01%2F04&amp;page=7&amp;entityid=Pc00701&amp;view=entity"
                        >“Mad My Masters, Mad!”</xref> drawing on a scene from Shakespeare’s
                        <title>King John</title> in which Constance (pictured by Morgan as Ireland)
                    kneels before King John (here imagined as John Bull). While this is not one of
                    Morgan’s most powerful images, it does demonstrate the central importance of
                    visual material to the overall message of the periodical.</p>
                <p>Arguably, it was the sophisticated and unique cartoons by Morgan that had the
                    greatest impact in <title>Tomahawk</title>, and for which the periodical is now
                    usually known. A well-known illustrator by the time he came to edit
                        <title>Tomahawk</title> at the age of 31, Morgan had cartooned for
                        <title>Punch</title> and for <title>Fun</title>, gradually developing his
                    own impressive style. While most illustrated satirical magazines contained
                    illustrations, they tended to rely on caricature and stereotype that had the
                    power to convey messages immediately and unambiguously – for example, the stock
                    images of John Bull, Britannia, Caledonia, or the simian-looking Paddy – but
                    Morgan’s cartoons for <title>Tomahawk</title> departed from this mainstream
                    convention. According to Klemnitz, Morgan sought ‘to create a sensation with his
                    popular art, and at <title>Tomahawk</title> he was able to combine daring and
                    controversial subject matter with technical sophistication to produce
                    outstanding cartoons’ (Klemnitz 1975, 10-11). Indeed, it is the technical
                    brilliance that makes these images so striking, certainly when compared with the
                    more familiar cartoons found in, for example, <title>Punch</title>. Morgan had a
                    number of advantages going for him when creating work for
                    <title>Tomahawk</title> – the regular use of double-page, high-impact cartoons;
                    the use of colour in inventive ways; and control of the production process which
                    allowed him to experiment with his engraver and friend, Thomas Bolton (see
                    Klemnitz 1975, 11). All of these factors, combined with Morgan’s bohemian
                    individualism enabled <title>Tomahawk</title> to publish what may be the finest
                    satirical cartoons in any nineteenth-century periodical.</p>
                <p>Morgan succeeded where other less ambitious illustrators didn’t in creating
                    emotionally engaging dramatic images given depth through composition, colour and
                    contrasting chiaroscuro-like tonality. Take the double-page colour cartoon for
                    July 10 1869 – <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1869%2F07%2F10&amp;page=8&amp;entityid=Pc00800&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘“Our Hereditary Legislators”: or, What it may come to. (Dedicated to the
                        rising generation of the House of Lords)’</xref>– which provides a visual
                    statement complementing the first article in the issue, <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1869%2F07%2F10&amp;page=4&amp;entityid=Ar00303&amp;view=entity"
                        >‘Peerless Honour’</xref>, attacking recent scandals in the House of Lords.
                    Morgan’s cartoon provides a Darwinian reading of the peers who are stuck in a
                    kind of gothic, primordial mud while the moon struggles to break through the
                    ominous clouds. Or, consider the double-page colour cartoon for <xref
                        type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1869%2F07%2F31&amp;page=6&amp;entityid=Pc00600&amp;view=entity"
                        >July 31 1869</xref> which addresses the problems in Ireland, in which
                    Morgan creates a similarly atmospheric but more active and dramatic scene – a
                    squabbling Protestant and Roman Catholic are about to lead their boat over a
                    waterfall of ruin, with the caption reading: ‘Christian Charity! Or, They Will
                    Sink the Boat Between Them.’ These are just two examples of the powerfully
                    affecting images that Morgan did best and that came to define the visual content
                    of <title>Tomahawk</title>.</p>
                <p>Looking back at <title>Tomahawk</title> now, it is true that the cartoons are the
                    first thing to catch the eye – the colour, the double pages, the unique dramatic
                    intensity of the composition, the sharpness of the critique. The images
                    complement the clever, often thoughtful words on the page. This was a carefully
                    thought through periodical, from its Prefaces to its impressive Almanacs, with
                    tremendous energy and verve, as readers noted from the moment of its audacious
                    launch. It’s perhaps curious, then, that despite the extraordinary competition
                    in the marketplace, <title>Tomahawk</title> only lasts for six volumes. The
                    truth is, we don’t yet know why – on 30 July 1870 – the periodical came to a
                    ‘mysterious and abrupt end’, as Kent describes it. A Beckett went on to work at
                        <title>Punch</title> and Morgan ended up in North America; of the other
                    regular contributors, one became poet laureate, another became a successful
                    writer of farces, still others leading and important journalists. In short,
                    there is much more research still to be done on the magazine; our hope is that
                    by providing access to the journal in digitized form, explorations in the world
                    of <title>Tomahawk</title> will be greatly enabled, allowing new ideas to emerge
                    about its cultural formation, its significance and its relationship to the
                    broader field of nineteenth-century journalism.</p>
            </div>
            <div>

                <head>The <hi rend="italic">Tomahawk</hi> in ncse</head>

                <p>This edition of the Tomahawk was filmed from the hard copy held at the British
                    Library newspaper collection at Colindale. As microfilm renders colours
                    monochrome, and the creation of digital images sometimes fails to render the
                    subtle changes of contrasts, the quality of many of the cartoons deteriorated
                    after digitisation. Although the microfilm operators attempted to compensate
                    when they thought a particular image might not film well by altering the
                    contrast, they had no way of assessing whether this was effective. As a result,
                    many of the cartoons were either too light or too dark, usually where the
                    engraving was executed on a blue ink wash. To compensate for this we surveyed
                    the images in <title>Tomahawk </title>to work out which were the worse affected.
                    With the cooperation of the British Library we obtained new digital images
                    filmed directly from the hard copy. In these images it is possible to fully
                    appreciate the different colours and tones that Morgan used to create the
                    striking cartoons.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Works Cited</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Kent, Christopher, 1998, ‘The Angry Young Gentlemen of
                        <title>Tomahawk</title>,’ in <title>Victorian Journalism: Exotic and
                            Domestic Essays in Honour of P.D. Edwards</title> ed. By Barbara Garlick
                        and Margaret Harris (Queensland University Press), 75-94.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Klemnitz, Thomas Milton, 1975, ‘Matt Morgan of “Tomahawk” and English
                        Cartooning, 1867-1870,’ <title>Victorian Studies</title> 19:1, 5-34.</bibl>
                    <bibl>VanArsdel, Rosemary T., and J. Don Van, 1994, <title>Victorian Periodicals
                            and Victorian Society</title> (Scolar Press).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <p>Mark Turner</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
