<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_1">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Choice of the cluster</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>



            <p>The selection of six titles for the ncse edition out of the possible 30-50,000
                estimated to have been published in the period by John North (in the <xref
                    type="external" url="http://www.victorianperiodicals.com">
                    <title>Waterloo Directory</title>
                </xref>) is by definition somewhat arbitrary. Several objectives governed our
                choice. In so far as we were interested in the nature of the press itself and the
                cluster of journals, we were keen to choose titles that represented a variety of
                types of serial. We have included a newspaper as well as periodicals; frequencies
                vary: monthly, weekly, and fortnightly; titles emanate from the North as well as the
                South, and there are pictorial papers as well as non-illustrated titles. We have
                also tried to gender the cluster, showing the masculinity of the majority of the
                press and including an early feminist title.</p>
            <p>The cluster comprises a selection of general periodicals, ‘class’ titles, and a trade
                paper, and the trade is publishing. Moreover, we have selected titles that together
                span the century, with a few overlaps. Many of these papers involve individual
                figures – editors or journalists - whose names are still recognisable to students of
                the nineteenth century: the Unitarian minister William J. Fox, the MP Feargus
                O’Connor, the journalist George Henry Lewes, the female activists Jessie Bourcherett
                and Emily Faithfull, and the a Becketts family of engravers. There is some range of
                class, but what we have not included is the radical, cheap, unstamped or popular
                press. Still, it is probably untrue that all of the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> titles
                fall into what was called by contemporaries ‘the higher journalism’, as the
                    <title>Northern Star</title>, steeped as it is in activist politics around the
                Charter, is on the borders of the popular press, despite its high price.</p>
            <p>These types of serial, in all their variety, attach to key strains of
                nineteenth-century cultural life. Thus in the <title>Monthly Repository</title>
                (1806-1837) we chose a theological/religious/philosophical journal, associated with
                reform and vigorous debate around issues of belief. Our earliest title, it is
                steeped in eighteenth-century models of organisation and notions of a community of
                serial contributors, whereby letters from correspondents made up the copy in its
                early period. The <title>Northern Star</title> (1837-1852), originally from Leeds,
                is a weekly broadsheet newspaper, rooted in Chartism and political organisation
                across the country; distributed partly at political meetings in a variety of urban
                centres of industry, with its focus on parliamentary and social reform. The
                    <title>Leader</title> (1850-1860) is a type of weekly newspaper, in three-column
                folio, distinctive from the broadsheet example of the newspaper press as exemplified
                by the <title>Northern Star</title>. Similarly committed to political reform, and
                overlapping chronologically with the <title>Northern Star</title>, the
                <title>Leader</title>, however, is open generally to exploration of radical reform
                rather than focussed on a single extant campaign. It also contains a political front
                and an arts back, in which literature, poetry and fiction appear, as well as reviews
                of books, art, theatre and music. The <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> is a
                monthly, and one of the earliest committed to women’s rights in the nineteenth
                century, in particular to the education and employment of women. In so far as it was
                published from early on by the Victoria Press, Emily Faithfull’s outfit that trained
                women in aspects of the print trade, it also draws attention to the cultural
                industry of serial production. The other point about the <title>English Woman’s
                    Journal</title> is its link not with a formal issuing body, such as the
                Unitarians, the SDUK, or the Chartists, but with a small group of political
                activists, the Langham Place Group. <title>Tomahawk</title> is here as part of the
                tradition of satirical, illustrated papers, a short-lived, more radical contemporary
                of <title>Punch</title>, involving a family of former <title>Punch</title>
                engravers.</p>
            <p>It gives <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> an opportunity to engage with the pictorial press.
                Lastly, we chose a decade of the <title>Publishers’ Circular</title>, as a
                fortnightly trade paper, involved with aspects of the industry responsible for the
                other titles in the project. We were reluctant to include earlier issues of this
                publication, when it consisted largely of advertisements, so we selected a decade
                towards the end of the century, when it had begun to incorporate narrative
                commentary to accompany the elaborate map of the industry represented by the
                advertisements, and which featured the seasonal efflorescence of Christmas numbers.
                It also includes the most elaborate supplement of all, the annual English Catalogue,
                which bears witness to the close relation between the publication of serials and the
                book trade.</p>












        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
