<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_9">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Core</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The ‘Core’ refers to a selection of about 30,000 pages of serial text on which
                multi-level processing and editing was to have been carried out. It was developed in
                the autumn and winter of 2005/6 and it was abandoned by the spring. Nevertheless,
                the process of the selection of criteria for the core enabled the team to
                familiarise itself further with the characteristics of the six titles, individually
                and as a cluster in the edition, to hazard identification of defining elements of
                serials, and to test the degree to which these were shared by our diverse titles.</p>
            <p>In the trajectory of development of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> the Core was Plan B. It was devised
                in response to two assumptions that changed. The first was that the project would
                consist of 30,000 pages of text. The discovery of the multiple editions prompted us
                to revise this estimate to around 110,000 pages. As this almost tripled the amount
                of pages that we would have to review, edit, and markup we began to reconsider the
                amont of manual editorial work it would be possible to do. The second assumption was
                that the model of multi-level processing envisaged by the team and Olive software,
                in which segmentation would be carried out on items and the departments in which
                they were nested, could be perfected and adopted. On the understanding that
                multi-level processing could only be managed and afforded on 30,000 pages the
                research team decided to devise a selection process that would provide a manageable
                sub-section of the resource on which these advanced editorial and computational
                methods could be applied. Affording was a matter of time for Olive, CCH, and the
                research team as well as cost.</p>
            <p>While the core was to be a diagnostic space on which intensive processing and editing
                would be demonstrated, and possibilities of electronic publication of serials
                explored, the entire resource (i.e. all 100,000 pages) would also be released to
                users in readable and, on a basic level, searchable form so that the Core would be
                accessible in its serial contexts.</p>
            <p>Four criteria were selected for inclusion of resource in the Core. They were:</p>
            <list type="bulleted">
                <item>the beginning and ending of each generic title</item>
                <item>moments of change of editor</item>
                <item>proportional representation of visual elements in the cluster</item>
                <item>thematic content: court prosecution for libel and sedition of editors</item>
            </list>
            <p>The resulting tranche was then finessed with respect to further criteria:</p>
            <list type="bulleted">
                <item>chronological spread across the century</item>
                <item>title spread, and some attempt to reflect the proportion of the edition that
                    individual runs represented</item>
                <item>continuity: in order to minimise fragmentation of the resource and to honour
                    continuity as a basic principle of seriality, we decided that the smallest
                    fragment would be a calendar year. </item>
                <item>Inclusion of multiple editions: it was decided to represent multiples at
                    moments of overlap between titles. 1837-8 (<title>Monthly Repository</title> and
                        <title>Northern Star</title>) and 1850-2 (<title>Northern Star</title> and
                        <title>Leader</title>)</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Core was abandoned in the spring of 2005 for several reasons. First, the research
                team and Olive came to the conclusion that multi-level processing was too difficult
                to achieve at acceptable standards within the time and budget at our disposal.
                Instead, we worked out a way to deliver the characteristics of dual level processing
                (i.e. items and departments) on the basis of single level processing and metadata
                entry. In the summer of 2005 Olive offered to process the whole 100,000 pages to
                this specification. We needed to decide whether we would go for the smaller
                processed core, on which we could do more intensive editing or a larger more
                consistent resource on which all parties could do less. Deliberations among the
                research team and the larger project team took place, and an assessment of automatic
                processes of text mining, entity extraction, and semantic tagging was made. The
                other criterion was the interest of our users and the larger world of electronic
                resources of nineteenth-century print. This combination of criteria led us to
                abandon the Core, and go for uniform processing across 100,000 pages.</p>
            <p>We developed various graphic representations of the Core, which are available <xref type="redist" from="pdf/core_distribution.pdf">here</xref>
                [PDF file]; there is also a fuller explanation of the Core in a
                research paper available <xref type="redist" from="pdf/2006_ncse_symposium.pdf">here</xref> [PDF file]. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
