<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_10">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Concept Mapping</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>



            <p>One of the original goals of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> was to map thematic content
                across the edition. However, the edition was not chosen to be thematically coherent,
                although biases are evident in the selection: click <xref type="internal"
                    from="p5_1">here</xref> to read more). Rather, we wanted to demonstrate
                connections that would inevitably occur among the contents of the titles. The
                concept maps were to provide the means to trace these connections, offering an
                alternative way of placing the titles within the culture that produced them.</p>
            <p>Between April and August 2005 the research team met to begin building a concept map
                for the edition. Taking a sample of each periodical in turn, the team tried to
                identify key themes of the articles that each contained. As the series of meetings
                progressed, we began to build up a vocabulary of possible concepts and grouped them
                under main headings. As the concepts were derived from our readings of the serials,
                they were expressed in the language used by our nineteenth-century actors. For the
                concept map to be fully realized, we began to organize these nineteenth-century
                concepts under terms that would be familiar to our users today. So, whereas the
                <hi rend="italic">Leader</hi> referred to the ‘woman question’ (for instance, <xref type="external"
                    url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1856%2F03%2F29&amp;page=15&amp;entityid=Ar01501&amp;view=entity"
                    >here</xref>), we retained this term but placed it in a wider category of
                ‘Gender’. In this way the concept map organized the thematic content according to
                nineteenth-century categories, and then mapped these onto contemporary terms.</p>
            <p>We developed some further principles to help us build the map, which related to our
                understanding of the character of the software. Our map was constrained to three
                levels, with the lowest (level three) the nineteenth-century term and the highest
                (level one) a term recognizable to users. Neither the top or the bottom terms were
                able to link horizontally: level three terms could only link to level two; and level
                one could only link to level two. Level two terms were designed to gather together
                level three terms, but also to provide more delimited categories than level one
                terms. We permitted horizontal linking (i.e. connecting two level two concepts
                together) as a way of bringing the two relationships together (i.e. the
                relationships between nineteenth-century concepts and the relationship these have to
                twenty-first century concepts), but found in practice that this was not necessary.</p>

            <p>Even on the basis of six samples (one from each title) of two or three pages, the map
                rapidly became very complex. In the seminars we modelled it using coloured pieces of
                paper tacked on a whiteboard. We then used <xref type="external"
                    url="http://cmap.ihmc.us/">cmap</xref> to model this electronically. To see the
                map as a pdf document, click <xref type="redist" from="pdf/concept_map.pdf"
                >here</xref>. We planned ultimately to render the map as a database, making it
                easier to trace the connections between terms. However, in our final concept mapping
                seminar, we began to appreciate how time-consuming it was to apply the map to the
                serials. We were working with the <hi rend="italic">Northern Star</hi>, a publication that consists of many
                short articles with a few longer accounts of meetings, trials, and processions.
                Short articles were difficult to characterize as they tended to be very oblique.
                Recovering what they meant would involve a great deal of research. Although the
                longer articles were easier to classify, they took longer to read. A further problem
                was the repetition of terms. We found, particularly when working with the <hi rend="italic">Northern Star</hi>, that certain types of articles or departments always fell under the same
                categories. As it was about this time when we began to appreciate the actual scale
                of the edition, we were forced to re-evaluate the feasibility of marking-up content
                by hand.</p>
            <p>During discussions about the core (for more details about the core, click <xref type="internal"
                from="p5_9">here</xref>) we remained committed to implementing some sort of concept mapping.
                The core provided us with a delimited set of content upon which it was possible to
                undertake hand mark-up. When we rejected the core, we also rejected any metadata
                that would have to be applied by hand at item level, making concept mapping
                impossible. Although we considered focusing on particular departments within issues
                (for instance leading articles) as a way of providing a rationale for delimiting our
                100,000pp of content, we were reluctant to privilege certain portions of issues at
                the expense of others. Instead, we began to investigate what it was possible to
                achieve using computational and statistical methods. UCREL’s (University Centre for
                Computer Corpus Research on Language) semantic tagger (called USAS) was able to
                produce lists of keywords from its own ontology, that attempted to indicate meanings
                in an individual article. We had initially thought that these keywords might be
                mapped to our concepts but, when we compared the two ontologies, we found the
                significant differences to be at level three (the nineteenth-century level). The
                semantic tagger uses the statistical occurrence and use of words to rank terms from
                its hierarchy: this means that when we applied it to nineteenth-century material it
                was attempting to process nineteenth-century language according to twenty-first
                century parameters. There was thus no effective way to link the keywords to our
                level three terms, which were nineteenth-century categories. We refined the keyword
                lists produced by the semantic tagger and they appear as the ‘Subject’ metadata that
                users can browse from the homepage or access for any items in the edition. To read
                more about this, click <xref type="internal"
                    from="p5_7">here</xref>.</p>








        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
