<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_11">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Metadata</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>


        <body>
            <div>
               
                <p>The addition of metadata to the contents of <hi>ncse </hi>was challenging. Not
                    only was there around 100,000 pages of content to which we had to add
                    information, but this content was structured in a complex hierarchy, creating
                    tiers of metadata at edition, title, volume, department and article level. This
                    page gives an account of how we addressed this challenge, as well as full
                    details of the resulting <hi>ncse </hi>metadata schema.</p>
                
                
                <div id="sch">
                    <head>
                        ncse Metadata Schema
                         
                    </head>
                    <p>The existing ncse metadata scheme is as follows:</p>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label"> Field: </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Description: </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Method </cell>
                            <cell role="label"> Applies to: </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Uniform periodical title</cell>
                            <cell>This describes the label given to the whole of a title, regardless
                                of changes over the run.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Actual periodical title</cell>
                            <cell>Gives the title as it appears on the masthead. Equivalent to
                                Dublin Core ‘Title.’</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Date</cell>
                            <cell>Gives the date of publication (as far as known). Equivalent to
                                Dublin Core ‘Date.’</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Source</cell>
                            <cell>Labels content as part of ncse Equivalent to Dublin Core ‘Source.’ </cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Volume number</cell>
                            <cell>Gives the volume and series number of the issue</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Issue number</cell>
                            <cell>Gives the number of the issue</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Edition</cell>
                            <cell>Labels the issue as being a particular edition (town, country,
                                1-9)</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Number of editions</cell>
                            <cell>Give the number of editions of an issue.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Image description</cell>
                            <cell>Gives a number of keywords that describe what the image contains.
                                Drawn from DMVI schema.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Price</cell>
                            <cell>Gives the price of an issue if known.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bibliographic location</cell>
                            <cell>Labels an article as appearing in the wrapper or in the issue
                                itself.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Size</cell>
                            <cell>Gives the paper size of an issue. Equivalent to Dublin Core
                                ‘Size.’</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>issue &gt; department &gt; item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Editor</cell>
                            <cell>Labels issues with the name of their editor.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>not used</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Publisher</cell>
                            <cell>Labels issues with the name of their publisher.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>not used</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Department genre</cell>
                            <cell>Labels departments with a genre descriptor.</cell>
                            <cell>hand / text mining</cell>
                            <cell>not used</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Department title</cell>
                            <cell>Labels departments with a title.</cell>
                            <cell>hand</cell>
                            <cell>not used</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Page number</cell>
                            <cell>provides a page label that corresponds to that printed</cell>
                            <cell>hand / script</cell>
                            <cell>page</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Names</cell>
                            <cell>Identifies all the people mentioned in the edition </cell>
                            <cell>named entity extraction</cell>
                            <cell>item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Institutions</cell>
                            <cell>Identifies all the institutions mentioned in the edition</cell>
                            <cell>named entity extraction</cell>
                            <cell>item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Places</cell>
                            <cell>Identifies all the places mentioned in the edition</cell>
                            <cell>named entity extraction</cell>
                            <cell>item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Genre</cell>
                            <cell>Marks up items that correspond to a list of predefined genre</cell>
                            <cell>text mining</cell>
                            <cell>item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Events</cell>
                            <cell>Marks up items that correspond to a list of predefined events</cell>
                            <cell>text mining</cell>
                            <cell>item</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Subject</cell>
                            <cell>Labels items with subject keywords. Drawn from USAS.</cell>
                            <cell>USAS semantic tagger</cell>
                            <cell>item</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>When making the decision whether or not to include multiple editions (for
                        information on this decision click <xref type="internal" from="p5_6"
                        >here</xref>) we also explored a variety of strategies to automate as much
                        of the metadata entry as possible. There were three moments when metadata
                        was added to content, and at each moment a combination of human and
                        automated input was employed. Where a field was not used, this was usually
                        because experiments proved unsuccessful or we did not have the time to do
                        the necessary research. Full details of these methods are below; however,
                        one of the strategies we implemented in order to save labour is relevant
                        here. In order to reduce the amount of manual data entry we designed the
                        facility for metadata to be inherited from issue to department and then to
                        item level. In the schema above, you can see the ways in which we took
                        advantage of this so as not to have to fill the same field for each item
                        within a department or issue. </p>
                </div>
                <div id="his">
                    <head>
                        History of the ncse metadata schema
                        
                    </head>
                    <p>In the early stages of the project we undertook a survey of the material to
                        try and understand what possible data categories we could identify in
                        serials and how they related to each other. The result was a very complex
                        diagram that can be downloaded <xref type="redist" from="pdf/data_map.pdf">here</xref>. Even given our
                        initial estimates of the scale of <hi rend="bold">ncse </hi>we recognized
                        that this was an unreasonable amount of data and set about creating a more
                        manageable schema.</p>
                    <p>Our early designs broke the diagram down into a number of areas:
                        bibliographic metadata; structural metadata; generic metadata; advanced
                        metadata; and concept mapping:</p>
                    <div>
                        <head> Bibliographic metadata </head>
                        <p>This applied both to the serials and the digital resource. Fields
                            included ‘title’ (of article), ‘creator’ (of article or digital
                            resource), ‘date’ (of article or digital resource), ‘publisher’ (name
                            and place of publisher of article), ‘printer’ (name and place of printer
                            of article), ‘editor’ (or article or digital resource), ‘pagination’
                            (span of the article), ‘price’ (of the issue), ‘creator’ (of digital
                            resource), ‘format’ (of digital resource), ‘origin’ (of digital
                            resource, i.e. ncse). In creating these fields we referred to the Dublin
                            Core schema in attempt to ensure compatibility.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head> Structural metadata </head>
                        <p>The structural metadata fields were designed to indicate where a
                            particular item occurred in the edition and what its relationships to
                            other constituent parts were. Fields included ‘given title’ (of whole
                            run), ‘actual title’ (i.e. that printed on the masthead of a single
                            issue), ‘series number’, ‘volume number’, ‘edition’ (intended to label
                            which edition a particular component occurred within), ‘prelims /
                            numbers’ (designed to distinguish between items that appeared on front
                            matter and those within issues themselves) label what we would later
                            call front matter), ‘department’, ‘item’</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head> Formal metadata </head>
                        <p>This category was principally designed to accommodate images. Initially
                            we were simply concerned to specify a field that would mark up images,
                            but when combined with bibliographic and advanced metadata we would
                            achieve a fuller description.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head> Generic metadata </head>
                        <p>This was a single field that would label each item with a genre such as
                            advertisements, obituaries, correspondence, leading articles, news etc.
                            We kept this field and used it to explore text mining techniques
                            strategies for <xref type="internal" from="p5_7">metadata
                        entry</xref>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Advanced Metadata</head>
                        <p>Advanced metadata described those categories that described the content
                            of articles. Initially we conceived these fields as being a form of
                            index, populated by the content of the periodicals. The categories were
                            ‘people’, ‘places’, ‘events’, ‘objects’, ‘publications’, and
                            ‘institutions.’ Although we attempted some experiments to see how long
                            these indexes would take to create by hand, our decision to include
                            multiple editions and so edit an edition of c100,000 pages rendered this
                            impractical. We pursued the advanced metadata categories through other
                            means, however, as you can read in Creating advanced metadata through
                            named entity extraction, text mining and semantic tagging [internal
                            link].</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Concept Mapping</head>
                        <p>Concept mapping was intended to map thematic concepts across different
                            types of content in the edition. For a description of our work in this
                            area click <xref type="internal" from="p5_10">here</xref>. For an
                            account of how we actually implemented thematic metadata go to Creating
                            advanced metadata through named entity extraction, text mining and
                            semantic tagging [internal link].</p>
                        <p>This metadata system was fairly loosely conceived as we designed it
                            alongside experiments in segmentation. Without a clear idea of how we
                            were going to produce digital copy, the form this would take, and the
                            way different components were linked to each other, we could not design
                            a metadata schema or the means for implementing it. </p>
                        <p>As we began to progress with the preparation of content and the
                            segmentation, we also began to refine the metadata schema. Over the
                            course of Autumn 2006 we developed it into a form that more closely
                            resembles the one given above. To download this earlier schema, click
                            <xref type="redist" from="pdf/06.12.28_metadata_table.pdf">here</xref>; to see a visual
                            representation of it click <xref type="redist" from="pdf/06.12.28_metadata_diagram.pdf">here</xref>.
                            As you may note, we had already separated the advanced metadata
                            categories out, and had begun to think carefully about the values that
                            would appear in each field. This was especially problematic for subject
                            and image. At this stage we were not sure how we could classify the
                            content for each category and were exploring various existing schemes,
                            as well as our own concept maps, in order to decide on a strategy that
                            was suitable for the project’s requirements. Accounts of how we
                            developed subject metadata can be read <xref type="internal"
                                from="p5_10">here</xref> and image metadata <xref type="internal"
                                from="p5_4">here</xref>.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div id="add">
                    <head>Adding metadata during segmentation</head>
                    <p>Once we established the methodology for the production of ncse, we began to
                        analyze the points at which we could implement our metadata schema. Having a
                        more developed workflow allowed us to begin to conceptualize what elements
                        of the structure would be encoded into the xml, and what relationship needed
                        to be labelled with metadata. The first place where we could begin to add
                        metadata was when working with the segmented pdfs to amend the segmentation
                        applied by Olive Software. At this stage we were mainly working to correct
                        the content: making sure the right pages were bound into the right issues;
                        that items were correctly distinguished from each other; and that
                        departments were correctly labelled. The Olive plugin for Adobe Acrobat
                        permits the addition of metadata but, rather than add all the metadata at
                        this stage, we simply used the plugin to make any changes to the page
                        numbers that were allocated to the pages of each pdf document. For more
                        information about page numbers, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_2"
                        >here</xref> .</p>
                    <p>The Olive Administrator Application is a web application that allows you to
                        both organize the content of data repositories and add metadata to parts of
                        it. While the pdfs were being segmented, output by Olive in Israel, and the
                        resulting data then being uploaded onto the server at King’s, we went over
                        the content in order to resolve any outstanding values that needed to be
                        finalized. These lists of values were then loaded into the Olive
                        Administrator Application, allowing our editorial assistants to insert
                        metadata into the xml through a relatively easy to use interface and
                        reducing the amount of metadata entered without a controlled vocabulary. We
                        conceived of the metadata task as two sweeps: one for bibliographic metadata
                        and one for image metadata. We began adding metadata at the end of November
                        2007 and this took a team of six part time editorial assistants until March
                        2008 to complete. For more information about the generation of the
                        vocabulary for the addition of image metadata, click <xref type="internal"
                            from="p5_4">here</xref>.</p>
                    <p>The fields completed at this stage were ‘Uniform periodical title’, ‘Actual
                        periodical title’, ‘Date’, ‘Source’, ‘Volume number’, ‘Issue number’,
                        ‘Edition’, ‘Number of editions’, ‘Image description’, ‘Price’,
                        ‘Bibliographic location’, ‘Size.’ As you can see from the schema above and
                        from Viewpoint, this is the bulk of the metadata in <hi rend="bold"
                        >ncse</hi>, and all the metadata that we entered by hand. These fields
                        attach important bibliographic metadata to all items within the edition that
                        labels them as to their relationship with each other, allowing complex
                        searches across the edition and the production of bibliographic citations in
                        search results.</p>
                </div>
                <div id="cre">
                    <head>Creating advanced metadata through named entity extraction, text mining
                        and semantic tagging</head>
                    <p>The fields that remained were those that started out as advanced metadata and
                        concept mapping. For an account of concept mapping click <xref
                            type="internal" from="p5_10">here</xref>. Of the advanced metadata
                        categories - ‘people’, ‘places’, ‘events’, ‘objects’, ‘publications’, and
                        ‘institutions’ – we had selected ‘people’ (as ‘names’), ‘places’,
                        ‘institutions’, ‘genre’, ‘events’, and ‘subject’ to pursue. We used <xref
                            type="external" url="http://gate.ac.uk/">GATE</xref> to extract a list
                        of proper nouns, which we sorted using a combination of sources including
                        the indices from John North’s <title>
                            <xref type="external" url="http://www.victorianperiodicals.com/"
                                >Waterloo Directory of English Periodicals and Newspapers,
                            1800-1900</xref>
                        </title>. On the basis of this work we were confident on producing indexes
                        of names, places and institutions. We attempted to use text mining
                        techniques to see if we could find a way of marking up ‘events’ and ‘genre’,
                        but were unable to obtain results that could be applied across the edition.
                        For ‘subjects’ we used UCREL’s (University Centre for Corpus Research on
                        Language) <xref type="external" url="http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/usas/"
                        >USAS</xref> (UCREL Semantic Analysis System) tagger to provide semantic
                        tags for individual articles, which we then refined to present to users. For
                        a fuller account of this research click <xref type="internal" from="p5_7"
                            >here</xref>.</p>
                </div></div>
            
        </body>




    </text>
</TEI.2>
