<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_7">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Text Mining</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>When the decision was made to process a segmented edition of 100,000 pages, we
                realized that we would be extremely limited in the amount of manual mark up that it
                would be possible to do. This prompted us to rethink the metadata strategy for both
                the bibliographic and advanced metadata. For more on these, click <xref
                    type="internal" from="p5_11">here</xref>. The advanced metadata was intended to
                provide a set of terms that would allow us to interrogate the edition in different
                ways from the more familiar process of searching text and browsing bibliographic
                information. Initially, we imagined concept maps that would demonstrate the thematic
                connections between articles, metadata that would identify the names of people,
                publications, institutions, place and events mentioned in articles, and metadata
                that would label the genre of a particular item. With over 400,000 items to markup,
                we had to explore other ways of entering this metadata.</p>
            <p>After a series of experiments carried out by Gerhard Brey at the Centre for Computing
                in the Humanities at King’s College London, we settled on the following strategies.
                For persons, places and institutions we would use named entity extraction to create
                lists of keywords. For the concept maps, we would use the USAS (<xref
                    type="external" url="http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/usas/">UCREL Semantic Analysis
                    System</xref>) tagger from the University of Lancaster.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Persons, places, institutions</head>
                <p>This data was created from the textual archive of <hi>ncse</hi> using <xref
                        type="external" url="http://gate.ac.uk/">GATE</xref>. GATE can analyse parts
                    of speech and then discriminate types of content by reference to various
                    authority lists. This means that the terms associated with articles in the
                    edition are based upon uncorrected OCR and delineated according to twentieth and
                    twenty-first century reference sources. After generating the lists, we applied
                    some filters to remove entries that were clearly the result of inaccurate OCR.
                    As the beta version of the project is updated, we will further refine the way
                    the software discriminates between terms in an effort to avoid anachronism and
                    more accurately delineate words as names, places or institutions. At present, we
                    have chosen to present the majority of the results on the basis that it offers
                    users the opportunity to see how the system works and to use their own judgement
                    when evaluating items.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Subjects</head>
                <p>The subject keywords were produced by using the <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/usas/">USAS semantic tagger</xref>. This
                    system uses its own hierarchy of subject classifications and, using
                    computational methods, identifies ranks those terms from the hierarchy that it
                    things are most relevant to the item. We reviewed the results of the tagger, and
                    opted not to display any results that were ranked less than 95 out of 100. As we
                    continue to work on the tagger, we will further refine the terms from the
                    hierarchy that are returned to users.</p>
                <p>For further details about these processes, see the technical introduction <xref
                        type="internal" from="p1_2">here</xref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
