<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_6">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Multiple editions and nineteenth-century print culture</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body><div>
            <div>
                
                <p>When the research team began to look at the resource to create what we called
                    ‘snapshots’ of each of the six titles, we quickly discovered the extent to which
                    multiple editions had been bound in with the regular issues of the
                        <title>Northern Star </title> and the <title>Leader</title>. Although certainly
                    not complete (the inclusion of multiple editions varied over the run), we had on
                    average 2.8 issues per week of the <title>Northern Star </title>and 1.8 issues per
                    week of the <title>Leader</title>. This represented a large increase in the
                    content of the edition, and it had consequences for the amount of detailed work
                    we would be able to do. Items of variations among editions may include, for
                    example, closing (financial) prices; breaking news; locally adjusted news;
                    locally-based advertisements; and a Stop Press column, which updates the
                    contents that was set first. Although most of the multiple editions contained
                    limited material that was unique to that particular edition, we felt that the
                    marginal condition of multiple editions – they were not only excluded from the
                    bound volumes of serials that survive, but they are often excluded from digital
                    editions created today – meant that we should attempt to preserve them. Multiple
                    editions provide more than ‘extra’ content, crowded or left out of the edition
                    that has been bound; they provide glimpses of how the news is disseminated
                    across space and time. As such – and in line with our editorial policy (to read
                    more about this, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_2">here</xref>) – we wanted to preserve
                    these multiple editions for what they revealed about the role of serials in
                    nineteenth-century print culture. In other nineteenth-century titles that
                    publish multiple editions , the amount of variation may be far greater than in
                    the examples in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>. To exclude the multiple editions from our runs of
                    the <title>Leader</title> and <title>Northern Star </title>would be to misrepresent
                    the way in which they were produced.</p>
                <p>Multiple editions force us to confront several circumstances of serial
                    publication. The first is that the date and number information printed on the
                    front of an issue does not necessarily mark that issue as the only version of
                    it. The presence of more than one published version of a particular issue
                    prevents us doing as the information in the masthead suggests and treating it as
                    one manifestation of a longer linear sequence. Rather, we have to allow some
                    serial texts to produce a range of issues, produced at different moments (and
                    often for particular readers), that are all associated with the date and issue
                    number printed on them. For instance, although the <title>Northern Star</title> is
                    a Saturday weekly, the actual issue might have been published on a Thursday
                    evening, Friday morning or Saturday morning or afternoon depending on which
                    edition it was. Equally although issues of the <title>Leader</title> are dated as
                    being published on Saturdays, as the town edition was, the country editions were
                    published the day before, on Fridays. Although the period of both journals is
                    the week, this only applies if you consistently read the same edition, as some
                    of the copy is common to both editions and relates to the week immediately past,
                    while the copy that varies relates to the previous seven days (the town edition)
                    or the week before that, beginning 14 days ago (the country edition).</p>
                <p>The reason multiple editions existed was to accommodate the time it took to
                    distribute printed matter to readers around the country. The practice of issuing
                    town and country editions was fairly common in the daily and weekly press.
                    Usually the first edition was intended for the widest distribution, with
                    subsequent editions providing more up-to-date news for local consumption. The
                    notion of timeliness thus depends on where a paper is bought and where it was
                    issued from. The <title>Northern Star</title>’s third edition was more up-to-date
                    than its first, but was only available in and around Leeds; however, the readers
                    of the <title>Leader’s </title>‘town’ edition – intended for London – had access
                    to more current information than those who received its ‘country’ edition.
                    Although different editions contained items with differing levels of relevancy,
                    they were designed to be consumed more or less simultaneously: readers of the
                        <title>Northern Star </title>in Scotland read Wednesday and Thursday’s news on
                    Saturday, whereas readers in Leeds read Wednesday, Thursday, Friday and
                    Saturday’s news. This is complicated further by the widespread practice of
                    reprinting the news from other printed sources. This introduced a further
                    variable into the temporalities that governed production. Whereas London papers
                    such as the <title>Leader </title>were well-positioned to include the latest news
                    from Parliament or the markets, regional papers had to wait for London news to
                    reach them. For the editors of the <title>Northern Star</title>, this meant
                    waiting for the first editions of the Saturday papers to reach Leeds on Friday,
                    and then rushing them into print to make the final edition late on Saturday.</p>
                <p>Multiple editions – like other forms of <xref type="internal" from="p5_5">paratextual content</xref> – resist the neat ordering to which we often subject serials.
                    Rather than, for instance, there being one issue per week there might actually
                    be two or, in the case of the <title>Northern Star, </title>five. This means that,
                    even if a periodical is paginated continuously throughout a volume, there might
                    actually be a number of versions of the same page. This creates editorial
                    problems: if one is to exclude the multiple editions, which is to represent the
                    issue? If they are to be included, in what order should they be displayed?
                    However, many of these editorial problems arise because of the attempt to fit
                    serials into the linear model of the codex. This is why, for instance, multiple
                    editions are often excluded from the bound volumes of periodicals that survive.
                    In a digital edition there is no need to replicate such a practice: the
                    non-linear nature of digital resources makes them ideal for representing the
                    complex publication patterns of nineteenth-century serials.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Multiple editions in ncse</head>
                <p>The decision to include multiple editions meant an edition of 67,000pp became an
                    edition of almost 100,000 pages. This increase in pagination affected most other
                    stages in the production of the edition: for instance, you can read about one of
                    the plans we considered to manage this <xref type="internal" from="p5_9">here</xref>. </p>
                <p>Once we had made the decision to include multiples we had to consider carefully
                    how we would represent them. The editions clearly interpose themselves at issue
                    level in our structural hierarchy:</p>
                <p>Edition &gt; title &gt; volume &gt; issue &gt; department
                    &gt; item</p>
                <p> One option that we considered was to have a folder for multiple editions in the
                volume folder of the folder tree:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <head>Volume 4</head>
                    <item>edition 1</item>
                    <item>edition 2</item>
                    <item>edition 3</item>
                </list>
                
                <p>However, we felt that this would restrict comparison between editions and would
                    unnecessarily separate editions from the issue to which they were associated.
                    Also, because there is often not a complete run of a single edition, we could
                    not present an unbroken run of issues to users. </p>
                <p>A better solution was to provide access to the multiples from within an issue
                    itself. By nominating one edition as the ‘main’ edition while also marking all
                    editions (including the ‘main’ edition) with metadata labelling it as a multiple
                    edition, we could gesture towards the linearity posited by the issue numbers
                    while also allowing users to access the other editions. The main difficulty in
                    doing this lay in identifying which issue was which and then deciding which
                    edition should act as the main edition. Further information on these decisions
                    is below. However, this strategy was further complicated by the way the Olive
                    system discriminates between content by date. The Olive system understands the
                    content as a series of single issues with the same title but different dates.
                    This caused us problems elsewhere in our delineation of content (click <xref type="internal" from="p5_2">here</xref>
                    to read more about this): for the multiples, which are
                    in effect two separate issues with the same title and same date, it was
                    extremely problematic. Our solution was to make each edition of a particular
                    title a separate publication as far as the system was concerned. So our
                        <title>Northern Star</title> actually consists of nine separate publications,
                    each containing a single edition of the title. </p>
                <p>It is these separate publications that populate the ‘search title(s)’ box of the
                    advanced search. The options that appear within the box are drawn from the
                    folders that structure <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> from ‘behind the scenes’. Although perhaps
                    not very elegant, this does allow users the option to search a particular
                    edition, or any combination of editions, from across the edition. This
                    functionality is in addition to the standard metadata search of the multiple
                    editions available on the right-hand side of the advanced search. As much of the
                    content for a particular issue is repeated between editions, searches within the
                        <title>Northern Star </title>and the <title>Leader </title>are likely to return
                    items that appear to be identical. By labelling all items with metadata that
                    identifies the edition that they are from, it was possible to provide an option
                    in the advanced search that allows users to select which edition they want to
                    search from.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Northern Star multiple editions</head>
                <p>We have up to nine editions for some issues of the <title>Northern Star</title>.
                    However, it is very difficult to know whether these are actual multiple
                    editions, or simply copies of an edition that have been bound into the volume.
                    Sometimes the editor of the <title>Northern Star </title>would indicate items
                    inserted into a later edition with a header such as ‘Second Edition’, but we
                    have no way other than by comparison to establish whether this practice was
                    consistent and exhaustive. Knowing the pressures under which the title was
                    produced all week, as well as the existence of items labelled ‘Second Edition’
                    and ‘Third Edition’ in the same number (see for instance the issue for 12
                    September 1840 <xref type="external" url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1840%2F09%2F12&amp;page=1&amp;view=document">here</xref>),
                    we did not feel that we could use these items to either establish which edition
                    it was that we were dealing with, nor the number of editions that were issued in
                    a particular week. We also could not rely on the archival practices of the
                    British Library at the point of collecting and binding, in the nineteenth
                    century. Although some of the issues in the BL run are hand-marked ‘first’,
                    ‘second’ or ‘third edition’, we lack textual evidence to support this
                    allocation. Also, we know that many issues are missing: we only have a single
                    issue for much of 1840, yet this consists of issues that contain items headed
                    with ‘Second’ or ‘Third Edition.’</p>
                <p>The uncertainty as to which edition is which in the <title>Northern Star</title>
                    limited the extent to which we could label them. As such, we made an editorial
                    decision to keep them in the order in which they appeared within the BL run
                    unless we had textual evidence to support moving them. The <title>Northern
                    Star</title> editions are consequently labelled 1-9, but these labels might not
                    correspond to the actual order in which they were published.</p>
                <p>The actual publication history of the editions of the <title>Northern Star
                    </title>is also difficult to establish. In 1840 the editor, William Hill,
                    published some ‘Brief Rules for the Government of all who Write in for the
                    Paper’ that stated that half of the paper was printed on Wednesday, the other
                    half on Thursday for the publication of the first edition. Items for inclusion
                    that arrive in the Friday morning post will make the second edition published on
                    Saturday. Spreading publication over almost four days allowed the <title>Northern
                        Star </title>to respond to events in a much more timely fashion than if it
                    had only one edition. For instance, often the paper went to press as events were
                    breaking so the editor promised to give further details in a subsequent edition.
                    This implies that readers in one geographic area might buy (or endeavour to
                    borrow) more up-to-date editions of the <title>Northern Star</title> as the week
                    progressed. Also, in 1840 the third editions of the paper, intended for delivery
                    late on Saturday in Leeds and the surrounding region, contained news from
                    London. In the <title>Northern Star </title>for 8 October 1842 the paper reports
                    on the sensational arrest of its editor and proprietor (<xref type="external" url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1842%2F10%2F08&amp;page=6&amp;entityid=Ar00600&amp;view=entity">here</xref>).
                    This had occurred the previous week but the first and most of the second edition
                    had already gone to press. Joshua Hobson, who was standing in for Hill, writes
                    that the ‘press was stepped several times during the course of Friday’, and new
                    matter inserted as it was obtained. However, as this ‘can only have been seen by
                    a few, comparatively, of the readers’ he opts to print all the reports again.
                    The editions the previous week, then, give news as it breaks, distributing the
                    story in different forms of completeness to the <title>Northern Star’s
                    </title>distributed readers. However, to ensure that everyone gets the same
                    version of the news from the <title>Northern Star</title>, it is printed once
                    again the following week, bringing all readers up-to-date.</p>
                <p>In 1844 the <title>Northern Star</title> moved to London, reconfiguring the way it
                    was distributed. In the issue for <xref type="external" url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1844%2F11%2F30&amp;page=1&amp;view=document">30 November 1844</xref>
                    – the same issue that announces a soirée to welcome the paper to the metropolis
                    – there is a note that states the first edition arrives in the country on
                    Saturday morning, with a later edition that will arrive on Sunday. They also
                    publish a late third edition for London on Sunday. Considering the
                        <title>Northern Star’s </title>origins as a Northern paper for the working
                    classes, with different editions for specific geographical areas, this
                    prioritization of London time is significant. Rather than seek to represent the
                    combined interests of workers in the manufacturing districts, this new
                    distribution system privileges both London news and London readers. Although
                    readers outside London could ask to receive later editions in order to get the
                    most complete edition of the paper, this would mean receiving news from outside
                    London – perhaps even their own news – later than those who opted to receive the
                    early editions. This means that London readers would be reading the second
                    edition while country readers were reading the first edition produced the day
                    before. They would also have privileged access to the most recent third edition
                    on the Sunday, possibly containing news for which country readers of the
                        <title>Northern Star </title>would have to wait until the following week.</p>
                <p>By 1851 the circulation of the <title>Northern Star </title>was flagging. In an
                    effort to gain readers its editor, George Fleming, proposed altering its
                    distribution in order ‘to place the Star on an equality with the other
                    metropolitan journals published on the same day, as regards the lateness and
                    variety of its news’. Specifically, this meant abolishing the Scottish edition
                    and delaying the first edition until Friday evening. The extension of the
                    railways would make it possible for Scottish readers to get this edition with
                    other readers from outside of London, bringing them within a day of London news.
                    This edition would be complemented by a Saturday edition for London and the Home
                    Counties. Unlike the change in publishing patterns in 1844 there is no list of
                    deadlines by which regional correspondents must send in copy; instead Fleming
                    proposes keeping correspondence short during the Parliamentary session in order
                    to concentrate on its proceedings. By 1851 then, the <title>Northern Star
                    </title>explicitly associates itself with the London weekly press: in fact, from
                    this point on, it publishes a ‘town’ and ‘country’ edition in the same as the
                        <title>Leader</title>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Leader multiple editions</head>
                <p>The first issue of the <title>Leader </title>in the British Library run that we
                    know had more than one edition is the fourth, dated 20 April 1850. There is a
                    note in this edition above the ‘Postscript’ – a department between ‘News of the
                    Week’ and the leading article in which the latest news was inserted – that
                    states that it first appeared in the second edition of the previous week. The
                        <title>Leader </title>published two editions: the first was for the country,
                    and contained the ‘Postscript’ from the previous week; and the second was for
                    the town, and contained a new ‘Postscript’ with the latest news. There is no
                    note in the second (town) editions, only the country: as there is no note in the
                    first three issues of the <title>Leader </title>in our run, they are either town
                    editions, or the only edition published. From the eighth issue, dated 18 May
                    1850, the edition is marked on the bottom of the first page.</p>
                <p>In publishing two editions a week the <title>Leader </title>was following a
                    well-established trend among London weeklies. The railways made it possible to
                    publish an edition on a Friday and distribute it around the country for reading
                    on Saturday. This edition was then complemented by an edition published on
                    Saturday with a smaller locus of distribution: usually London and the
                    surrounding area. This pattern posits two types of readership: the metropolitan
                    reader, who has news that is current up to the day before, and the country
                    reader, who is a day behind in news, and a week in Postscript and prices. The
                    designation ‘country’ does not discriminate between the rural areas and the
                    other cities in Britain; instead, they are all simply not London.</p>
                <p>The <title>Leader</title> published its country edition from two o’clock i Friday
                    afternoon and its town edition from half past one of the following Saturday.
                    This extra day allowed the insertion of the previous afternoon’s news, usually
                    in the ‘Postscript’ department. This late news was of limited use to those
                    readers who took the country edition and so received it with the following
                    week’s news. By 6 December 1851 a <xref type="external" url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1851%2F12%2F06&amp;page=11&amp;entityid=Ar01106&amp;view=entity">note</xref> ‘To Readers and Correspondents’ appears
                in which subscribers are asked ‘which edition they wish to receive’, given the
                    later publication date of the town edition; country readers have to choose
                    whether they receive the <title>Leader </title>late, on Mondays, with its up to
                    date news and prices, or read it ‘on time’ on Saturdays, with last week’s
                    updates and prices. On 29 January 1853 the editors recognize that some country
                    readers have objected to the lateness of this news, and announce that they will
                    only publish one edition from then on. However, a comparison between the two
                    editions in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> reveals that the ‘Postscripts’ still vary between
                    editions, sometimes appearing in both, but sometimes only appearing in one.
                    Rather than distribute identical copy to readers in London and readers
                    elsewhere, the editors of the <title>Leader </title> are often prompted to insert a
                    ‘Postscript’ but do not reproduce this content for the country readers in the
                    following edition. Readers receiving the country edition, therefore, would never
                    know if they were getting all of the news.</p>
                <p>This practice continues intermittently until issue number 247, dated 16 December
                    1854. From this point on the ‘Postscript’ appears in both editions that we have,
                    suggesting that identical copy was being distributed across the country.
                    However, as these issues are not marked with an edition, we have no way of
                    determining if they are two editions, or simply copies.</p>
            </div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
