<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_5">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Paratextual Material</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Serials are often imagined as neat series of issues, unfolding in a linear fashion
                and gathered into volumes at fixed intervals. This impression is reinforced by the
                way in which many serials survive in library archives: however, often material bound
                into volumes hints at a different publishing history. On this page you can read more
                about such material and what it means for the print culture of both the six titles
                in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> and nineteenth-century print culture more broadly.</p>

            <div>
                <head>Multiple Editions</head>

                <p>Two of our six publications published more than one edition per issue. The
                    presence of multiples editions reminds us that although individual issues were
                    marked with a date and an issue number, there might be more than one edition of
                    them. This means that although the issues seem to indicate that they be placed
                    in a series, with one issue per date of publication, to create such a series
                    would involve a decision to choose one particular edition over another to
                    represent that issue. Often the runs that appear as bound volumes (or indeed in
                    digital editions) are composites, consisting of different editions with their
                    differences effaced. In <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> we have tried to maintain the
                    distinction between editions and, although we have had to privilege one edition
                    in our resource, we have made all the editions that we have located available to
                    users. For more information on multiple editions, click <xref type="internal"
                        from="p5_6">here</xref>.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Supplements</head>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">ncse </hi>contains a range of material that is supplementary to the dated
                    and numbered issues that make up the majority of the runs of our six titles.
                    These supplements include ‘extra’ issues, promotional material, coverage of
                    special projects or, in some cases, whole new publications. Although the issue
                    numbers and dates on individual issues indicate their primacy in the series,
                    suggesting that they are the main constituents of a title, the presence of this
                    other published material reminds us that the identity of a particular serial
                    does not end with the dated and numbered issues. Rather, although supplements –
                    as supplements – are in addition to the dated and numbered issues, they still
                    remain constitutive parts of the content of the title: indeed, often they are
                    explicitly extensions of it, permitting the text to extend beyond the boundaries
                    of the single issue. Supplements may be gratis or priced. The impetus for their
                    issue is varied, perhaps celebrating an internal anniversary (their first year),
                    or a public event (the death of Wellington or the repeal of the Newspaper Tax)
                    or a consumer/advertising opportunity, eg Christmas Books. </p>
                <p>The economy that underpins serial production is one of space. Proprietors are
                    selling printed paper, and the contents of these pages determines their
                    financial return either by attracting readers or advertisers. The space
                    available in a single issue of a serial was predicated on the size of the sheet
                    of paper on which it was printed. If there was more content than space, after
                    smaller fonts, editing, and layout had been tried, then another sheet would have
                    to be used. This recourse was only open to papers that could afford it; the
                    titles in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> mainly worked to a pre-determined length,
                    and held back copy that could not be accommodated for the following issue. As
                    paper was a major expense in any publishing enterprise, attracting tax until
                    1861, it was in the interests of publishers to keep waste to a minimum. In the
                        <title>Monthly Repository</title> we have supplements from volume three
                    onwards, with none appearing between volume six and volume thirteen. However, we
                    know from other runs than the British Library’s that there were supplements for
                    these volumes. The most complete run of the <title>Monthly Repository
                    </title>that we found during our research was the one held at the Bodleian, but
                    even this had ‘To be preserved’ written in pencil above most of supplements,
                    suggesting that some content may have been excised from it. </p>
                <p>The <title>Monthly Repository’s</title> supplements were increasingly used to
                    contain reports of the Unitarian Association. In February 1832 the main sections
                    of the journal dealing directly with Unitarian affairs were published separately
                    as the <title>Unitarian Chronicle</title>. In the very first article within the
                        <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1832%2F02%2F01&amp;page=2&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity">
                        <title>Unitarian Chronicle</title>
                    </xref>, the links between the two titles were stressed: ‘The Editor has
                    endeavoured to provide for preserving the continuity of this holy chain
                    unbroken’, the editor writes, ‘The “Unitarian Chronicle” will also be the
                    “Companion to the Monthly Repository”, uniform in its size, form, type, and
                    paper, so as to preserve uniformity of general appearance.’ This would permit
                    readers to ‘bind them up together’ if they so desired but, ‘Others will prefer
                    collecting the intelligence by itself into volumes.’ There were benefits,
                    therefore, in supplementarity: some readers might choose to consider the
                        <title>Unitarian Chronicle </title>an extension of the <title>Monthly
                        Repository</title>, others to treat them as distinct titles.</p>
                <p>The <title>Unitarian Chronicle </title>also published supplements. In June 1832
                    they published a 16pp supplement for 3d, i.e. the same size and price of the
                    regular issues. In July the cover price of the regular issue was doubled, and a
                    16pp supplement provided for ‘free’. These supplements were treated by the
                    editor as extensions of the main issues, as you can see <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=SMRP%2F1832%2F06%2F01&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >here</xref>, the first article in both begins mid sentence! The issue for July
                    1832 attempts to regularize the situation, calling itself a ‘double number’ and
                    begging the readers for forgiveness. However, the <title>Unitarian Chronicle
                    </title>continues as a 32pp, 6d monthly from that issue onwards.</p>
                <p>The <title>Northern Star</title>, as a weekly newspaper, did not publish many
                    supplements. However, we do have an ‘Extraordinary’ number of the
                        <title>Northern Star </title>published immediately after the West Riding
                    Meeting on Hartshead Moor on <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=SNSS%2F1838%2F10%2F16&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >Monday 15 October 1838</xref>. As the <title>Star </title>published its
                    <xref type="internal" from="p5_6">multiple editions</xref> over a couple of days, it could
                    respond in a fairly timely fashion to passing events, and incorporate any new
                    material that it received. Issues of the <title>Northern Star </title>were dated
                    on a Saturday, but (at least in 1840) publishing began on Wednesday and ended on
                    Friday. Rather than wait until the next issue, which – if their publishing
                    routine was the same in 1838 – would go to press only two days after the
                    meeting, they instead rushed out a 2pp extra number in the afternoon of the
                    meeting in order to make Monday night’s mail.</p>
                <p>This is the only example of this we have in <title>Northern Star</title>,
                    suggesting that the publication opted to use its editions to keep abreast of
                    developments rather than rush out supplementary numbers that might not reach all
                    its readers. However, the <title>Northern Star</title> did adopt a policy of
                    issuing supplement portraits to entice readers to subscribe. These portraits
                    were the subject of an exhibition at the National Portrait Gallery from August
                    2006 to January 2007. We were aware of these portraits from our reading of the
                        <title>Northern Star</title> but, as they were issued separately, they had
                    not been preserved along with the run at the British Library. We took advantage
                    of the exhibition to attempt to find as many of the portraits as possible and,
                    with the co-operation of Rab MacGibbon, Malcolm Chase and Dorothy Thompson,
                    succeeded in including fifteen portraits in our edition. However, before we
                    could do this, we had to work out how to incorporate them. As they were not
                    printed as part of the <title>Northern Star</title> and were not intended to be
                    bound within volumes of the newspaper, we did not think we could treat them like
                    the other supplements in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>. Although the portraits were
                    announced with considerable fanfare in the paper, as they were steel engravings
                    they were produced at a much slower rate than the paper itself. This meant that
                    distribution of a particular portrait actually spanned several issues as it was
                    distributed to different regions of the title’s readership. We could have
                    included them in a ‘supplements’ folder, associating them with a volume rather
                    than a particular issue, but we decided in the end to keep them separate from
                    the Olive components of the resource. This allowed us to use <xref type="external" url="http://www.zoomify.com/">zoomify</xref>, permitting users to better
                    appreciate their detail. For more about the portraits, and to view them, click
                    <xref type="internal" from="p2_2">here</xref>.</p>
                <p>The <title>Leader </title>published at least two supplements over its run. The
                    first, a single, 12 page, gratis supplement dated 16 June 1855, was to accommodate
                    book and theatre reviews. The reasons that prompted it are unstated, although it
                    might have been one or some combination of the following: a response to the
                    repeal of the Stamp Duty in May; and / or an attempt to foreground its claim to
                    Literature on the occasion of its addition of a sub-title the following week, ‘A
                    Political and Literary Review’. This acknowledgement of the increasing
                    attractions of the <title>literary</title> market for serial publishers is
                    similarly marked by <title>Chambers’s Journal</title>, another weekly, which
                    changed its title in 1854 to signal its allocation of more space for serialised
                    fiction, embraced in its subtitle’s reference to ‘Popular Literature’. The
                    second, dated 14 April 1860, has a more explicit purpose. It was written in
                    response to the controversy prompted by a pamphlet accusing life assurance
                    companies of shady practices. What is notable about both of these supplements is
                    the lack of textual evidence for them within the regular issue that they
                    supposedly supplement. Without such evidence, it is difficult to state whether
                    these two supplements are the only ones published in the <title>Leader</title>,
                    or whether others were issued that we do not have.</p>
                <p> Although the supplements discussed so far were issued on an occasional basis
                    with regular issues, two of our supplements were published annually. The
                        <title>English Catalogue of Books </title>is a list of all books published
                    for the previous year, giving details of author, title, price, size and
                    publisher. It also gives the month in which the book was published, allowing
                    readers to cross reference the <title>English Catalogue </title>with the
                        <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>to find out more information about its
                    publication. The <title>English Catalogue</title>, then, functions as an index
                    to the <title>Publishers’ Circular</title>. At 5s, it was only a shilling less
                    than a year’s subscription to the <title>Publishers’ Circular</title> but, as
                    the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>did not publish an index, it was an
                    invaluable resource for navigating its often bulky volumes. This supplement
                    reflects the trade paper genre of the <title>Publishers’ Circular</title>, as
                    the <title>Catalogue</title> functioned practically within the book trade, as
                    well as an Index to its parent publication. </p>
                <p>The other annual supplements that appear within <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> are the
                        <title>Tomahawk</title> almanacks. These were based upon
                    <title>Punch</title>’s almanacks, published in the December of each year since
                    1846. Like <title>Punch’s </title>almanacks, <title>Tomahawk’s</title> were a
                    separate publication published in December. They cost 3d – a penny more than
                    regular issues of the title – but contained five colour cartoons and many other
                    engravings. It seems that the first almanack was more difficult to produce than
                    Á Beckett realized: advertisements for the almanack began to appear from the
                    beginning of November onwards; in issue number 30 (30 November 1867) they give 5
                    December as a publication date; but the almanack itself did not appear until the
                    12 December.</p>
                <p>Although some supplements were linked to the appearance of regular issues, the
                    extraordinary issue of the <title>Northern Star</title> and the annual
                    supplements of <title>Tomahawk </title>and <title>Publishers’ Circular
                    </title>complicate the publishing rhythms of their respective titles.
                    Publications like the almanacks and the <title>English Catalogue </title>are
                    like front and end matter, components that appear annually, punctuating the
                    weekly series of regular issues. Such supplements demand that we reconsider what
                    actually constitutes the titles. Supplements such as those to the June and July
                    1832 issues of the <title>Unitarian Chronicle </title>seem to suggest that it is
                    the regular dated and numbered issues that are the actual contents of the
                    journal. However, the <title>Unitarian Chronicle </title>itself is a supplement
                    to the <title>Monthly Repository</title>, positing an identity with it even
                    while being issued separately from it. Finally, of course, there are the annual
                    supplements whose appearance marks another manifestation of the serial: the
                    volume. For further comments on how the different forms of serial texts guided
                    our editorial strategy, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_2">here</xref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Wrappers </head>
                <p>Most publications in the nineteenth century carried advertisements. However,
                    advertisements were pejoratively connected with the material world of
                    trade and commerce, and editors frequently grouped them together in order to
                    separate them from other types of implicitly more elevated content. The most
                    effective way of doing this was to print advertisements on an advertising
                    wrapper that, because it consisted of pages outside the paginated letterpress
                    that contained the content, was easily identifiable as separate from the ‘real’
                    issue itself. Moreover, wrappers physically protected the content inside them
                    from damage during distribution. Such publishing strategies legitimated the
                    practice of those archivists who habitually stripped publications of advertising
                    material prior to binding them for preservation in libraries and archives.
                    Publishers themselves stripped them out for their annual or bi-annual
                    publication of periodicals in volume form. Thinner copy reduced binding expenses
                    and cover price. Yet wrappers, carrying the bulk of the advertising material so
                    important for financing a publication, are crucial parts of the economy of
                    serial publication. Arguably, for the original readers, information in
                    advertising wrappers made up part of the news and interest of issues. Moreover,
                    publishers and editors themselves often used wrappers to publish Addresses or
                    Notes to their readers. The wrappers, therefore, contain vital historical
                    information about the role of the serials in nineteenth-century commodity
                    culture.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> we are lucky in that we have some of the wrappers for two of our
                    weeklies, <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>and <title>Tomahawk</title>. The
                        <title>Leader </title>also chooses to rearrange its advertising department
                    into a wrapper in July 1858. In the issue for <xref type="external" url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1858%2F07%2F17&amp;page=12&amp;entityid=Ar01204&amp;view=entity">17 July 1858</xref> the editors insist
                    that this move has been at the request of readers but note that such a move will
                    make ‘the volume more convenient for binding’ while also ‘offering additional
                    advantages to advertisers.’ Yet the layout of the wrapper in the <title>Leader
                    </title>is different than the wrappers in <title>Tomahawk </title>or
                        <title>Publishers’ Circular</title>. In both of those titles the wrapper has
                    its own pagination and so doesn’t interfere with the page sequence that runs
                    through all the regular issues in a volume. Equally, both titles make clear with
                    a prominent masthead where the issue ‘proper’ begins. As you can see by clicking
                    <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint-stg.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=LDR%2F1858%2F07%2F24&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >here</xref> neither of these features are taken up in the <title>Leader</title> and, to
                    make matters more complicated, its closing wrapper covers three pages while the
                    opening – as one would expect – only covers two. This makes the
                    <title>Leader</title> wrapper more like two sections of advertisements that open
                    and close the issue, rather than a form of content that represents itself as
                    being supplementary to it. To read more about how we incorporated wrappers
                    within the edition click <xref type="internal" from="p5_2">here</xref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
