<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_8">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Runs</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
           
            <p>‘Runs’ refer to the successive numbers of a title which appear regularly, and have
                usually survived in bound volumes in library collections. However, it is common that
                the span of a serial’s life has a variety of markers which punctuate it, and
                characterise it formally at particular tranches of its duration. For example, titles
                are often divided into Series, described either by numbers (eg 1<hi
                    rend="superscript">st</hi> Series, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Series, 3<hi
                    rend="superscript">rd</hi> Series) or by the term New Series (often abbreviated
                ns). Runs sometimes have vertical additions to the succession of regular numbers;
                these include supplements and/or multiple editions as are seen in this edition in
                the <title>Northern Star</title> and the <title>Leader </title>(which have both), or in
                the <title>Monthly Repository, </title>which allows a new title (the <title>Unitarian
                    Chronicle</title>) to piggy-back on its monthly issues.</p>
            <p>Readers of serials that have survived in volume form should be aware that volumes do
                not necessarily reflect the run as it was initially published. If serial volumes are
                compiled and bound by their original publishers, it is likely that covers,
                advertising supplements or wrappers, and some other paratextual materials are
                removed and/or excluded. Multiple editions of single issues do not normally appear
                in such bound volumes. Other materials found in Volumes, such as Volume title pages,
                Volume Tables of Content and/or Indexes are often additional or optional to
                periodical issued over the year. </p>
            <p>If runs are bound by libraries or individuals from single issues collected over the
                run, then the contents of volumes may be more inclusive and variable. For example,
                the British Library volumes of the <title>Northern Star </title>include multiple
                editions, but in no clear or designated order; this is also the case with the
                multiple editions of the <title>Leader</title> we include in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>, in which case it
                can be seen how unsystematic the inclusion of two editions is. Apart from a short
                period of just over two years, when the <title>Leader </title>had clearly designated
                Town and Country editions, it is often difficult to know which edition is bound
                first. With respect to the <title>Monthly Repository </title>its Supplement, the
                    <title>Unitarian Chronicle, </title>was bound separately, and appears in the
                British Library catalogue and on the shelves as an independent title, perhaps
                because it did eventually break free of its host publication into independent
                status. As it is, we are unclear whether the Unitarian Chronicle was ever sewn into
                its host when they were originally circulated, or whether it was simply slipped in.
                Moreover, binders in libraries or private persons sometimes place Tables of
                Contents, illustrations and Indices in the wrong order in volumes, or attach them to
                the wrong issues. We need to be aware that the representation of runs in bound
                volumes represents convention, in the case of the publishers’ volumes, and to a
                certain extent haphazard selection and order in the case of volumes bound
                individually by libraries or readers.</p>
            <p>Some specific positions in runs tend to be most informative about the nature of
                titles and changes within them; these include the beginning of runs, when manifestos
                are often reprinted (having appeared before launches as separate publications or as
                announcements in other serials), and self-assessments are in evidence; often new
                journals publish feedback in the form of snippets from reviews, attached to adverts
                for the new title as quotations, or correspondence about the new publication. Such
                reflexive material may also appear at the ends of runs, at anniversaries of the
                launch, at the start of volumes or years, at the commencement of new series or on
                the occasion of a change of title, both of which may themselves signal a change of
                proprietor, editor and/or publisher.</p>
            <p>Changes of title in runs of serials are commonplace, and often represent changes of
                editorial policy and/or attempts to attract a different or broader readership. In
                    <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> in order to represent this dual state of change within continuity,
                we have opted for a generic title (eg, the <title>Leader</title> or the <title>Northern
                    Star)</title> to designate the complete run of each serial, and the specific,
                historical titles that attach to individual issues, which record accurately as they
                occur any changes in title. These are also signalled and discussed in head
            notes.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
