<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p5_4">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Visual Material</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <p>In a speech in January 2006 to the Oxford Media Convention, the then Secretrary of
                State for Culture, Media and Sport, Tessa Jowell, making the case for media literacy
                in an age of media convergence, argued:</p>
            <p>I do not exaggerate when I say that media literacy in its widest sense is as
                important to our development as was universal literacy in the 19th century. Then,
                the written word was the only passport to knowledge. Now, there are many more.  And
                the most insidious digital divide is between those equipped to understand that and
                those who aren't.</p>
            <p>Even accounting for political rhetoric, Jowell’s remarks reveal a common assumption:
                that the nineteenth century was dominated by the word. However, a glance at the
                front pages (not to mention the wrappers) of any of the titles in <hi rend="bold"
                    >ncse</hi> reveals this assumption to be largely false. This page provides some
                brief accounts of both the importance of visual material in nineteenth-century print
                culture, and our treatment of it in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>.</p>

            <div>
                <head>Importance of the visual</head>
                <p>Although Jowell is trying to claim that there is something distinctly
                    twenty-first century about media literacy, this is clearly untrue.
                    Nineteenth-century proprietors and editors were adept at using combinations of
                    words, blank space and images to create distinct identities for their
                    publications that engaged with social codes and attempted to interpellate groups
                    of readers. Even an early, relatively austere unillustrated periodical such as
                    the <title>Monthly Repository</title> employed a visual repertoire through its
                    typography, graphic devices to separate departments and items, icons to indicate
                    notes, and the way words were displayed on the page. For instance, issue no. 1
                    of the <title>Monthly Repository</title>, from January 1806, has a variety of
                    different sizes and formats of type; uses a range of icons to indicate
                    footnotes, and breaks up its single block of text on page 49 into two columns.
                    Although it never brought illustrations as such into its letterpress over its 32
                    year run, the <title>Monthly Repository</title> did issue high quality portraits
                    and other illustrations as annual supplements, often with instructions that they
                    be bound in at the front of the volume (for instance see the ‘Memoir of the late
                    Dr Cogan’ in vol. 14 (1819) <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=MRP%2F1819%2F01%2F02&amp;page=5&amp;entityid=Ar00100&amp;view=entity"
                        >here</xref>). Although the
                        <title>Monthly Repository</title>, which began publication in 1806, predates
                    the expansion of the illustrated press in the 1830s, its use of visual material
                    demonstrates the popularity of prints for its readers. The high quality
                    illustrations celebrate notable people and buildings within the periodical’s
                    culture, while the way they were issued links them to its serial production.</p>
                <p>The other five periodicals in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> all employ visual
                    material in different ways. This is partly related to the changing economics of
                    print production, which reconfigured the practical demands of getting images
                    into letterpress. The economics of different modes of reproducing images are
                    demonstrated in the <title>Northern Star</title>. Although not cheap because it
                    paid the newspaper stamp tax, the <title>Northern Star</title> was aimed at a
                    working class readership and produced as cheaply as possible. The most visually
                    striking pages in its letterpress are those containing advertisements. For
                    instance, the front pages of the first 60 issues of the <title>Northern
                    Star</title> (roughly up until March 1839 with the preparation of the first
                    Chartist petition) are devoted to six columns of advertisements. Each
                    advertisement uses a different combination of type and space in order to
                    distinguish itself visually from the others that surround it. Many, such as
                    those for <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1838%2F04%2F07&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >Whitehead’s</xref> Tea and Coffee shop on Briggate in Leeds (just down the
                    road from the <title>Northern Star’s</title> offices) are high quality and used
                    for a number of issues. Others, such as the small woodcut for Batty’s <xref
                        type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1838%2F06%2F09&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >Circus Royal</xref> appeared for only a handful of issues, before the
                    circus moved on. </p>
                <p>Although the <title>Northern Star </title>did include some images to accompany
                    its articles, these tended to be quite crude woodcuts. In the early
                    nineteenthcentury it was difficult to commission, design and execute a woodcut
                    within weekly publishing rhythms. A good example of this is on the front page of
                    the <title>Northern Star </title> vol. 5, <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=NSS%2F1842%2F08%2F20&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >issue no. 249 (18??)</xref>. The first two editions of this issue feature a
                    blank space where a woodcut was supposed to appear. The subsequent three
                    editions all have the woodcut. In the white space there is an explanation as to
                    why the woodcut does not appear. The editors had been promised it would arrive
                    from London that morning, but it was not on the expected 6 am train. The editors
                    claimed that readers of their first edition would be ‘naturally anxious to hear
                    the news’ so would prefer an incomplete paper than a delayed but
                    fully-illustrated one. Of course there may be other reasons to do with
                    distribution and printing schedules that would make such a delay unaffordable,
                    but that the space was set, and then kept available until the last moment, gives
                    the front page a timeliness that emphasizes its news value. The space itself is
                    particularly suggestive of the absent image: the retention of the title and the
                    caption allows readers to appreciate what should have been there, and the space
                    itself indicates its size. By signalling the absent image, the editors of the
                        <title>Northern Star </title>demonstrate the expense they have gone to in
                    order to produce the engraving (even thought it isn’t there), while sacrificing
                    the space by not filling it with letterpress or advertisements. The space
                    invites readers to imagine the absent image, especially as the other relevant
                    components on the page – the tribute to Henry Hunt printed in the space usually
                    reserved for the proprietor Fergus O’Connor in the first column, and the other
                    cut showing Hunt in full flow with the Peterloo Massacre raging around him at
                    the bottom – are present. Yet the white space reminds readers that this is an
                    incomplete version of the Northern Star and that a different, more up-to-date
                    version exists elsewhere. This white space, therefore, does not just represent
                    an absent image, but also reminds us of the presence of its other editions.</p>
                <p>Where the <title>Northern Star </title>was more successful was in issuing one-off
                    engravings as supplements. Almost from the outset it issued fine steel
                    engravings of notable figures to encourage a particular form of accessing the
                    paper, subscriptions, and to create a sense of unity amongst the developing
                    Chartist movement. For more on the portraits, and to see them, click <xref type="internal" from="p2_2">here</xref>. As steel engravings the portraits were difficult to produce in the
                    necessary numbers. Although the <title>Northern Star</title> aggressively
                    promoted the portraits, it was often forced to issue them on a regional basis
                    over a period of weeks in order to meet demand. As the steel plates
                    deteriorated, so did the quality of the portraits.</p>
                <p>By the 1860s illustrated weekly journalism was well-established. The
                        <title>Illustrated London News</title> and <title>Punch </title>appeared in
                    1841 and 1842 respectively, demonstrating the possibility of high-quality,
                    timely illustrated journalism. These respectable titles were joined, in 1845, by
                    the <title>London Journal</title>, a more down-market illustrated weekly that
                    obtained large sales combining illustration with serial fiction. Twenty years
                    later <xref type="internal" from="p2_5">
                        <title>Tomahawk</title>
                    </xref> was set up as a direct rival to <title>Punch</title> and featured a
                    large cut (either one or two pages) in every issue. These were engraved onto
                    separate sheets and then bound into the issue. As the reverse side of the image
                    was left blank, they could take up to four pages of a ten to twelve page issue.
                    The images themselves were engraved by Matt Morgan to produce combinations of
                    black and white line against a coloured ink wash. Each cut had a caption and was
                    also often accompanied by a satirical article in the letterpress, creating a
                    complex dialogue between the text and image across its pages.</p>
                <p>Aside from the tomahawks that graced its masthead and leader, the large cuts were
                    the only illustrative material to appear within <title>Tomahawk</title>.
                    However, the journal was issued in an advertising wrapper that was marked by a
                    striking title page. As you can see <xref type="external"
                        url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Default.htm?href=TTW%2F1869%2F01%2F16&amp;page=1&amp;view=document"
                        >here</xref> both the wrapper and the advertisements it
                    contains are packed with images, creating a visually dense page in stark
                    contrast to the sparse paginated letterpres. As a trade journal, the
                        <title>Publishers’ Circular’s </title>entire complement of images is located
                    in its advertisements. At the end of the century a mature market for the
                    production, distribution, and preserving of images coupled with new technologies
                    such as photo-mechanical reproduction made it much easier to print visual
                    material. However, as the Christmas numbers of the <title>Publishers’s
                    Circular</title> demonstrate, there was still a substantial demand for
                    illustration. The Christmas number was published in the first week of December
                    in addition to the two usual fortnightly issues that month. It was intended to
                    showcase the illustrations that were to be printed in the Christmas numbers of
                    the illustrated press, and the abundance of visual material that this brought
                    into the issue also made it more attractive to advertisers. These issues were
                    usually four or five times the length of a regular issue, and included
                    separately paginated inserts of illustrations from the periodical press that was
                    interleaved with the regular advertisement section.</p>
                <p>As reading necessarily entails looking, the visual is a key component of any
                    text. As the periodical and newspapers in <hi rend="bold">ncse </hi>demonstrate,
                    visual material is not restricted to pictures. Although they did play a part in
                    serials throughout the nineteenth century, other aspects such as mastheads,
                    icons, typography and layout constitute the bulk of visual material in the
                    press. The visual is not only a decorative addition to the textual content, but
                    is the way in which that content is presented. As such, visual material is part
                    of the content, structuring the ways in which it is encountered. It is through
                    the combination of visual features, as well as what verbal text says, that
                    individual issues posit an identity that can transcend their specific, dated
                    material, linking them to the title as a whole.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Images in ncse</head>
                <p>The predominant model for digitizing printed texts is to combine facsimile page
                    images with a textual transcript, usually generated from optical character
                    recognition (OCR). It is the OCR transcript that provides the searchable index
                    to a digital resource, although this is usually complemented by other searches
                    of the metadata. As search is essentially a textual procedure – searches work by
                    looking for text strings that are similar to that proposed by a user – it is
                    notoriously hard to include visual material within search engines. The most
                    straightforward way of doing this is to include some sort of textual information
                    along with the image that can be interrogated by a search engine. As this
                    information is interpretive – it attempts to render the picture into words – it
                    has to be entered by a human. Not only is this time-consuming but, as most
                    digital resources tend to be top-down models, the process has to be carefully
                    managed in order to standardize the judgements and control the vocabulary.</p>
                <p>As mentioned above, there are lots of different types of visual material in <hi
                        rend="bold">ncse</hi>. Although we recognized the importance of marking-up
                    pictures, we also wanted to signal the other types of visual material and how
                    they interact with each other. In the early stages of the project we attempted
                    to delineate all the possible data structures in the edition, before analyzing
                    them to work out which could be achieved with the resources available. Olive
                    Software’s segmentation allowed us to decide what constituted an item, and our
                    editorial policy, which recognized that issues are more than a series of
                    articles, prompted us to identify any textual component on a page as a single
                    item (for more on our editorial policy click <xref type="internal" from="p5_2"
                        >here</xref>). This means that items could be mastheads, datelines or
                    running heads as well as whole articles. Olive Software permits items to be one
                    of three types: articles, advertisements or pictures. Where an item is a
                    picture, we have marked it as such; where an item contains a picture (for
                    instance a picture within an article), we have marked the picture as a picture
                    and then embedded it within the item. This allows users to open the item as a
                    whole in the component viewer or, if they only want to see the image, open the
                    image without the accompanying text. The one place where this causes
                    difficulties is in advertisements. As noted above, advertisements are often the
                    most visually diverse portions of an issue. However, Olive’s software does not
                    permit pictures to be embedded within advertisements. As we did not want to
                    exclude this important source of visual material, we ensured that images within
                    advertisements were marked up with image metadata. Although a search made from
                    within the edition that is delimited to images will therefore exclude any images
                    that appear in advertisements, browsing the image metadata will produce results
                    from all the images in the edition, whether included in advertisements or
                    articles. You can read more about our image metadata below.</p>
                <p>Although our segmentation policy allowed us to recognize a more diverse
                    repertoire of content than articles and images, we were restricted in the extent
                    to which we marked them up. <hi rend="bold">ncse </hi>contains things like
                    handwritten notes, newspaper stamps, library accession numbers, rules,
                    ornaments, fingerposts, mastheads – all of which constitute visual material of
                    one kind or another. These are segmented within the edition as items, formally
                    recognizing that they are as much part of the issue as verbal contents and
                    conventional images. We could have also chosen to label them with metadata,
                    distinguishing them from each other and allowing them to be included within
                    searches. However, because of the size of the edition we were restricted in the
                    extent to which we could add metadata at item level and, after carefully
                    considering the benefits to users, decided to treat these types of content in
                    the same way as other items: i.e., with metadata that is inherited from higher
                    levels in the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> structural hierarchy. For more about our
                    metadata, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_11">here</xref>.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Image metadata in ncse</head>
                <p>All of our images, whether part of articles, inserts into front matter, or
                    appearing in advertisements, are labelled with image metadata and so can be
                    searched and browsed. It is notoriously difficult to come up with a
                    classificatory scheme for images. We considered adapting well-known schema such
                    as <xref type="external" url="http://www.iconclass.nl/">Iconclass</xref> as a
                    way of labelling images in a way that would be compatible with other projects.
                    However, because Iconclass is designed to label works of art (predominantly from
                    a Western tradition), there are large domains that it does not cover that are
                    crucial for labelling the types of images in <hi>ncse</hi>. For instance, a
                    large number of our images are within advertisements and are therefore usually
                    representations of the goods that are advertised. As Iconclass tends towards the
                    thematic (it is, after all intended to be an iconographic schema) it cannot
                    provide terms to label, for instance, types of bookcase.</p>
                <p>Many projects that work with images evaluate Iconclass as a possible schema. The
                        <xref type="external" url="http://www.dmvi.cardiff.ac.uk/">Database of
                        Mid-Victorian Woodcut Illustration</xref> (DMVI) considered a range of
                    possible iconographic schema, before opting to design their own. As their
                    resultant iconographic schema was a bespoke system designed to label
                    illustrations in nineteenth-century periodicals, it was very close to our needs.
                    The Project Director of DMVI, Julia Thomas, kindly allowed us to use their
                    schema for ncse.. We adapted it by selecting its more descriptive categories ,
                    and then tested them on different types of content in order to find any areas in
                    which we needed to supplement them. It is a testament to their schema that even
                    when a group of editorial assistants all worked on the same content, they came
                    up with largely the same terms. You can read more about the DMVI schema <xref
                        type="external" url="http://www.dmvi.cardiff.ac.uk/guide/iconography.html"
                        >here</xref>.</p>
                <p>As any markup of images is necessarily interpretive, it is a process that
                    involves a great deal of human input. There are over 5000 individual images
                    scattered throughout <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>: although we knew where most were
                    concentrated (for instance <title>Tomahawk’s</title> central cut; advertisements
                    etc.) and could use Olive’s image search to find many of them, we still needed
                    to scan every page and mark up each as it was found. As images do not produce
                    legible OCR transcripts, it was possible to speed up this process by scanning
                    the lists of item titles that populated the tables of components in the Olive
                    Administrator Tool. As this was the tool though which we added most of the <xref
                        type="internal" from="p5_11">metadata</xref>, it was a particularly
                    convenient method for finding images. In order to ensure as much consistency as
                    possible through the edition, we carried out extensive checking of image
                    metadata, comparing different editorial assistants’ work and keeping a log of
                    any decisions that were made. </p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
