<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p1_2">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Technical Introduction</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <head>Technical Introduction</head>

            <p>As can be seen in the accompanying <xref type="internal" from="p5">editorial
                    commentary</xref> for this edition, <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> is large and
                varied, containing well over 400,000 articles that originally appeared in roughly
                3500 issues of six nineteenth-century periodicals. Published during a span of 84 years,
                materials within the corpus exist in numbered editions, and include supplements,
                wrapper materials and visual elements. A key challenge in creating a digital system
                for the management of such a body of material is to design and build appropriate and
                innovative tools to assist scholars in <hi rend="italic">finding</hi> materials that
                support their research while challenging and enabling new and innovative approaches
                to it.</p>
            <p>In the past, notably on the <xref type="external"
                    url="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/research/projects/proj-keyword.html">Keyword
                    project</xref>, the Centre for Computing in the Humanities (CCH) has
                investigated the use of computational linguistics techniques for the extraction of
                keywords from full-text content. The genesis of this work was the realization that a
                great deal of human effort and skill are required to add intellectual data such as
                keywords and abstracts to materials included in digital archives. <note> Marilyn
                    Deegan, Harold Short, Dawn Archer, Paul Baker, Tony McEnery, Paul Rayson (2004)
                    Computational Linguistics Meets Metadata, or the Automatic Extraction of Key
                    Words from Full Text Content. RLG Diginews, Vol. 8, No. 2. ISSN
                1093-5371.</note> The benefits of doing so, however are clear; though full-text
                searching is useful in conducting 'known-item' searches, other kinds of metadata,
                including bibliographic description, keyword assignment, and the application of
                taxonomic structures to materials improve the precision of items returned (that is,
                their relevance to the research question at hand) and their recall, or the degree to
                which a search returns <hi rend="italic">all</hi> relevant documents.</p>
            <p>In a series of trials with collaborating institutions, the project used material in
                the corpus of the Forced Migration Online project, a digital library with a variety
                of on-line contemporary materials to demonstrate that the techniques of
                computational linguistics could be applied to full text content from digital
                libraries in order to extract 'meaningful keywords for a variety of purposes:
                browsing content, improving thesauri and metadata' <note>For the full report of the
                    outcomes of this work, read: <xref type="external "
                        url="http://www.keyword.kcl.ac.uk/redist/pdf/mellon.pdf"
                        >http://www.keyword.kcl.ac.uk/redist/pdf/mellon.pdf</xref></note>
            </p>

            <p>The technical components of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> thus build on this earlier research to
                explore how the use of similar natural language processing techniques can be adapted
                and applied to enhance a scholarly edition, with the aim of addressing
                three primary research questions: <list type="ordered">
                    <item>How might a semantic 'view' be generated of items within the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> corpus
                        through a hybrid approach of manually and algorithmically assigned keywords?</item>
                    <item>What kinds of end-user facilities could be produced using this data to aid
                        the user in locating and selecting articles relevant to their research?</item>
                    <item>How can this semantic environment best be integrated with end-user
                        browsing and searching services provided within the Olive software?</item>
                </list>
            </p>

            <p>Following is a brief overview of the technologies and processes used to create
                    <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>. Interested readers may also wish to consult our list
                of <xref type="internal" from="p1_7">Technical Acknowledgements.</xref></p>

            <div>
                <head>ncse Facsimiles</head>
                <p>The texts in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> were scanned from microfilm by <xref type= "external" url="http://www.olivesoftware.com/">Olive
                    Software</xref> and processed using their Viewpoint software. </p>
                <p> ViewPoint comprises three main modules – XML Distiller, Olive XML
                    Warehouse and the Olive ViewPoint Server <note>To learn more about Olive Software, read: <xref type="external" url="http://www.olivesoftware.com">http://www.olivesoftware.com</xref></note>. The XML Distiller captures
                    unstructured, multiple format document resources and transforms them into a
                    unified, structured XML schema (PrXML). Content is fully indexed for searching
                    and stored in the Olive XML warehouse file system. The ViewPoint Server provides
                    dynamic access, viewing and search services. ViewPoint's XML-based
                    search engine can search through the text of an entire document warehouse,
                    including metadata, to retrieve components from multiple documents. The search
                    engine displays search results based on the proprietary 'Relational Relevance
                    Ranking' algorithm, allowing for retrieval of the relevant components from the
                    specific documents that contain the search term, relative to neighboring
                    components. Results are highlighted directly on the 'image'. A full catalogue
                    record, produced by the research team, was also produced for each document using
                    Olive software tools that included bibliographic and structural metadata.
                        <note>To learn more about the processes used in identifying and applying
                        metadata to items, read <xref type="internal" from="p5_11">Metadata</xref>
                        in the editorial commentary.</note>
                </p>

                <p>
                    <figure url="olive-viewpoint"/>
                </p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Keyword Assignment</head>
                <p>Keywords were assigned to materials by extracting the uncorrected OCR text of
                    each article in the corpus from the Olive Viewpoint server, for storage within a
                    MySQL token database.</p>

                <div>
                    <head> Entities: Persons, Places and Institutions </head>
                    <p>Persons, places and institution entities were extracted from
                        the texts in the corpus using Gate, the General Architecture for Text
                        Engineering.<note>To learn more about Gate, see <xref type="external" url="http://www.gate.ac.uk/">http://www.gate.ac.uk/</xref></note></p>

                    <p>
                        <figure url="gate"/>
                    </p>

                    <p>Within <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>, the GATE subcomponents ANNIE and JAPE were
                        used to extract information about pre-specified entities according to a set
                        of pre-determined rules, and in comparison with gazetteers, plain text files
                        that contain lists of names for each entity type. </p>


                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Subject Descriptors</head>
                    <p>With the assistance of Paul Rayson of UCREL, a cross-departmental research
                        centre at Lancaster University that specializes in computer-aided analysis
                        of naturally occurring language, subject descriptors were automatically
                        applied to the corpus. This work was performed using the UCREL Semantic
                        Analysis System or USAS. USAS is a dictionary-based content analysis tool
                        that automatically links words in running text to one or more semantic
                        categories. <note>For an introduction to USAS, see: <xref type="external"
                                url="http://www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/computing/users/paul/publications/tokyo2002/"
                                >http://www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/computing/users/paul/publications/tokyo2002/</xref>
                        </note></p>

                    <p> The USAS system is designed to undertake the automatic semantic analysis of
                        present-day English texts (spoken and written), in a two-stage process:
                            <list type="ordered">
                            <item>A part-of-speech tag is assigned to every lexical item or
                                multi-word expression (MWE), using probabilistic Markov models of
                                likely part-of-speech sequences (- 97% accuracy) </item>
                            <item>Output is fed into SEMTAG, which assigns semantic field tags on
                                the basis of pattern matching between the text and two computer
                                dictionaries developed for use with the program, and then applies a
                                set of disambiguation techniques intended to select the correct
                                semantic tag on each item given its context (- 92% accuracy) </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Within <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>, Dr. Rayson tailored USAS to process the
                        entire the entire text of the corpus<note>The text used for this work was
                            taken from a 17 January 2008 "snapshot" of the corpus.</note>. Reports
                        were created for each article in the corpus over 300 characters <note>This word
                            threshold was selected as in articles shorter than 300 characters there is not enough context to
  enable the semtag-process to extract meaningful data. </note> that included:
                            <list type="unordered">
                            <item> a copy of the original file</item>
                            <item>a semantic tag report with each lists of subject descriptors from
                                the semantic tagset sorted in order of relevance</item>
                            <item>a "names" report with lists of words of the semantic categories
                                "personal names", "geographical names", and "other proper names"
                                    <note>This separate names report was created to use in
                                    comparison with the GATE entity output.</note>
                            </item>

                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p><figure url="usas"/></p>

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Image Descriptors</head>
                    <p>Images appearing within the corpus were manually catalogued by the editorial
                        team within the Olive administrative interface using an adapted form of the
                        Database of Mid-Victorian Illustration taxonomy, an organised system of
                        iconographic terms tailor-made to describe Victorian visual art. To read
                        more about this process, see the essay on <xref type="internal" from="p5_4"
                            >Visual material</xref> within the editorial commentary.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Web Delivery Framework</head>
                <p>To create the web delivery framework, extracted entities, semantic tags and image
                    descriptors, along with the bibliographic metadata for each article, were
                    aggregated according to their Olive system identifier. For each keyword type, a
                    Python script was written to apply additional filters to the extracted data as a
                    part of the aggregation process: <list>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">Semantic Tags</hi>: Only those semantic tags assigned
                            to a document which are calculated to have a 95% percentile significance
                            level were included in the exported data. Any semantic tags belonging to
                            the Z class were also removed. </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="bold">Person, Place, Institution Entities</hi>: 
                              Entities consisting entirely of non-alphanumeric characters
                              as a result of incorrect OCR recognition 
                              were filtered out the of keyword framework, while such characters
                              appearing within words were replaced by the underscore character ( _ ). Any entity that is a
                            single character was also filtered. </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="bold">Image Keywords</hi>: All image keywords, having been
                            human-assigned, were included in the keyword framework. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p> After filtering was complete, the Python script included items output for the
                    web framework if: keywords exist in any form (semantic tags, persons, places,
                    institutions or images), and meaningful bibliographic metadata (in particular,
                    an item title) could be extracted from Olive repository. </p>

                <p>
                    <figure url="cch-ncseweb"/>
                </p>

                <p>Finally, the Python script created XML files for each file, optimised for use
                    with Ereuna, a search framework, based on Apache Lucene, built with the purpose
                    to speed the development of search facilities for web applications. This
                    language independent framework can be used with a wide range of source materials
                    (XML and non-XML bases), requiring little need for specific programming
                    knowledge of the underlying Lucene architecture. </p>
                <p> Within <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>, Ereuna works in the following way: <list>

                        <item>First , the XML documents created by the Python aggregator are
                            processed by Apache Lucene to create a searchable index;</item>
                        <item>An Apache Cocoon web framework uses the index to execute searches and
                            return search results (arrow 4 in the figure).</item>
                    </list>
                </p>

                <p>The web delivery framework thus comprises two interrelated components: the
                    Olive produced <hi rend="bold">facsimile</hi> repository which allows for full-text searching and
                    browsing, and a rich <hi rend="bold">keyword</hi> repository, in which users can browse for and
                    search articles according to the ways in which they have been
                    semantically identified.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions and Future Directions</head>
                <p>Within the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> project, the focus was on nineteenth-century language, an area for
                    which specialized USAS thesauri do not yet exist, and GATE gazetteers must be crafted. In addition, the source text
                    for the keyword generation work was uncorrected OCR. Therefore, while early
                    results of this work are quite promising, the keyword index cannot yet boast of
                    high precision or recall when compared to the full-text results generated in the
                    Olive facsimile repository. </p>

                <p>However, the work performed to-date for the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> has allowed the CCH to explore
                    the develoment of a full-featured bibliographic system developed using 
                    data mining techniques, and early anecdotal feedback suggests that the
                    semantic 'view' metaphor used in constructing the beta website helps the user to 
                    find relevant documents, particularly for searches that include subject descriptors. 
                    Furthermore, early feedback suggests that the system invites the scholar to engage with the material in new ways.</p>

                <p>In conclusion, the work of the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> is perhaps best termed "at the end of the
                    beginning". Planned enhancements include: <list type="ordered">
                        <item>Additional refinements to the facsimile repository user interface, </item>
                        <item>Refinements to the keyword extraction processes, to improve
                            reliability and relevance of terms returned,</item>
                        <item>Development of 'user tools' for text mining and network analysis,</item>
                        <item>Inclusion within the keyword repository of additional materials from
                            the corpus, and</item>
                        <item>Improved integration between the keyword and facsimile
                        repositories.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>


            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
