<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p1_1">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Welcome to ncse</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
      </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

           

            <p>Like all editions, ncse makes an argument about its contents. The project team saw
                the project as a chance to explore two research questions: how can you edit
                nineteenth-century serials in a scholarly edition; and how can digital resources be
                best used to model nineteenth-century serials in paper? ncse provides an answer to
                both of these questions. We approached the serials as objects to be edited in their
                own right, rejecting approaches that would privilege certain types of content,
                certain periods, or certain figures. We then explored how to represent these data
                structures in digital form, working with Olive Software to adapt their Viewpoint
                application and with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities to integrate it with
                our own bespoke site with its own metadata and search functions. For further
                information about our methdology, click <xref type="internal" from="p5">here</xref>
                for the editorial commentary and <xref type="internal" from="p6">here</xref> for the
                history of the project.</p>
            <p>The majority of our content was contributed by the British Library. However, this
                material was supplemented from a variety of institutions and individuals: the
                    <title>Northern Star</title> portraits came from the National Portrait Gallery
                and from the collection of Dorothy Thompson; the 1827 volume of the <title>Monthly
                    Repository</title> and issues 165-173 of <title>Tomahawk</title> came from the
                Bodleian; and the <title>English Woman’s Journal</title> is from the Women’s
                Library. John North generously helped us build our advanced metadata with his
                indices from the <title>
                    <xref type="external" url="http://www.victorianperiodicals.com">Waterloo
                        Directory of English Periodicals and Newspapers</xref>
                </title> and J. Thomas, P. T. Killick, A. A. Mandal, and D. J. Skilton generously
                let us adapt the iconographic schema from their <title>
                    <xref type="external" url="http://www.dmvi.cf.ac.uk">Database of Mid-Victorian
                        wood-engraved Illustration</xref>
                </title> for our image metadata.</p>
               <div><head>Project Partners:</head>
                   <p>[Logos of stakeholders: AHRC, BL, BBK, KCL, CCH, Olive]</p></div>
               <div><head>Contributors:</head>
                   <p>[Logos of contributors: University of Birmingham, Women’s Library, NPG, Waterloo Directory, Bodleian]</p></div>
           












        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
