<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p8">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head>Searching</head>
                <p> The keyword index allows users to search for keywords that have been
                    assigned to items within <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> using a combination of
                    controlled and free-text entry fields.  The index was compiled by first
                    algorithmically and manually applying keywords to articles in the <hi rend="italic">ncse</hi>
                    corpus.  The outputs of these processes were then aggregated, and indexed using the high-performance 
                    text search engine Lucene.  Persons, places, institutions, and subjects were generated by processing
                    the <hi rend="italic">uncorrected</hi> OCR output housed in the facsimile repository using a variety
                    of data mining and natural language processing techniques.  Image descriptors were manually applied to articles
                    within the corpus using a controlled vocabulary.   The index represents approximately 317,402 items within
                    the facsimile repository, including titles, articles, advertisements, front matter, and images.
                    To learn more about the processes undertaken in generating the keyword index, read the 
                    <xref type="internal" from="p1_2">Technical Introduction</xref>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    
                    
                    This section describes how to enter
                    search terms and refine search queries, and how to interpret and refine search
                    results. It <hi rend="bold">does not</hi> describe how to search the full-text
                    appearing within fascimiles. For this information, please read: <xref
                        type="external" url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Tips.htm">Advanced
                        Search Tips</xref> in the fascimile repository. </p>

                <div>
                    <head>Free-text Entry Search Fields</head>
                    <p>To search for Persons, Places or Institutions, select the keyword type
                        from the drop down menu of the corresponding field, and then key in text. Multi-word terms may be entered in full (e.g. John
                        Smith), or in a partial form (e.g. Smith). </p>
                 
                   <div>
                        <head>Multiple Terms in One Search Box</head>
                        <p>Multiple terms typed into one search box are automatically interpreted as
                            a Boolean AND, and are treated as separate queries. If conducting a Boolean search using different operators
                            (e.g. OR, NOT), enter terms into separate search boxes.  Boolean terms entered directly into the search fields will result in zero results being returned.</p>
                   </div>
                    <div><head>Case-Insensitive</head>
                        <p>
                    Search terms can be entered in upper or lower case.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Approximate Match Searching</head>
                        <p>By default, queries entered using the free-text fields are compared to the
                            keyword index based on an exact match  to the terms entered.  However, the
                            user can select a percentage to request that search terms be matched that are of higher
                            or lower degrees of similarity to the terms indexed in the database.  Entering a higher percentage (e.g. 90%) will return
                            matches that are very similar to the entered text, while entering a lower percentage (e.g. 50%) will return results that
                            are much less similar to the entered text.                         
                            
                        </p>
                        <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>Adjust this threshold to account for differences in the terms that result from the OCR extraction process on which this index is based.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Wildcard/Stemming</head>
                        <p>As an alternative to approximate matching, use an asterisk (*)  or question mark (?) to broaden search results. You can use wildcard searches in the middle of a term , however,
                        you cannot use a * or ? symbol as the first character of a search.</p>
                        
                        <p> Use an asterisk (*) to search for different words beginning with the same stem.  </p>
                        
                        <p>  
                            <list>
                                
                                <item>
                                    e.g. place: <hi rend="italic">waterl*</hi> will match waterloo and waterlow (a possible result based on OCR output). </item>
                                </list>
                        </p>
                        
                        <p>The question mark (?) performs a single character wildcard search, and will return variants of the
                            term entered with the single character replaced.  
                        </p>
                        
                        <p>  
                            <list>
                                
                                <item>
                                    e.g. person: <hi rend="italic">darw?n</hi> will match darwin and darwjn (a possible result based on OCR output). </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                                            
                        <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>Experiment with wildcards to account for differences in the terms that result from the OCR extraction process on which this indexed is based.</p>
                        

                    </div>
                    <!--<div>


                        <head>Wildcard and Approximate Match Searches</head>
                        <p>A user may enter a term with a wildcard AND a term without into a single
                            free-text search field; these will be treated as separate queries (the
                            term with operators as a wildcard query, and the one without as a
                            "fuzzy" search). </p>
                    </div> -->
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Controlled Vocabulary Search Fields</head>
                    <p>
                    Subject and Image descriptors are entered by selecting terms from a controlled
                    vocabulary.  To select a term, select the vocabulary you want to use, and then click the vocabulary icon next to the input field. This will result launch a pop-up window that displays the entire
                   hierarchical controlled vocabulary.  Navigate through the hierarchy by expanding and contracting classes.  To select a term, click the checkbox appearing
                    next to it, and then press the 'Insert' button that appears in the bottom of the window.  Your term will appear in the search form.  To close the Controlled Vocabulary, click the 
                    close button at the bottom of the window.</p>
             
                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>You may select more than one term from different points in the hierarchy; these will be joined during the search with a Boolean AND.</p>
                              
                
                </div>
                
                
                
                <div>
                    <head> Boolean Searches:  AND, OR, NOT</head>
                    <p>
                        Separate search terms into individual fields to conduct searches using additional Boolean
                        operators (AND, OR, or NOT). </p>
                    
                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>Multiple terms entered into a single field are automatically joined with a Boolean AND.</p>
                        
               
                    <div><head>AND Searches</head>
                        
                        <p>
                        To generate fewer search results, add additional terms to the query.  For instance the query 
                        <hi rend="italic">bacon AND spedding</hi> returns more results than <hi rend="italic">bacon AND spedding AND ellis</hi>.
                    </p>
                    <p>  
                        <list>
                        
                        <item>
                           e.g. person: <hi rend="italic">bacon spedding</hi> (entered in one person field) </item>
                        <item>
                            e.g. person: <hi rend="italic">bacon</hi>  <hi rend="bold">AND</hi> person: <hi rend="italic">spedding</hi> <hi rend="bold">AND</hi> person: <hi rend="italic">ellis</hi>
                        </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                   </div>
                    
                
                
                <div><head>OR Searches</head>
                    
                    <p>
                        To broaden search results, use the OR operator.  For instance to find all articles with occurrences of oxford university or cambridge university construct the following query.
                    </p>
                    <p>For Example: 
                        <list>
                            <item>
                               institution: <hi rend="italic">oxford university </hi> <hi rend="bold">AND</hi>  institution: <hi rend="italic">cambridge university </hi></item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div><head>NOT Searches</head>
                    
                    <p>
                        A NOT search can be used to filter items from results. For example to distinguish between the person Darwin, and the place Darwin, construct the following query.    
                    </p>
                    <p> 
                        <list>
                            <item>e.g. 
                                person: <hi rend="italic">darwin</hi> <hi rend="bold">NOT</hi> place: darwin</item>
                          
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                
          </div>
                
                <div><head>Date Ranges</head>
                    <p>Search queries can be constrained to examine only a subset of publication years; for example to find articles referencing The Great Exhibition of 1851 that were published 
                        in the months leading up to the event, try the following query. </p>
                        
                    <p> 
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                e.g. <hi rend="italic">institution: glass house </hi> <hi rend="bold">AND</hi>  <hi rend="italic">year from: 1850, year to: 1852</hi></item>
                           
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div><head>Publication Filter</head>
                    <p>Queries can be constrained to examine only a subset of the six core titles in the corpus by selecting the filter criteria (AND, OR, or NOT) and selecting one or more titles
                        from the select box.  Front matter materials, supplements and end matter material will be searched according to the core title to which they belong.  When more than one title is selected, these are treated within the query as a Boolean OR.
                           </p>
                                                       
                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>By default, searches operate across all publication titles.</p>
                     
                     
                    <p> 
                        <list>                            <item>
                               e.g. <hi rend="bold">AND</hi>  <hi rend="italic">Leader (1850-1860)</hi> - only returns items appearing in the Leader.</item>
                            <item> 
                               e.g.  <hi rend="bold">NOT</hi> <hi rend="italic">Leader (1850-1860)</hi> - returns items appearing in titles other than the Leader.
                            </item>
                            <item>e.g. <hi rend="bold">AND</hi> ( <hi rend="italic">Leader (1850-1860)</hi> OR <hi rend="italic">Northern Star (1838-1852)</hi>) - only returns items appearing in the Leader or the Northern Star.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div><head>Sorting Results</head>
                    <p>Results may be sorted according to publication date, by publication title, or by relevance.  The default sorting criterion is by relevance,
                        a scoring mechanism used within the underlying search engine, Lucene.  Within Lucene, relevance is determined by how many times a query term
                        appears in a document relative to the number of times the term appears in all documents in the index.
                        When sorting by date, results are ordered by year, month, and then day. Sorting by publication results in items that are ordered according to the <hi rend="italic">actual</hi> publication title for the issue in which they occur,
                        in ascending order.
                    
                    </p>
                    
                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>With large resultsets, try sorting by publication to page through results alphabetically.</p>
                    
                   </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Search Results</head>

                    <p>Search results are returned for each item in the keyword repository matching
                        the supplied search criteria.</p>
               
               
                       <p>MORE TO COME</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Refining Results</head>
                    <p> Users may refine a result set by selecting a semantic qualifier (names,
                        persons, places, institutions, semantic tags, image metadata). Once
                        selected, this term is added to the query as a boolean AND. </p>
                    <p>Filters may be removed by clicking the 'remove' link next to a filter. </p>
                </div>

                </div>

            </div>


            <div>
                <head>Browsing</head>
                <p>Browsing indexes have been created out the hierarchical schemes used to assign
                    controlled subject and image descriptors to items in the facsimile repository.
                    Subjects have been automatically assigned using the <title>UCREL Semantic
                        Analysis System (USAS)</title>tagset; Image descriptors have been manually
                    assigned using an adapted form of the <title>Database of Mid-Victorian
                        Illustration (DMVI)</title> To learn more about these controlled
                    vocabularies and the process used to assign keywords, please read the <xref
                        type="internal" from="p1_2">Technical Introduction</xref>.</p>

                <div>
                    <head>Selecting Terms</head>
                    <p/>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Refining Results</head>
                    <p>to come</p>

                </div>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
