<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
  <TEI.2 id="p8">
      <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
          <fileDesc>
              <titleStmt>
                  <title>FAQ and Help</title>
                  
              </titleStmt>
              <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                  <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
              </publicationStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="NO">
                  <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
              </sourceDesc>
          </fileDesc>
          <encodingDesc>
              <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
          </encodingDesc>
          <revisionDesc>
              <change>
                  <date>2008-03-27</date>
                  <respStmt>
                      <name>EL</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <item>created file</item>
              </change>
              
              
          </revisionDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      
      <text>
          <body>
<div>
              
              <head>FAQ and Help</head>
    <div>
   <head>Search</head>
    <div>
              <p>Multiple terms entered into a single field are treated as boolean ANDs.
</p>
</div>
<div><head>Fuzzy Searching</head>
<p>The default search type is fuzzy - the user can select from the similarity dropdown list, or take the default value, 90%.  Selecting a lower percentage will increase the number of results returned, because the search engine will count 'fuzzier' or less exact matches as hits.
</p>
</div>
<div><head>Wildcard/Stemming</head>
<p> If the user enters a term with a wildcard, the term will be searched as a wildcard query.  To perform a single character wildcard search use the "?" symbol. To perform a multiple character wildcard search use the "*" symbol.  The single character wildcard search looks for terms that match that with the single character replaced. For example, to search for "text" or "test" you can use the search: te?t
</p>
<p>Multiple character wildcard searches looks for 0 or more characters. For example, to search for test, tests or tester, you can use the search: test*
</p>
<p>You can also use the wildcard searches in the middle of a term: te*t
But, you cannot use a * or ? symbol as the first character of a search.</p>

</div>
<div>
<head>Combined Searches</head>
<p>A user may enter a term with a wildcard AND a term without into a single search field; these will be treated as separate queries (the term with operators as a wildcard query, and the one without as a "fuzzy" search).
</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Search Results</head>
<p>

Users may refine a result set by selecting a semantic qualifier (names, persons, places, institutions, semantic tags, image metadata). Once selected, this term is added to the query as a boolean AND.
</p>
<p>Filters may be removed by clicking the 'remove' link next to a filter. 
</p>
              
</div>
</div>
 <div><head>Browse</head>
     <p>Users may browse the controlled vocabularies for two keyword types: semantic tags, and image descriptors.</p>
     </div>
</div>              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
          </body>
      </text>
  </TEI.2>
  
