<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
  <TEI.2 id="p8">
      <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
          <fileDesc>
              <titleStmt>
                  <title>Help</title>
                  
              </titleStmt>
              <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                  <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
              </publicationStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="NO">
                  <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
              </sourceDesc>
          </fileDesc>
          <encodingDesc>
              <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
          </encodingDesc>
          <revisionDesc>
              <change>
                  <date>2008-03-27</date>
                  <respStmt>
                      <name>EL</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <item>created file</item>
              </change>
              
              
          </revisionDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      
      <text>
          <body>
                       
   <div>
   <head>Keyword Search Tips</head>
        <p>
            The Keyword Repository allows users to search for keywords that have been assigned to items within <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>
            using a combination of controlled and free-text entry fields.  This section describes how to enter search terms and refine search queries, and how to
            interpret and refine search results.
        </p>
       <p>
           This section <hi rend="bold">does not</hi> describe how to search the full-text appearing within fascimiles.  For this information, please read: <xref  type="external" url="http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/Tips.htm">Advanced Search Tips</xref>           in the fascimile repository.
       </p>
       
       <div><head>Free-text Entry Search Fields</head>
           <p>Persons, places and institutions can be entered by selecting the entity type from the drop down menu of the corresponding field, 
               and then keying in text (See example below).  Multi-word terms may be entered in full (e.g. John Smith), or in a partial form (e.g. Smith).
           </p>
           <p>[Insert Screenshot ]</p>
           <p>Subject and Image descriptors are entered by selecting a controlled vocabulary from the drop down menu, and then selecting terms from the corresponding thesaurus, reached by clicking
           the thesaurus icon: [insert icon] next to the input field.</p>
           
    <div>
        <head>Multiple Terms in One Search Box</head>
        <p>Multiple terms typed into one search box are automatically interpreted as a Boolean AND.  If conducting
            a Boolean search using different operators (e.g. OR, NOT), enter terms into separate search boxes </p>
        
             <p>[Insert John Smith Screen shot]</p>
             
</div>
<div><head>Approximate Match Searching</head>
<p>By default, queries using the free-text fields are compared to the keyword index based on an exact match match to the terms entered- the user can select from the similarity dropdown list, or take the default value, 90%.  Selecting a lower percentage will increase the number of results returned, because the search engine will count 'fuzzier' or less exact matches as hits.
</p>
</div>
<div><head>Wildcard/Stemming</head>
<p> If the user enters a term with a wildcard, the term will be searched as a wildcard query.  To perform a single character wildcard search use the "?" symbol. To perform a multiple character wildcard search use the "*" symbol.  The single character wildcard search looks for terms that match that with the single character replaced. For example, to search for "text" or "test" you can use the search: te?t
</p>
<p>Multiple character wildcard searches looks for 0 or more characters. For example, to search for test, tests or tester, you can use the search: test*
</p>
<p>You can also use the wildcard searches in the middle of a term: te*t
But, you cannot use a * or ? symbol as the first character of a search.</p>

</div>
<div>
<head>Combined Searches</head>
<p>A user may enter a term with a wildcard AND a term without into a single search field; these will be treated as separate queries (the term with operators as a wildcard query, and the one without as a "fuzzy" search).
</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Search Results</head>
<p>

Users may refine a result set by selecting a semantic qualifier (names, persons, places, institutions, semantic tags, image metadata). Once selected, this term is added to the query as a boolean AND.
</p>
<p>Filters may be removed by clicking the 'remove' link next to a filter. 
</p>
              
</div>
</div>
 </div>
       
       <div><head>Browsing Tips</head>
     <p>Users may browse the controlled vocabularies for two keyword types: semantic tags, and image descriptors.</p>
     </div>
  
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
              
          </body>
      </text>
  </TEI.2>
  
