<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p8">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Help</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head>Searching Keywords</head>
                <p> The keyword index allows users to search for keywords that have been assigned to
                    items within <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> using a combination of controlled and
                    free-text entry fields. The index was compiled by first algorithmically and
                    manually applying keywords to articles in the <hi rend="italic">ncse</hi>
                    corpus. The outputs of these processes were then aggregated, and indexed using
                    the high-performance text search engine Lucene. Persons, places, institutions,
                    and subjects were generated by processing the <hi rend="italic">uncorrected</hi>
                    OCR output housed in the facsimile repository using a variety of data mining and
                    natural language processing techniques. Image descriptors were manually applied
                    to articles within the corpus using a controlled vocabulary. The index
                    represents approximately 317,402 items within the facsimile repository,
                    including titles, articles, advertisements, front matter, and images. To learn
                    more about the processes undertaken in generating the keyword index, read the
                        <xref type="internal" from="p1_2">Technical Introduction</xref>. </p>
                <p> This section describes how to enter search terms and refine search queries, and
                    how to interpret and refine search results. It <hi rend="bold">does not</hi>
                    describe how to search the full-text appearing within fascimiles. For this
                    information, please read: Searching Facsimiles, below. 
</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Free-text Entry Search Fields</head>
                    <p>To search for Persons, Places or Institutions, select the keyword type from
                        the drop down menu of the corresponding field, and then key in text.
                        Multi-word terms may be entered in full (e.g. John Smith), or in a partial
                        form (e.g. Smith). </p>

                    <div>
                        <head>Multiple Terms in One Search Box</head>
                        <p>Multiple terms typed into one search box are automatically interpreted as
                            a Boolean AND, and are treated as separate queries. If conducting a
                            Boolean search using different operators (e.g. OR, NOT), enter terms
                            into separate search boxes. Boolean terms entered directly into the
                            search fields will result in zero results being returned.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Case-Insensitive</head>
                        <p> Search terms can be entered in upper or lower case. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Approximate Match Searching</head>
                        <p>By default, queries entered using the free-text fields are compared to
                            the keyword index based on an exact match to the terms entered. However,
                            the user can select a percentage to request that search terms be matched
                            that are of higher or lower degrees of similarity to the terms indexed
                            in the database. Entering a higher percentage (e.g. 90%) will return
                            matches that are very similar to the entered text, while entering a
                            lower percentage (e.g. 50%) will return results that are much less
                            similar to the entered text. </p>
                        <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>Adjust this threshold to account for
                            differences in the terms that result from the OCR extraction process on
                            which this index is based.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Wildcard/Stemming</head>
                        <p>As an alternative to approximate matching, use an asterisk (*) or
                            question mark (?) to broaden search results. You can use wildcard
                            searches in the middle of a term , however wildcard symbol cannot be the
                            first character of a search term.</p>

                        <p> Use an asterisk (*) to search for different words beginning with the
                            same stem. </p>

                        <p>
                            <list>

                                <item> e.g. place: <hi rend="italic">waterl*</hi> will match
                                    waterloo and waterlow (a possible result based on OCR output).
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>

                        <p>The question mark (?) performs a single character wildcard search, and
                            will return variants of the term entered with the single character
                            replaced. </p>

                        <p>
                            <list>

                                <item> e.g. person: <hi rend="italic">darw?n</hi> will match darwin
                                    and darwjn (a possible result based on OCR output). </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>

                        <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>Experiment with wildcards to account for
                            differences in the terms that result from the OCR extraction process on
                            which this index is based.</p>


                    </div>
                    <!--<div>


                        <head>Wildcard and Approximate Match Searches</head>
                        <p>A user may enter a term with a wildcard AND a term without into a single
                            free-text search field; these will be treated as separate queries (the
                            term with operators as a wildcard query, and the one without as a
                            "fuzzy" search). </p>
                    </div> -->
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Thesaurus Search Fields</head>
                    <p> Subject and Image descriptors are searched by selecting terms from a
                        controlled vocabulary, or "thesaurus". To select a term, choose a vocabulary
                        and then click the vocabulary icon next to the input field. This will launch
                        a pop-up window that displays the entire hierarchical controlled vocabulary.
                        Navigate through the hierarchy by expanding and contracting classes. To
                        select a term, click the checkbox appearing next to it, and then press the
                        'Insert' button that appears in the bottom of the window. Your term will
                        appear in the search form. You may select more than one term from different
                        points in the hierarchy; these will be joined during the search with a
                        Boolean AND. To close the vocabulary, click the close button at the bottom
                        of the window.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>Searching within the image vocabulary will
                        only return items from the corpus that contain visual material.</p>


                </div>
                <div>
                    <head> Logical Operators: AND, OR, NOT</head>
                    <p> Separate search terms into individual fields to conduct searches using
                        additional logical or Boolean operators (AND, OR, or NOT). </p>

                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>Multiple terms entered into a single field are
                        automatically joined with a Boolean AND.</p>


                    <div>
                        <head>AND Searches</head>

                        <p> To generate fewer search results, add additional terms to the query. For
                            instance the query <hi rend="italic">bacon AND spedding</hi> returns
                            more results than <hi rend="italic">bacon AND spedding AND ellis</hi>. </p>
                        <p>
                            <list>

                                <item> e.g. person: <hi rend="italic">bacon spedding</hi> (entered
                                    in one person field) </item>
                                <item> e.g. person: <hi rend="italic">bacon</hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold">AND</hi> person: <hi rend="italic">spedding</hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold">AND</hi> person: <hi rend="italic">ellis</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>



                    <div>
                        <head>OR Searches</head>

                        <p> To broaden search results, use the OR operator. For instance to find all
                            articles with occurrences of oxford university or cambridge university
                            construct the following query. </p>
                        <p>For Example: <list>
                                <item> institution: <hi rend="italic">oxford university </hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold">AND</hi> institution: <hi rend="italic"
                                        >cambridge university </hi></item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>NOT Searches</head>

                        <p> A NOT search can be used to filter items from results. For example to
                            distinguish between the person Darwin, and the place Darwin, construct
                            the following query. </p>
                        <p>
                            <list>
                                <item>e.g. person: <hi rend="italic">darwin</hi>
                                    <hi rend="bold">NOT</hi> place: darwin</item>

                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>

                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Date Ranges</head>
                    <p>Search queries can be constrained to examine only a subset of publication
                        years; for example to find articles referencing The Great Exhibition of 1851
                        that were published in the months leading up to the event, try the following
                        query. </p>

                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <item> e.g. <hi rend="italic">institution: glass house </hi>
                                <hi rend="bold">AND</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">year from: 1850, year to: 1852</hi></item>

                        </list>
                    </p>

                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Publication Filter</head>
                    <p>Queries can be constrained to examine only a subset of the six core titles in
                        the corpus by selecting the filter criteria (AND, OR, or NOT) and selecting
                        one or more titles from the select box. Front matter materials, supplements
                        and end matter material will be searched according to the core title to
                        which they belong. When more than one title is selected, these are treated
                        within the query as a Boolean OR. </p>

                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>By default, searches operate across all
                        publication titles.</p>


                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <item> e.g. <hi rend="bold">AND</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Leader (1850-1860)</hi> - only returns items
                                appearing in the Leader.</item>
                            <item> e.g. <hi rend="bold">NOT</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Leader (1850-1860)</hi> - returns items appearing
                                in titles other than the Leader. </item>
                            <item>e.g. <hi rend="bold">AND</hi> ( <hi rend="italic">Leader
                                    (1850-1860)</hi> OR <hi rend="italic">Northern Star
                                (1838-1852)</hi>) - only returns items appearing in the Leader or
                                the Northern Star.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>

                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Sorting Results</head>
                    <p>Results may be sorted according to publication date, by publication title, or
                        by relevance. The default sorting criterion is by relevance, a scoring
                        mechanism used within the underlying search engine, Lucene. Within Lucene,
                        relevance is determined by how many times a query term appears in a document
                        relative to the number of times the term appears in all documents in the
                        index. When sorting by date, results are ordered by year, month, and then
                        day. Sorting by publication results in items that are ordered according to
                        the <hi rend="italic">actual</hi> publication title for the issue in which
                        they occur, in ascending order. </p>

                    <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi>With large resultsets, try sorting by
                        publication to page through results alphabetically.</p>

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Search Results</head>

                    <p>Search results are returned for each item in the keyword index matching the
                        supplied search criteria. Each result includes a bibliographic citation for
                        the item, links to the facsimile repository, and a panel containing keywords
                        that have been assigned to the item. View the keywords by clicking the '+'
                        sign next to each item. </p>
                    <p>Within the panel that displays, keywords of each type (persons, places,
                        institutions, subjects and images) are alphabetically arranged, and include
                        the frequency with which they appear in the item. Each keyword is also a
                        link.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Refining Results</head>
                        <p> Click a keyword appearing with items to to add it search query as a
                            Boolean AND. This will reduce the number of results returned, as the
                            refined result set will only include items that met the original query
                            terms AND the keyword term. Multiple filters may be added in this way,
                            and may be removed in any order, by clicking the 'x' symbol next to the
                            term as displayed in the search results summary. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Viewing Items</head>
                        <p> To view items from search results in the facsimile repository, use the
                            links provided with the bibliographic citations provided for each
                            result. The 'item' link will display the individual item, while the page
                            and issue links display the item within a larger context.</p>
                    </div>

                </div>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Browsing Keywords</head>
                <p>Browsing indexes have been created out the hierarchical schemes used to assign
                    controlled subject and image descriptors to items in the facsimile repository.
                    Subjects have been automatically assigned using the <title>UCREL Semantic
                        Analysis System (USAS)</title>tagset; Image descriptors have been manually
                    assigned using an adapted form of the <title>Database of Mid-Victorian
                        Illustration (DMVI)</title> To learn more about these controlled
                    vocabularies and the process used to assign keywords, please read the <xref
                        type="internal" from="p1_2">Technical Introduction</xref>.</p>
                <p>Begin browsing by selecting a top-level term from the chosen vocabulary. When a
                    term is selected, the items in the corpus assigned the term will be displayed.
                    Items are ordered by relevance, a scoring mechanism used within the underlying
                    search engine, Lucene. Within Lucene, relevance is determined by how many times
                    a query term appears in a document relative to the number of times the term
                    appears in all documents in the index. </p>
                <p>To the right of the intermediate results, the hierarchy will display. Use the
                    tree display to navigate and combine terms from different sections of the
                    hierarchy in order to narrow the search results returned. Terms added to queries
                    may be removed by clicking the 'x' symbol next to the term as displayed in the
                    search results summary.</p>
                <p>For example, to find <hi rend="bolditalic">images of children at the sea</hi>,
                    browse by image as follows: </p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Settings <hi rend="bold">NARROWED TO</hi> Natural environments
                            &gt; The sea <hi rend="bold">COMBINED WITH</hi> People &gt;
                            Figures &gt; Children </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>To search for items about <hi rend="bolditalic">war activities at sea</hi>, try
                    the following query:</p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Government &amp; the Public Domain <hi rend="bold">NARROWED
                            TO</hi> Warfare, defence and the army; weapons <hi rend="bold">COMBINED
                                WITH</hi> Movement, Location, Travel &amp; Transport &gt;
                            Sailing, swimming, etc. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="bolditalic">Tip:</hi> The keyword index includes over a million terms
                    from the subject hierarchy. Combine terms to return a manageable resultset.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Searching Facsimiles</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>The Facsimile component of ncse is delivered using Olive Software's Viewpoint
                        software. This comes at the end of a sequence of processing carried out by
                        Olive which involves a number of stages:</p>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                        <item><hi rend="bold">digitization</hi> of each page from micro-film</item>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">optical character recognition</hi> (OCR) to produce a
                            text version of each page</item>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">segmentation</hi> of each issue and page into
                            'articles', which may often be quite small elements, e.g. an obituary
                            notice</item>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">integration</hi> of the page image and text materials
                            and the segmentation information into a repository that can be made
                            available to readers via the Viewpoint software</item>

                    </list>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Viewpoint</hi> software provides a number of different
                        types of browse and search functions to aid readers in reading and exploring
                        the digitized materials.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Searching in the Facsimile component</head>
                    <p>The Olive software provides very sophisticated search facilities, which are
                        described, with examples, below. There are a number of important factors to
                        bear in mind in relation to the results that are shown:</p>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                        <item>The searches are carried out on the text produced in the OCR process.
                            The success rate of the OCR process is often quite remarkable, but it is
                            constrained by the quality of the source materials. In some cases the
                            source materials cannot even be read by the human eye, and in a number
                            of other cases there is smudging or other distortion of the print that
                            makes reliable OCR impossible even where it is decipherable to the human
                            eye. It is important to remember in carrying out searches that the
                            results can only be as good as the OCR. For any given search, therefore,
                            the results will show all the instances where the search term has been
                            correctly converted to text, but there may of course be other cases
                            where the term was indeed in the original print but cannot be retrieved
                            because the software has no way of identifying it.</item>
                        <item>Results are displayed in the same format, and the result list has the
                            same features, for all the different types of search. <list>
                                <item>Up to 1,000 'hits' will be returned, the results shown by
                                    default in the form of snippets, with up to five results per
                                    screen, and with the search term highlighted in each display.</item>
                                <item>The hits are shown in order of 'relevancy', based on an
                                    algorithm in the Olive system.</item>
                                <item>The search results are based on 'segments', with one result
                                    included for each segment in which the search term is found.</item>
                                <item>Full bibliographic information is shown for each item, and
                                    where the display is in the form of snippets, it is possible to
                                    view the OCR text of the snippet (i.e. the text produced in the
                                    OCR process).</item>
                                <item> Click on the snippet itself to see the full text of the item,
                                    which opens in a new window.</item>
                                <item> It is also possible to view the full page in which the item
                                    appears, or the cover of the issue in which it appears, by
                                    clicking on the relevant thumbnail.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>The full <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> resource includes multiple editions
                            where these exist. This may have a distorting effect on the number of
                            hits, with segments apparently repeated when in fact it is the same item
                            appearing in a number of editions.</item>
                        <item>In general it would be true to say that the simple browse and search
                            functions require little prior knowledge or understanding of the <hi
                                rend="bold">ncse</hi> publications and their history, but effective
                            use of the more sophisticated search techniques tends to require a
                            greater degree of familiarity and understanding.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Simple Search</head>
                    <p>The reader may enter any term in the Search box, and may either search in all
                        types of material (the default), or may restrict the search to Articles,
                        Pictures or Advertisements. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Example:</hi> If you type 'wellington' in the search box,
                        1,000 hits are returned, the exact number 1,000 suggesting that there are
                        more than 1,000 occurrences of Wellington in the repository. Keeping the
                        same term, and restricting the search to Articles has little effect on the
                        number of hits, not surprisingly. Restricting the same search to
                        Advertisements, however, reduces the number of hits to 807. </p>
                    <p>Changing the search term to 'walmer' reduces the number of hits to 100, many
                        from the coverage of the death of the Duke of Wellington at Walmer Castle.
                        Changing the search term again, to 'Walmer Castle' reduces the hits to 44:
                        the software looks for instances of 'Walmer' and 'Castle' in reasonably
                        close proximity. It is also possible to search for this as an <hi
                            rend="italic">exact term</hi> by using "Walmer Castle" - i.e. enclosed
                        in double quotes - and this reduces the number of hits further, to 28. </p>
                    <p>A search for 'darwin' produces 539 hits. 'charles darwin' reduces the hits to
                        337. With the exact-term form "charles darwin" there are only 47. Searching
                        on 'erasmus darwin' produces 29 hits, but since this is not the exact-term
                        form a number of the hits refer in fact to Erasmus's grandson Charles. The
                        exact-term form "Erasmus Darwin" produces 6 hits. </p>
                    <p>For more on 'exact term' searches, and other features of the search function,
                        see <hi rend="italic">Extending your use of the Search Function</hi> below.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Advanced Search</head>
                    <p>The advanced search screen provides a number of ways to filter the search
                        results in order to help readers find what they are looking for more
                        precisely. <hi rend="italic">Note that in order to refine an advanced search
                            you have already executed, you need to click again on the Advanced
                            Search link in the results screen.</hi> The filter mechanisms include:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>restricting the search to a single title and type of material </item>
                        <item>providing a 'metadata' profile, in which a combination of metadata
                            elements can be specified: Issue title; Volume/Series; Issue number;
                            Edition; Page; Price; Bibliographic Location; Size. Where feasible, the
                            metadata terms can be selected from a drop-down list, so the reader is
                            guided on what are the valid search terms. To use this feature
                            effectively, some understanding is required of the <hi rend="bold"
                            >ncse</hi> publications and their structures. </item>
                        <item>search within a specified date range. E.g. a search for 'dickens'
                            within the date range 1/1/1806-31/12/1830 produces 4 hits, none to do
                            with Charles Dickens. The same search in the range 1/1/1831-31/12/01850
                            gives 361 and for the range 1/1/1851-31/12/1870 there are 997 hits; most
                            of the hits in the later periods are of course to do with the author.
                                <hi rend="italic">Note that in using the date range filter, it is
                                important to take into account the date ranges of the publications
                                in</hi>
                            <hi rend="bolditalic">ncse</hi>. </item>
                        <item>the Edition buttons allow you to choose whether to search across all
                            the editions, or to limit it to the Main editions, thereby excluding the
                            'extra' editions, e.g. of the Northern Star, which are listed in the
                            Select Titles box. </item>
                        <item>you may also choose to view your results as 'Snippets' (the default),
                            or in the form of full Articles, or as full pages. Snippets is
                            recommended until your filtering has produced a very small set of
                            results. </item>
                        <item>finally, you may choose to sort the results list by relevance (the
                            default), title, date or size.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Extending your use of the Search Function</head>
                    <p>Click on 'Advanced search tips' in the Advanced Search screen for detailed
                        information on the range of search techniques that are available within the
                        Facsimile system, enabling you to take advantage of the sophisticated search
                        facilities supported by the Olive software. Although these additional
                        features are indeed advanced, in every case they extend or modify the search
                        phrase, and will therefore be typed in the main 'search' box, and do not in
                        fact require the reader to be in the advanced search screen. Where the
                        Advanced Search screen will be needed is when these techniques are combined
                        with other advanced search features, such as filtering by date. The examples
                        below may help to make this clearer.</p>
                    <p> The additional features described are: Wildcards; Logical Operators; Word
                        Modifiers; and Escaping. The last is rather technical and will be very
                        seldom used. The first three, however, may sometimes or often be useful.
                        Rather than repeating what is described in detail in the Olive 'tips'
                        sections, below are some examples to suggest ways in which the advanced
                        features may be used. </p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Wildcards</head>
                        <p>The use of the asterisk to represent any or no characters may be familiar
                            from use of other computer systems. In <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> it may
                            help to compensate for OCR problems, but at the same time it is likely
                            to introduce a certain amount of 'noise' into the results. For example,
                            as noted above, a search for 'darwin' produces 539 hits. A search for
                            'darw*' - meaning the characters 'darw' followed by any number of
                            further characters or by none - gives 913 hits, including not only some
                            additional 'genuine' Darwin references, but items also for 'Darwood' and
                            'Darwen' and so on.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Logical Operators</head>
                        <p>Also known as 'Boolean Operators', these techniques may be useful in
                            expanding or narrowing a set of search results while increasing the
                            degree of accuracy. The &lt; OR &gt; operator increases the
                            number of hits by including all items which contain any one of the
                            search terms, while the &lt; AND &gt; operator decreases the
                            number by requiring that both/all terms are present simultaneously
                            within each item. </p>
                        <p>For example, a search for 'austen &lt; OR &gt; eliot' produces
                            over 1,000 hits, including references to Sir John Eliot and Admiral
                            Austen, while the exact-terms search for "jane austen" &lt; OR
                            &gt; "george eliot" gives 209 hits, but loses such references as
                            'something ... here reminds us of the incomparable Miss Austen...'. </p>
                        <p> The search 'austen &lt; AND &gt; eliot' gives 54 hits, all from
                            catalogues in the Publishers' Circular. A search for 'wellington
                            &lt; OR &gt; napoleon' produces over 1,000 hits, but 'wellington
                            &lt; AND &gt; napoleon' brings the number down to 684. </p>
                        <p>The &lt; NOT &gt; operator allows you to exclude terms from your
                            search. More useful perhaps is the &lt; NEAR &gt; operator,
                            which allows you to search for combinations of terms within a range of
                            up to 9 words of each other. The search 'wellington &lt; NEAR/9
                            &gt; napoleon' reduces the 684 hits found above to 124 items - i.e.
                            there are 124 items in which the names Wellington and Napoleon occur
                            within 9 words of each other. </p>
                        <p> The search 'palmerston &lt; AND &gt; grey' gives 738 hits, while
                            'palmerston &lt; NEAR/9 &gt; grey' produces 76. Similarly,
                            'palmerston &lt; AND &gt; gladstone &lt; AND &gt;
                            disraeli' provides 310 items, while 'palmerston &lt; NEAR/9 &gt;
                            (gladstone &lt; OR &gt; disraeli)' reduces this to 162 hits. The
                            search 'palmerston &lt; NEAR/9 &gt; (gladstone &lt; NOT
                            &gt; disraeli)' produces 79 items - i.e. those in which the names
                            Palmerston and Gladstone are within nine words of each other but
                            Disraeli's name is not within this range. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Word Modifiers</head>
                    <p>The most useful of these is likely to be the &lt; FUZZY &gt;
                        operator, which allows the reader to indicate how many 'errors' to allow in
                        matching the search term. It is an alternative and perhaps a bit more
                        sophisticated method than wildcards for making allowance for OCR errors. As
                        indicated above, a simple search for 'darwin' produces 539 hits; changing
                        the search term to '&lt; FUZZY/1 &gt; darwin' tells the system
                        you're prepared to accept one character being different, and the number of
                        hits goes up to 758. Among these are some extra 'genuine' Darwin references,
                        but also 'darlin' and 'darwen' (see the wildcard example above for
                        comparison). Increasing the degree of latitude to '&lt; FUZZY/2 &gt;
                        darwin' gives over 1,000 hits.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Complex/Compound Searches</head>
                    <p> It is possible to combine more or less all the advanced search techniques in
                        quite complex ways, and in creating these the Advanced Search screen will be
                        needed. </p>
                    <p>The most frequent type of compound search is likely to involved adding a date
                        filter to some other technique. For example you could carry out the same
                        search for each of several decades: 'gladstone &lt; NEAR/9 &gt;
                        disraeli' for the period 1/1/1840-31/12/1849 produces 8 hits; the same
                        search for 1/1/1850-31/12/1859 provides 95 hits; and for 1/1/1860-
                        31/12/1869 there are 13 hits; and so on. </p>
                    <p> There may be occasions when the reader wishes to search within a particular
                        publication. The search for Gladstone and Disraeli in close proximity in the
                        period 1/1/1850-31/12/1859 reduces the number of hits from 95 to 53 when
                        only the Leader - Town Edition is searched. There is no point carrying out
                        this search in the Northern Star since its coverage is 1837-1852, but in
                        fact the search for Gladstone near Disraeli over the whole of the Northern
                        Star - Main Edition yields only 4 hits. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <p>It takes time to become familiar with the various ways in which the advanced
                        search features in the Facsimile part of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> can be used. Experimentation
                        is the key, and with time and patience readers will be able to become expert
                        in retrieving the information they wish to find and in developing techniques
                        to explore the edition for new questions and lines of enquiry. </p>
                    <p> A further level of complexity is introduced by the parallel searching and
                        browsing that is possible within the Keyword part of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>. The final section
                        of this guide will give some comparative examples of searching for the same
                        kind of information in each of the two components. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
