<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd" >
<TEI.2 id="g4_ng003" n="" type="pop" rend="type03"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>Refugee populations in the UK</title> 
		  <title type="sub">Algerians</title><author><name type="foreName">Michael</name>
			 <name type="surname">Collyer</name></author></titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <p><date><date>April 2003</date></date></p> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <p></p> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <revisionDesc> 
		<change><date>2003-06-23</date> 
		  <respStmt><name>FH</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		  <item>made some corrections</item> 
		</change> 
		<change><date>2003-06-01</date> 
		  <respStmt><name>FH</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		  <item>finished checking guide</item> 
		</change> 
		<change><date>2003-05-31</date> 
		  <respStmt><name>FH</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		  <item>added boxes and dates to the text</item> 
		</change> 
		<change><date value="2003-05-08">2003-06-11</date> 
		  <respStmt><name>JG</name><resp>encoder</resp> 
		  </respStmt> 
		  <item>made changes</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisionDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text id="p4_ng003"> 
	 <group> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_00" rend="off"> 
		  <body><head>About the author and acknowledgements</head><div type="about"><head>About the author</head> 
		  <p>Michael Collyer currently holds a Nuffield Foundation New Career
			 Development Fellowship at the Sussex Centre for Migration Research, University
			 of Sussex. He recently completed his DPhil, also at Sussex. His thesis set out
			 to explain the movement of Algerians to the UK. Before starting his DPhil he
			 spent four years as a youth worker in Marseilles, working closely with groups
			 of North African origin and particularly refugees from the Algerian conflict.
			 The author can be contacted at 
			 <xref rend="email" url="M.Collyer@sussex.ac.uk">M.Collyer@sussex.ac.uk</xref>.
			 </p></div><div type="ackno"><head>Acknowledgements</head> 
		  <p>The author would like to thank the staff at the Algerian Refugee
			 Council, the staff of the Algerian Education Association and the many other
			 individuals who assisted with the research on which this report is based. Some
			 of this material was presented to an audience at the <foreign>Society for Algerian
			 Studies</foreign> and feedback resulting from that paper was gratefully received. ICAR
			 would also like to thank Alison Pargeter, Research Fellow at the International
			 Policy Institute, King's College London, for her comments on final drafts of
			 this guide. Much of the research was undertaken during the author's DPhil
			 fieldwork that was supported by an ESRC postgraduate training award [no.
			 R00429834348] and further investigation has been supported by a Nuffield
			 Foundation New Career Development fellowship. </p></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_01"> 
		  <body> 
		  <head>Introduction</head><div> 
			 <p>The Algerian population in Britain is poorly known and little
				understood in the wider British community. Until the early 1990s there were
				relatively few Algerians in the <foreign>UK</foreign>. Over the last ten years, particularly since
				the escalation of the conflict in Algeria from 1992 onwards, the number of
				Algerians has grown significantly. Even though this population remains small
				compared to more established migrant and refugee groups in the UK, it is
				extremely diverse. Developing events in Algeria have provoked the departure of
				a number of very different groups of people, many of whom are represented in
				the population resident in the UK.</p> 
			 <p>Although there are a number of Algerian associations in the UK,
				these are not necessarily representative of the population as a whole, and
				although bonds of solidarity between individuals are extremely strong, there is
				little sense of a unified 'community'. Indeed, some sections of the Algerian
				population are characterised more by mutual suspicion than by solidarity. This
				concern is not helped by the widespread ignorance of the situation in Algeria
				amongst the UK population as a whole. In general Algerians in Britain,
				particularly recent arrivals, are extremely isolated since many of them lack
				both a cohesive community and a sympathetic host population.</p>
			 <p>This navigation guide is focused on Algerian refugees and asylum
				seekers in the UK, though the scope of the guide is not restricted to those
				people who have requested or been granted asylum. There is also a considerable
				group of undocumented Algerians resident in the UK who have either been refused
				asylum or who, for a variety of reasons, have never applied for international
				protection. In a legal sense, these people are obviously not refugees, but the
				guide will also consider their situation. There is considerable agreement that
				the sociological understanding of refugee populations must be separated from
				the legal definition, in order to include the category of 'genuine but
				unrecognised refugees'<note>See, for example, Zolberg, A. R., Suhrke, A. and
				  Aguayo, S. [1989] 
				  <title>Escape from violence: Conflict and the refugee crisis in
					 the developing world</title>. Open University Press, New York.</note></p> 
			 <p>Comments in this guide on the Algerian population will therefore
				be concerned with those Algerians who left Algeria after the state of emergency
				was declared in February 1992. Although the author recognises that not all
				these people are refugees, in either a legal or a sociological sense, the
				situation of generalised violence that has persisted during the state of
				emergency is likely to have played a role in their decision to leave the
				country. In order to keep terminology free from confusion, the guide will refer
				to those people who are not awaiting the result of an asylum claim, or who have
				not been recognised as a refugee or granted Exceptional Leave to Remain [ELR],
				as 'migrants'<note>ELR status has now been replaced by a new 'humanitarian
				  protection' status. More information about this change is available from the 
				  <xref url="http://www.refugeecouncil.org.uk/news/dec2002/curr049.htm">Refugee
					 Council's news briefing</xref> and the 
				  <xref url="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/n_story.asp?item_id=293">Home
					 Office</xref>.</note>. This should not be taken as a judgement on the
				legitimacy of any claim they may have to refugee status. The guide also
				includes some information on the small population of Algerians who were already
				resident in the UK when the state of emergency was declared. </p>
			 <p>This navigation guide aims to present a coherent account of the
				situation facing Algerians in the UK through the provision of basic information
				and links to other resources. The first section briefly examines the historical
				context of the movement of Algerians to the UK and aims to highlight the range
				of explanations of Algerian history and introduce the reader to the diversity
				of material available on this. The following section then provides basic
				information on the characteristics of the Algerian community, based on the data
				and information available. The legal issues section discusses key legislation
				affecting this population and section four turns to statistical data and
				presents available quantitative information from national and international
				sources. </p>
			 <p>Section five provides a brief outline of Algerian literature,
				music and film in order to give some cultural background to the community and
				the following section then considers a range of key issues facing this
				population; asylum, undocumented status, employment, isolation and contacts
				with Algeria. The final sections detail all references and websites cited and
				provide more information to follow up in each area. The information in the
				guide is based on the author's own DPhil research, carried out between May 2000
				and September 2001. This remains the most significant research undertaken with
				the Algerian population in the UK and it is supplemented, for this guide, with
				follow up work carried out in January and February 2003. This involved primary
				research with Algerian migrants and a range of key informants in addition to
				collating data from available NGO reports and secondary literature
				sources.</p></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_02"> 
		  <body> 
		  <head>Historical context</head><div> 
			 <p>There is a wide range of online<note>mongst the most comprehensive
				  is the 
				  <xref url="http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/dztoc.html">book length
					 study</xref> at the Library of Congress. The history section in English at 
				  <xref url="http://www.rcd-algerie.org/history.htm">Algerian
					 online</xref> is shorter and still very good.</note> historical sources on
				Algeria and a growing body of work published in English, as well as a large
				number of publications in other languages, particularly French. This section
				provides a brief overview of early events in Algeria's history and the
				background to the current conflict. </p> 
		  </div> 
		  <div><head>The turbulent history up to the current conflict</head> 
		  <p>The original inhabitants of North Africa were Berber speaking
			 people. There is a great diversity of Berber languages; the site 
			 <xref rend="external" url="http://www.ethnologue.com/show_country.asp?name=Algeria">Ethnologue</xref>
			 cites 13 separate Berber groups currently resident in Algeria, although many of
			 these are very small. By far the most significant are Kabyle, currently spoken
			 by at least 2.5 million people and Chaouia, spoken by 1.4 million. These groups
			 resident in what is now Algeria came under Roman, Vandal and Byzantine
			 influence before the eighth century conquest of the Arabs which profoundly
			 changed the character of the area. Under the influence of the Arabs, Berbers
			 gradually converted to Islam and in the areas of Arabic settlement they
			 intermarried. Berber communities remained relatively distinct in the
			 mountainous areas and these are the areas of strong Berber nationalism today.
			 The Spanish made a number of brief incursions in the fifteenth and sixteenth
			 centuries but they were repelled by Ottoman forces. Algeria became part of the
			 Ottoman empire in the sixteenth century.</p> 
		  <p>The area remained under Ottoman control until it was invaded by the
			 French in 1830. For several decades the French remained relatively concentrated
			 on the coast. From 1830 to 1847 the French fought a series of battles with the
			 charismatic figure Abdel-Kader who galvanised Algerian resistance and remains a
			 significant national hero. After they had put down the final 1871 rebellion,
			 the French government began to promote European settlement more actively and
			 the number of Europeans grew. In 1900, there were 500,000 Europeans living in
			 Algeria and by the end of the Second World War this number had grown to more
			 than a million.<note>Stora, B. [1991] 
				<title>Histoire de l'Algérie coloniale [1830-1954]. La
				  Découverte</title>, Paris.</note> These settlers were known as pieds noirs and
			 took control of the most fertile land. They included not only French but
			 significant groups of Italian and Spanish settlers. As new generations were
			 born and raised away from Europe their own identity evolved, autonomous from
			 Europe and associated very much with North Africa. The French administered
			 Algeria not as a separate colonial territory but as an integral part of France.
			 Uniquely among French colonies, it was subdivided into three
			 <hi>départements</hi>.<note>French colonies were administered in one of three
				ways: first as an Overseas Department [Département Outre Mer, DOM, such as
				Martinique today]; secondly as an Overseas Territory [Territoire Outre Mer,
				TOM, such as New Caledonia today] or thirdly as a Protectorat, [as was the case
				for Morocco and Tunisia]. Algeria was the only exception.</note> The bond
			 between France, Algeria and successive generations of pieds noirs settlers was
			 captured in the notion of l'Algérie Française. The strength of this bond must
			 be appreciated if the tremendous violence of the 1954-62 war, which resulted in
			 Algerian independence, is to be understood.</p> 
		  <p>The first mobilisation for Algerian independence occurred not in
			 Algeria, where the French kept a very tight control over any political
			 developments, but in France. There was a significant Algerian population in
			 France by the 1920s and these emigrants were, and have remained, extremely
			 politically active.<note>Stora, B. [1992] 
				<title>Ils venaient d'Algérie: l'immigration algérienne en France
				  1912-1992</title>. Fayard, Paris.</note> The war of 1954-62 was extremely
			 traumatic for both sides and comparisons have inevitably been made between this
			 and the current conflict. Algeria achieved independence on 5 July 1962, though
			 it is a significant reflection of the symbolic importance of the liberation
			 struggle that the most significant day in the Algerian calendar is not 5 July
			 but the date on which the first shots of the war were fired; 1 November 1954.
			 Mythology and symbolism of the war continues to dominate Algerian political
			 life and throughout the current conflict all sides have claimed to be the true
			 inheritors of the aims of this war.</p><div type="box"><head>The 1954-62
			 war</head> 
		  <p>What is referred to as the war of Algeria in France, and the
			 National War of Liberation or the Revolution in Algeria, is typically called
			 the Algerian war of independence in English. However conceiving of it solely as
			 an independence struggle is to underestimate its significance. Though
			 independence was obviously the aim and one of the results of this war, some may
			 suggest that it has more in common with the ending of apartheid in South
			 Africa; the war marked the end of a period of rule by a minority racial group
			 over the majority of the population. The pieds noirs of Algeria did not
			 consider themselves to be colonisers. Many of them had lived in Algeria for
			 four or five generations and felt Algeria to be their home just as much as the
			 home of the 'Algerian Muslims'. Algeria was declared to be part of France under
			 the Second Republic, in 1848. More than 100 years later, the prime minister
			 famously declared 'Ici, c'est la France' shortly after the opening shots of war
			 on 1 November 1954.<note type="box">Horne, A. [1996] 
				<title>A savage war of peace: Algeria 1954-62</title>. Papermac,
				London.</note></p> 
		  <p>The deep attachment of the pieds noirs to Algeria and the continued
			 conviction that Algeria, unique among colonies, was actually an integral part
			 of France explains why the war lasted eight years and was fought to near
			 destruction on both sides, even after it was clear that empires were coming to
			 an end around the world. Both French and Algerian forces fought extremely
			 brutally with widespread use of torture and extra-judicial killings and the
			 total death toll is generally quoted as 1 million people. This has led some
			 people to compare the current conflict with the previous one,<note type="box">Provost, L. [1996]<title> La seconde guerre d'Algérie. Le quidproquo
				  franco-algérien.</title> Flammarion, Paris.</note> though more recently this
			 has been rejected as obscuring more than it clarifies.<note type="box">Stora,
				B. [2001] 
				<title>La Guerre Invisible Algérie, années 90</title>. Presses de
				Science Po, Paris.</note> The end of the war and the declaration of Algerian
			 independence provoked a tremendous exodus of pieds noirs from Algeria; more
			 than half a million people arrived in Marseilles during a period of three
			 months in the summer of 1962.<note>Sayad, A., Jordi, J. and Temime, E. [1991] 
				<title>Migrance: Histoire des Migrations à Marseille</title> vol.
				4. Edisud, Aix-en-Provence.</note> The intensity of this conflict and the
			 traumatic way in which it ended soured Franco-Algerian relations for many
			 years. President Bouteflika was the first Algerian head of state to make an
			 official visit to France in 2000.</p></div></div><div> 
			 <p>On independence the National Liberation Front [Front de Libération
				Nationale, FLN] formed the government, under the presidency of Ahmed Ben Bella.
				In 1965, Ben Bella was deposed in a coup d'état and an army officer, Houari
				Boumediène, took over the presidency. Boumediène was responsible for shaping
				and directing Algeria for the next 13 years. He was extremely influential in
				forging the institutions of the state and his presidency is viewed with great
				nostalgia by many Algerians as a time of peace and economic prosperity. Under
				Boumediène's leadership, Algeria came to be seen as the leader of the
				non-aligned movement and though it was influenced strongly by socialist
				policies, particularly from 1971 onwards, it did not express allegiance to
				either side during the Cold War.</p> 
			 <p>Boumediène died suddenly in 1978 and Chadli Bendjedid became
				president. In contrast to the 1970s, the 1980s saw growing economic and
				political disturbance, some say as a result of over-reliance on heavy industry
				and under-funding of agriculture during the 1970s.<note>Adamson, K. [1998] 
				  <title>Algeria: a study in competing ideologies</title>.
				  Casswell, London.</note> In early 1980, the long-standing demands for cultural
				recognition from the Berber minority coalesced in the formation of the Berber
				Cultural Movement [Mouvement Culturel Berbère, MCB] and significant protests by
				Berber groups were violently repressed. This became known as the Berber Spring
				and took on a significant symbolic importance in all subsequent Berber
				activism. The Islamist movement also began to grow from the early 1980s, and in
				1985 the Islamist leader Mustapha Bouyali carried out a range of violent
				attacks in the region around Algiers, evading capture [and death] until 1987
				and providing an inspiration to more violent Islamist groups that formed in the
				early 1990s. Serious riots in Algiers and elsewhere in October 1988 promoted
				the president to abandon the one party system focused on the FLN and introduce
				a new constitution legalising the formation of political parties in 1989 with
				the aim of gradually implementing a more democratic system. This provided the
				trigger for the conflict from which Algeria has still not fully
				emerged.</p></div><div><head>The Algerian conflict and the resulting
			 emigration</head><div><head>Chronology of events </head> 
		  <p>Since 1992, more than 120,000 people have been killed,<note>Most
				historical sources cited here published from the mid-1990s onwards refer to 'at
				least 100,000', and this was confirmed by President Bouteflika on his election
				in 1999 [see Amnesty reports]. It is now reckoned to be even higher. This
				figure is an estimate based on Algerian newspaper reports.</note> tens of
			 thousands have left the country [estimates range as high as 450,000<note>The 
				<xref url="http://www.refugees.org/world/countryrpt/africa/2002/algeria.cfm">US
				  Committee for Refugees 2002</xref> report on Algeria refers to 'hundreds of
				thousands'. Ghiles, F. [1998] 'L'armée a-t-elle une politique économique:
				chronique de douze années de compromis incertains.' 
				<title>Pouvoirs</title> 86 pp. 85-106, and Ait Amara, H., J.
				Gallot, B. Mediene and P. Sindic [2000] 
				<title>Algérie, débats pour un issue: Assises pour un nouveau
				  partenariat Algérie, France, Europe - Marseille 27-28 novembre 1998</title>;
				Publisud, Paris, cite figures of between 200,000 and 450,000 managers and
				professional people who have left Algeria during this time, though the source
				of these statistics is not clear.</note>] and an estimated 200,000 people have
			 been internally displaced.<note>The<xref url="http://www.db.idpproject.org/Sites/IdpProjectDb/idpSurvey.nsf/wCountries/Algeria">
				  Global IDP project Algeria</xref> page.</note> The origins of this conflict can
			 be traced back to at least the mid-1980s. Austerity measures, introduced by
			 Chadli from the early 1980s to establish the foundation of a market economy,
			 resulted in growing inequality and withdrawal of public services. This offended
			 the egalitarian aspirations of the Algerian people and was a key factor
			 provoking the riots around the country in October 1988. The introduction of a
			 new political system in 1989 did not fully address the rioters' concerns and in
			 the absence of an effective state response, before or since the riots, popular
			 discontent was mobilised and partially addressed by Islamic groups who provided
			 considerable social assistance. </p> 
		  <p>The new 1989 constitution legalised political parties and a total of
			 60 were formed. These included the Islamic Salvation Front [Front Islamique du
			 Salut, FIS], formed of a disparate collection of religious groups, which
			 quickly mobilised millions of supporters<note>Addi, L. [1996] 'Réflexion
				politique sur la tragédie algérienne' 
				<title>Confluences</title> 20 pp. 43-51.</note> and produced an
			 effective 'challenge' to the regime.<note>Willis, M. [1996] 
				<title>The Islamist Challenge in Algeria. Ithaca Press</title>,
				Reading.</note> The FIS won the local elections of June 1990 very convincingly.
			 The situation became more turbulent during the course of 1991 with a string of
			 provocative statements from the leaders of the FIS that resulted in their
			 arrest. The party nonetheless contested the general elections in December 1991
			 in which they again achieved a large majority. They looked set to take control
			 of the National Assembly but the army cancelled the second round of the general
			 elections in January 1992.</p>
		  <p>The situation deteriorated rapidly after the cancellation of the
			 elections. President Chadli resigned and a state of emergency was introduced on
			 9 February 1992 that remains in force. The FIS was declared illegal in March
			 1992. Mohammed Boudiaf, a respected veteran of the 1954-62 war was appointed by
			 the army to lead the new Council of State. Under Boudiaf's orders as many as
			 10,000 Islamist supporters were detained in huge camps in the desert. Boudiaf's
			 assassination in June 1992 confirmed the severity of the situation and
			 destroyed many people's hopes that the crisis would be over quickly. Liamine
			 Zeroual was immediately appointed to replace Boudiaf. Detainees from the camps
			 were progressively released from the summer of 1992 onwards.</p> 
		  <p>The camps had actually provided an opportunity for networks to
			 become established between Islamist activists and many left the camps to join
			 existing armed groups or found others. These armed groups were not well
			 directed or organised<note>Some commentators have identified as many as seven
				separate strands of organisation, each with different methods and goals,
				Khelassi, N. [1998] 'La Violence' 
				<title>Pouvoirs</title> 86, pp. 107-116. The most notorious of
				these is undoubtedly the Groupe Islamique Armée [GIA] who have claimed
				responsiblity for the majority of attacks on civilians.</note> but the
			 government was neither prepared nor the army trained for dealing with this kind
			 of enemy. From 1993 onwards certain armed groups began a policy of individual
			 assassination, frequently targeting prominent intellectuals, journalists,
			 artists or doctors; during May 1993 alone 200 individuals were
			 assassinated.<note>Reporteurs Sans Frontiers [1994] 
				<title>Le Drame Algerien: un peuple en otage</title>. La
				Decouverte, Paris.</note> During 1994, large areas of the country were under
			 the de facto control of the armed groups and there were suggestions that the
			 government could lose control entirely.<note><title>Le Monde</title>
				16.9.94.</note></p>
		  <p>In 1994 France stepped in to help the government and arranged or
			 provided more than US$6 billion of assistance, much of it in the form of
			 military hardware.<note>Leveau, R. [1994] 'Algerie: les pièges de l'aide
				internationale' 
				<title>Politique internationale</title> 65 automne, pp.
				171-192.</note> New presidential elections were held in 1995 confirming Liamine
			 Zeroual as the new president. The elections were welcomed and Zeroual's
			 policies, backed up with substantial French support, were greeted as the
			 beginning of the end of the conflict. He introduced a policy of clemency,
			 involving partial pardons for members of armed groups and initially there were
			 signs that this was successful. By 1997, hopes that the end of the conflict was
			 near were again destroyed as killings of individuals gradually escalated to a
			 series of terrible massacres of tens and later hundreds of people. </p> 
		  <p>In August and September 1997, hundreds of civilians were killed in
			 the villages of Bentalha, Rais and Beni Messous, near Algiers and by the end of
			 the year, the remote mountainous area of Relizane was targeted. These events
			 terrified the local population and provoked huge internal population movements;
			 some spoke of an 'exodus' from the area near Algiers, the
			 <hi>Mitidja</hi>.<note>Stora, B. [2001] 
				<title>La Guerre Invisible Algérie, années 90</title>. Presses de
				Science Po, Paris.</note> The Groupe Islamique Armeé [Armed Islamic Group, GIA]
			 later claimed responsibility for these massacres, though a series of high
			 profile accounts in the press, and later in books, questioned the role of the
			 army. Few serious commentators support the notion that the army actually
			 committed these massacres, though this is the essence of some of the
			 accusations, but the published accounts at least raise the question of why the
			 government did so little to prevent them occurring.</p>
		  <p>In 1999, the election of President Bouteflika was again seen as
			 heralding a real change in the war as he outlined a number of bold initiatives
			 to bring an end to the violence. Over time it became clear that these ideas
			 were being blocked due to conflict within the administration, and the hopes
			 incited by his election have faded. By 2001 violent attacks were again
			 increasing, and from April onwards a series of protests to mark the 21st
			 anniversary of the Berber Spring were again violently repressed by the police,
			 resulting in the death of at least 60 people and exacerbating the alienation
			 felt by the Berber minority. At present the situation seems deadlocked. There
			 is no possibility that the government will be overturned, as seemed possible in
			 1994, but the ongoing violence will prove difficult to stop completely without
			 more genuine reforms of the political system.</p></div><div type="box"><head>Linking fluctuating numbers of asylum seekers and developing
			 events in Algeria</head> 
		  <p>Empirically it seems that the overall numbers of Algerians
			 requesting asylum relates far more closely to events in Algeria than to any
			 developments in asylum policy in the receiving states. The graph separates
			 requests made in Germany from all other applications since in the early years
			 of conflict Germany was by far the most significant destination for Algerian
			 asylum seekers.</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <figure url="c001"> 
			 </figure></p> 
		  <p><hi rend="bold">The total number of Algerian asylum seekers [above]
			 related to events in Algeria [below]</hi></p> 
		  <table> 
			 <row><cell>2001</cell><cell>Attacks in Kabylia</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>2000</cell><cell>Violence escalates</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1999</cell><cell>Bouteflika elected</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1998</cell><cell>Massacres spread</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1997</cell><cell>Massacres in Algiers area</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1996</cell><cell></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1995</cell><cell>Zeroual elected; new constitution; policy
				  of 'clemency'</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1994</cell> 
				<cell>Significant French military aid begins</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1993</cell><cell>Assassinations of prominent
				  intellectuals</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1992</cell><cell>Elections cancelled; FIS declared
				  illegal; Boudiaf assassinated</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1991</cell><cell></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1990</cell><cell>FIS win local elections</cell> 
			 </row> 
		  </table> 
		  <p>Even in 1990 the number of Algerian asylum seekers was not
			 inconsiderable reflecting the continued concern resulting from the 1988 riots.
			 The deteriorating situation provoked by the cancellation of the elections in
			 1992 forced many more people to leave. This initial movement of asylum seekers
			 included moderate Islamist politicians who left once their membership of the
			 FIS was criminalised and was directed significantly to Germany. Germany's use
			 of the authorisation principle [see legal issues section] meant that they were
			 far more likely to recognise refugees fleeing the government [therefore
			 Islamists] than refugees fleeing armed groups.</p> 
		  <p>The second movement of refugees from Algeria fled as a result of the
			 assassinations of intellectuals. This group was very different from the first.
			 Both groups of refugees left during 1993 producing the peak of asylum requests
			 during this year. In 1994, although the overall requests fell due to the
			 dramatic fall in Germany, the numbers of asylum applicants in all other states
			 continued to rise considerably as the violence in Algeria escalated. Zeroul's
			 election as president in 1995 was greeted with widespread optimism, reflected
			 in the graph of asylum requests with the dramatic fall in 1996. The wave of
			 massacres in 1997 in villages on the outskirts of Algiers shocked the country
			 and forced more people into exile. By the end of the year, the massacres
			 extended to the more remote mountain area of Relizane, again affecting the
			 profile of people leaving the area, and eventually the country, and explaining
			 the continued growth in asylum numbers in 1998.</p> 
		  <p>The election of Bouteflika was again greeted as a promising sign and
			 asylum applications fell slightly but it was soon clear that this optimism was
			 misplaced. Renewed violence in 2000 was marked by a further increase in
			 applications in 2001, and following the disturbances in Kabylia in 2001, there
			 was another change in profile to include a growing number of refugees from the
			 Berberregions.</p> 
		  </div><div> 
			 <p>The unfolding of these events can usefully be related to changes
				in the numbers of asylum seekers from Algeria [see above]. There have been at
				least five distinct movements of people out of Algeria relating to the
				unfolding of events over the last decade and each group has a different profile
				and different needs. These groups consist of moderate Islamists from 1992
				onwards, typically from areas that were previously FIS controlled such as
				around Oran; intellectuals and artists from 1993 onwards, mostly from the
				capital; army deserters from 1994; more remote rural residents from 1997; and
				more recently, since the events in Kabylia of 2001, a greater number of Berber
				migrants. Individuals have left Algeria due to both individual and generalised
				threats. An individual who had been regularly warned by armed groups during
				1993 and 1994 and eventually left, described how he lived with the knowledge
				that he was a constant target:</p> 
			 <q rend="block">It's not the fear of a day, or a week, of an event, a
				movement, an insurrection that only lasts a day, it really goes on. And you
				don't know how to live with it, how to be vigilant, how to preserve yourself
				because a bomb can explode at any time, they can come to your house, they can
				kill you in the street, on your way to work, they can kill you, and your
				children.</q> 
			 <p>However, a much greater number of people have been given refugee
				status due to their fear of the government, and many refugees in Europe face a
				death threat in Algeria even though their activities have been considered to be
				political by European courts. There has also been a much larger movement of
				people who have great difficulty demonstrating the individual persecution that
				is required for them to receive refugee status and who, in some cases, have no
				interest in receiving refugee status. However, even for those individuals who
				have not been individually targeted by either side in the conflict, the
				generalised state of violence that has prevailed in many parts of Algeria for
				the last decade is likely to have been the most significant factor in their
				decision to leave. A young student described the sort of occurrence that was
				relatively widespread, at least in the region around Algiers, for much of the
				1990s:</p><q rend="block">To go to the university there are two buses and one
				day I took the first bus. We heard a huge explosion behind us, it was the
				second bus that had blown up. The windows of the bus had all smashed. We saw
				these people run towards us, some of them wounded, but we couldn't move. There
				were twenty or so dead and a lot of injured. I'll never forget it, when you see
				that you think "and if that was me, in the second bus…if I'd been a bit slower
				this morning.</q></div><div><head>Explaining the conflict</head> 
		  <p>Even the most basic facts of the current conflict in Algeria are
			 contested. The initial controversy centred on the army's motives for canceling
			 the 1992 elections. The army argued that it was acting to protect the
			 democratic process from a party that did not respect democracy.<note>Taheri, A.
				[1998] 'Entretien avec le général X: Algérie: Les grands cimeterres sous la
				lune.' 
				<title>Politique Internationale</title> 79, pp. 11-32.</note>
			 Others refer to a coup d'etat and see the cancellation of the election as the
			 result of the efforts of a particular section of the political elite to cling
			 to power.<note>Addi, L. [1999] 'L'armée, la nation et l'Etat en Algérie' 
				<title>Confluences</title> 29, pp. 39-47.</note> The controversy
			 surrounding the role of the Algerian government in the conflict has continued
			 ever since with a range of accusations of army involvement in killing
			 civilians, particularly in the massacres of 1997 and 1998. There can be no
			 doubt that the government has been complicit in a series of human rights
			 abuses<note>Criticisms of the Algerian government, human rights record are
				extensively documented in a range of reports from 
				<xref url="http://web.amnesty.org/ai.nsf/countries/algeria?OpenView&amp;Start=1&amp;Count=30&amp;Expandall&amp;ft=S">Amnesty
				  International</xref> and 
				<xref url="http://www.hrw.org/mideast/algeria.php">Human Rights
				  Watch</xref> and are raised in two 
				<xref url="http://www.un.org/french/newlinks/dpi2007/part5.htm">UN
				  reports on Algeria</xref> in 1998.</note> but some observers argue that this is
			 an inevitable consequence of the 'transition to democracy' that began in
			 1989.<note>Djerbal, D. [1998] 'Algérie: La Communauté Internationale et les
				Droits de l'Homme: Entre Soverainété et Droit d'Ingerence.' 
				<title>Monde Arabe Maghreb Machrek</title> 162 pp. 119-124.</note>
			 The suggestion that the army actively took part in massacres of civilians is
			 obviously a far more serious charge. It was first raised in books by a survivor
			 from one of the massacres<note>Yous, N. [2000] 
				<title>Qui a tué à Bentalha? Chronique d'un massacre
				  annoncé</title>. La Decouverte, Paris.</note> and later by an army
			 officer<note>Souaidia, H. [2001] 
				<title>La Sale Guerre</title>. La Découverte, Paris.</note> and,
			 though some commentators have found no further evidence to support their
			 claims,<note>Stora, B. [2001] 
				<title>La Guerre Invisible Algérie, années 90</title>, Presses de
				Science Po, Paris.</note> others argue that they still cast serious doubt on
			 the issue and the army must at least answer the charge of why it failed to
			 intervene in these massacres.<note>Roberts, H. [2003] 
				<title>Algeria the battlefield 1998-2002: studies in a broken
				  polity</title>. Verso, London.</note></p> 
		  <p>The government maintains increasingly stringent controls on
			 information so it is often difficult to follow the twists and turns of events
			 in Algeria and more difficult to understand the power struggles behind them.
			 This has encouraged the growth of independent sources of information,
			 frequently produced by emigrants and diffused through the internet [see below].
			 As with the 1954-62 conflict, it is likely that the 'facts' behind the events
			 of this conflict will take many decades to surface.</p></div></div> 
		  <div type="box"><head>Algeria on the web</head> 
		  <p>There is now a huge range of websites devoted to Algerian issues.
			 These range from official sites of Algerian national newspapers,<note>See 
				<xref url="http://www.arabji.com/algeria/Media.htm">http://www.arabji.com/algeria/Media.htm</xref>
				for a full list of Algerian newspapers available on the internet.</note>
			 government departments<note>See the 
				<xref url="http://www.ons.dz/index.htm">National Statistic
				  Office</xref>.</note> and 
			 <xref url="http://www.consalglond.u-net.com/Embassy.htm">embassies</xref>, political
			 parties,<note>See the 
				<xref url="http://www.rcd-algerie.org/">RCD</xref>.</note> pressure
			 groups of many kinds, solidarity or development organisations,<note>See 
				<xref url="http://www.algeriensdumonde.org/">Algériens du
				  Monde</xref>.</note> cultural pages,<note><xref url="http://www.algeriades.com/news/sommaire.php3">Algeriades</xref> or 
				<xref url="http://www.planet-dz.com/">Planet DZ</xref>.</note>
			 economic advice columns,<note>Such as 
				<xref url="http://www.algeriafocus.com/">Algeria
				  Focus</xref>.</note> 
			 <xref url="http://www.arabji.com/algeria/">directories</xref> and
			 bulletin boards encouraging discussion on a wide range of subjects. Many of
			 these are produced by and/or for the emigrant community.<note>Collyer, M.
				[2003] 'Are there national borders in cyberspace? Evidence from the Algerian
				transnational community' 
				<title>Geography</title> [forthcoming].</note> Algeria is obviously
			 not exceptional in this. What is, perhaps, more unusual is the high level of
			 control that the government maintains over national and international media and
			 the low level of confidence in official explanations felt by many Algerians.
			 This combination of factors has produced a huge range of alternative
			 information sources on the internet concerning the history of the current
			 conflict and offering a range of explanations.</p> 
		  <p><xref url="http://www.algeria-interface.com/">Algeria
				Interface</xref> [in English and French] offers a wealth of detail and extracts
			 of local Algerian newspapers and official reports with little apparent
			 selectivity of coverage. The site of 
			 <xref url="http://www.algeria-watch.org/francais.htm">Algeria
				Watch</xref> [in French and German] is also extremely comprehensive and
			 regularly updated. One of the journalists on Algerian Watch co-wrote Nesroulah
			 Yous' polemic account of the massacre at Bentalha and Algeria Watch has paid
			 particular attention to these debates. This degree of focus on the issue of
			 'who is really killing?', which is unlikely to ever be effectively proved or
			 disproved, led Paul Silverstein to comment on the prevalence of conspiracy
			 theories in these transnational fora.<note>Silverstein, P.A. [2000] 'Regimes of
				[un]truth: conspiracy theory and the transnationalization of the Algerian civil
				war' 
				<title>Middle East Report </title>214, pp. 6-10.</note> The
			 question of responsibility for the massacres perhaps receives more attention
			 than any other issue. Sites such as 
			 <xref url="http://www.pourinfo.ouvaton.org/go.htm">POUR!</xref> are
			 devoted to undermining suggestions that the army is responsible for the
			 massacres since its authors feel that this removes guilt from the Islamist
			 groups where they feel the real danger lies. POUR! has a long, comprehensive
			 dossier of evidence of Islamist activity in France. Their links are also
			 strongly critical of the Algerian government and they produce an extensive
			 almost daily round up of news on Algerian issues.</p> 
		  <p>The 
			 <xref url="http://www.anp.org/">Mouvement Algérien des Officiers
				Libres</xref> [MAOL] is another interesting and controversial organisation,
			 made up of dissident officers from the Algerian army. Their website [in Arabic,
			 French and English] focuses on publishing detailed reports on the activities of
			 the most important generals in government. POUR! has linked MAOL with Islamist
			 groups,<note>POUR! letter 29 [2000].</note> but MAOL challenge this evidence
			 and maintain their independence from political parties.<note>See the French 
				<title>Libération</title> 17.5.01.</note> Avowed Islamist sites
			 have also been keen to publicise any information that will discredit the
			 government, and both the 
			 <xref url="http://www.fis-info.net/index.php">FIS</xref> [in English,
			 French and Arabic] and the Islamic focused site 
			 <xref url="http://home.worldcom.ch/~hijra/">Hijra</xref><note>Hijra
				means migration in Arabic and has strong religious connotations. This site has
				not been updated for some time.</note> [in French and Arabic] have covered
			 details of the accusations against the government. Finally the Berber minority
			 also has a very significant community across the world. A number of these sites
			 are focused on Berber issues generally but 
			 <xref url="http://www.kabyle.com/">Kabyle.com</xref> [in English,
			 French and Tamazityt] presents an Algerian focused view of Berber
			 issues.</p></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_03"> 
		  <body><head>Profile of the Algerian population in UK</head><div> 
			 <p>This section turns to the Algerian population in the UK,
				presenting an overall profile. It is unfortunately only a partial picture as
				there has been very little research on the Algerian population in the UK. The
				total number of Algerians present in the UK is currently estimated at between
				25,000 and 30,000 people. Even the most significant study that exists only
				interviewed 30 individuals<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in
				  established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK'
				  University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British Library.
				  A summary of this research will soon be available online as Collyer, M. [2003]
				  'Explaining change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians
				  to France and the UK' 
				  <xref url="http://www.sussex.ac.uk/Units/SCMR/working_papers/">Sussex Migration
					 Working Paper 15</xref>, Sussex Centre for Migration Research, Brighton.</note>
				and other studies focused on Algerians have spoken to even fewer
				people.<note>Rocheron, Y. [2002] 'Paradoxes of Hijrah [Exile]: Tales from
				  Algerian Men in Britain' in S. Ouditt ed. 
				  <title>Displaced persons: Conditions of exile in European
					 culture</title>. Ashgate, Aldershot.</note> Algerians figure in more general
				work but typically in even fewer numbers.<note>Nagel, C. [2001] 'Hidden
				  minorities and the politics of 'race': the case of British Arab activists in
				  London' 
				  <title>Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies</title> 27.</note>
				Refugee support groups and other NGOs are of course in touch with many more
				individuals but few keep detailed records of their client group, and some do
				not even record the nationality of their clients.</p>
			 <p>Even where records exist, these are not much larger than the
				studies undertaken; the largest data source the author was able to consult
				recorded only nationality, gender and qualifications for 242 individuals. The
				information that follows is based on the small pool of research that exists,
				material gleaned from broader studies of the UK population, information
				obtained from NGOs and interviews with service providers, lawyers, NGO workers,
				refugee community organisations and key members of the Algerian
				community.<note>The bulk of this formed part of the author's DPhil research,
				  although a number of organisations and individuals were contacted as part of
				  the research for this guide in January and February 2003 to confirm that the
				  issues are still relevant.</note> It is by no means a complete picture, and may
				contain considerable inaccuracies, but can be considered the most accurate
				profile that is currently available.</p></div><div><head>Gender</head> 
		  <p>Available evidence suggests that the Algerian population in the UK
			 is overwhelmingly male.</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Of those recorded as being born in Algeria by the 1991 census,
				70% were male.</item> 
			 <item>Support services and lawyers in London working with Algerians
				reported that the Algerian client group was comprised of between zero and eight
				per cent women.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established
				  migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK' University
				  of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British
				  Library.</note></item> 
		  </list> 
		  <p>Possible explanations may be that:</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Algerian women are present in larger numbers but do not use
				services;</item> 
			 <item>Algerian women are more likely to live with relatives and since
				Algerians are concentrated in France their family is more likely to be located
				there;</item> 
			 <item>the UK is generally reached by undocumented migration and women
				are less prepared to resort to undocumented migration than men.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Ethnic background</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Algerians are mainly Arabs but there is a significant Berber
				presence [approximately 10% of the population in Algeria]. Although Berbers
				fall into a number of distinct sub-groups [the four most significant are
				Kabyle, Choauia, Toureg and Mozabite], they are typically categorised as a
				single ethnic minority in Algeria.</item> 
			 <item>Berbers, particularly Kabyles, are over represented within the
				Algerian community in France [approximately 20% of Algerians in France are of
				Berber origin].</item> 
			 <item>There is also a significant Berber presence in the UK, though
				the exact proportion is unknown. 
				<list> 
				  <item>The Member of the Algerian National Assembly representing
					 emigrants in Northern Europe elected in 1997 is a member of the RCD
					 [Rassemblement pour la Culture et la Democratie], a party with a strong Berber
					 constituency.</item> 
				  <item>There was a small but significant protest in Trafalgar
					 Square, London, against the violence of the police in the Berber region of
					 Kabylia in 2001.</item> 
				  <item>However, no services reported receiving a large number of
					 Berber clients and they are likely to remain a minority<note>Collyer, M. [2002]
						'Explaining change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians
						to France and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at
						the British Library.</note> within the wider Algerian population.</item> 
				</list></item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Languages spoken</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>The nationally recognised languages in Algeria are Arabic and,
				since 2002, the Berber language Tamaziyt; which of them is spoken will depend
				on ethnic background. The Arabic spoken is an Algerian dialect that is
				different from standard Arabic. </item> 
			 <item>Any Algerian educated to secondary level will also speak some
				French.</item> 
			 <item>English is growing in popularity and becoming more widely
				spoken, especially among those educated to a higher level.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Religion</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Islam is one of the founding principles of the Algerian state
				and the official religion of Algeria. The majority of Algerians are Sunnis and
				the Malki judicial school is the most common. South Asian Muslims, the most
				significant Muslim group in Britain, are Sunni and typically from the Hanafi
				judicial school, which is considered by Malkis to be far less conservative.
				There is no barrier between judicial schools and Algerians worship in a whole
				range of mosques in the UK.</item> 
			 <item>Though Algeria is far from being an Islamic state, as Islamic
				law [shari'a] is not in force, there is a strong Islamic influence on private
				or family law. The Code de la Famille [Family Code], introduced in 1984 and
				still in force, clearly relates to shari'a and is strongly opposed by feminist
				groups.</item> 
			 <item>Many Algerian Islamist groups and political parties draw their
				influence most strongly from groups such as the Muslim Brotherhood, founded in
				Egypt in 1928.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Age</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>A wide diversity of ages is represented, though there are many
				more young people.</item> 
			 <item>Those who have arrived since 1992 are much younger. This is
				unsurprising since 75% of the Algerian population is now under the age of
				30.</item> 
			 <item>Algerians who have been in the UK for longer are considerably
				older but much fewer in number.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Academic qualifications</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>The small number of Algerians who arrived in the 1970s and
				1980s are very highly qualified, in contrast to the more working class
				migration to France during this period.</item> 
			 <item>Studies suggest that Algerian emigrants since 1990 have
				generally been very well qualified, and that those with degree level education
				are over-represented compared to the UK population and compared to those who
				remained in Algeria.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established
				  migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK' University
				  of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British Library; Rocheron,
				  Y. [2002] 'Paradoxes of Hijrah [Exile]: Tales from Algerian Men in Britain' in
				  S. Ouditt ed. 
				  <title>Displaced persons: Conditions of exile in European
					 culture</title>. Ashgate, Aldershot.</note></item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Profession</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>The large proportion of the Algerian population who are
				undocumented means that the majority are working well below their high level of
				qualification.</item> 
			 <item>Even those with documented status are frequently working in
				unskilled jobs. This is particularly the case with doctors who are considered
				sufficiently qualified to work in France without retraining but stand little
				chance of passing the strict language requirements for recognition in the
				UK.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Length of residence</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Those individuals born in Algeria who were present for the 1991
				census now make up approximately 10% of the Algerian population in
				Britain.</item> 
			 <item>The large majority of Algerians have therefore arrived within
				the last 10 years. It is likely that this will be skewed even more to the last
				five years since Algerians did not begin to request asylum in significant
				numbers until 1995.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Political affiliation</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Those Algerians in Britain who voted in the 1997 Algerian
				general elections formed part of the section of the emigrant community
				[Northern Europe] who voted a member of the RCD to represent them at the
				National Assembly. The RCD is a strongly anti-Islamist, Berber party.
				Unfortunately the vote is not broken down further so this provides only an
				indication of the political affiliations of Algerians resident in
				Britain.</item> 
			 <item>One of the six members of the moderate wing of the Front de
				Libération Nationale [FIS], Djaffar Al Houari, is based in London. His role is
				to represent the FIS to the International Arab press based in London, not to
				organise the community politically.</item> 
			 <item>There is some evidence of a more extremist position, such as
				the organisation 'The Algerian Community of Great Britain', who were active in
				1994 and 1995 but have apparently disappeared.<note>This group distributed
				  leaflets in London in 1994 and published a summary of news reports on Algeria
				  in 1995 but have had no public profile since. Anecdotal evidence [see Collyer,
				  M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established migration systems: the movement of
				  Algerians to France and the UK' University of Sussex] suggests that a number of
				  them left for Afghanistan in 1996 or 1997.</note></item> 
			 <item>There is some evidence that younger Algerians develop political
				interests,<note>Denaud, P. [1997] 
				  <title>Le FIS : Sa direction parle…</title> Harmattan,
				  Paris.</note> but research suggests that this may be a minority position in the
				UK.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established migration
				  systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK' University of Sussex,
				  DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British Library.</note> Younger
				Algerians, who have now experienced war in Algeria for more than half of their
				lives are most often deliberately apolitical, rejecting all sides in the
				conflict.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established migration
				  systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK' University of Sussex,
				  DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British Library.</note></item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Geographic distribution</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Algerians are overwhelmingly concentrated in London.</item> 
			 <item>Within London there are concentrations around Finsbury Park,
				where the Algerian Refugee Council is located and in Waltham Forest where the
				Algerian Welfare Association is based.</item> 
			 <item>Dispersal statistics collated at the end of January 2003 showed
				that the largest numbers of Algerian asylum seekers in dispersal accommodation
				were based in Glasgow, Sheffield, Birmingham and Manchester. Outside London, it
				has also been suggested that there are also significant Algerian communities in
				Bournemouth and Leicester partly due to the government's policy of dispersing
				asylum seekers to particular locations but also due to the development of
				social networks. </item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Other characteristics</head> 
		  <p>The Algerian community in the UK has a growing reputation as an
			 artistic community. There are certainly a large number of singers, poets and
			 artists for a relatively small population. This may be attributed to the
			 profile of emigrants during the 1990s. These migrants may be more likely to be
			 interested in artistic pursuits due to the circumstances of their flight from
			 Algeria [see historical context on the flight of intellectuals and the cultural
			 background section on targeting of writers and musicians].</p></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_04"> 
		  <body><head>Legal issues</head> 
		  <p>The most significant legal issues affecting Algerians' journey to
			 and residence in Britain relate to visa restrictions, asylum applications and
			 detention.</p><div><head>Visa restrictions</head> 
		  <p>Visas for Algerians were introduced later than for other
			 asylum-seeking nationalities, but restrictions have been and remain tight.</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Algerians were required to hold a visa for the UK from March
				1989.<note>Personal communication with Mr Yamba, Pro-Consul, British Embassy,
				  Algiers.</note></item> 
			 <item>Since 
				<xref url="http://www.ind.homeoffice.gov.uk/news.asp?NewsId=273&amp;SectionId=1">May
				  2003</xref>, Algerians have needed a transit visa to pass through any British
				airport.</item> 
		  </list> 
		  <p>There is general agreement amongst the Algerian population and
			 service providers that it is extremely difficult to get a visa to come to the
			 UK. A 29-year old man commented:</p> 
		  <q rend="block">If you want to make a list of all the countries to get
			 a visa, Britain comes at the top. It is the most difficult. The US is maybe
			 fifth or sixth. France is tenth, its easy to get a visa for France, but
			 Britain! It's easier to get a visa for Paradise than for Britain!</q> 
		  <p>Throughout much of the conflict in Algeria, British visas were not
			 available in Algeria. In 1994, the visa section of the British embassy in
			 Algiers closed and all applications had to be submitted to the British
			 embassies in Tunis or Paris. A 35 year-old man who spoke excellent English and
			 was employed in well paid, full-time work in Algiers described his experiences
			 at the British embassy in Tunis:</p> 
		  <q>I stayed the night in Tunis. There were only a few people in front
			 of me in the queue, at seven in the morning. I was told that in 1995 there were
			 huge queues from very early in the morning, but now people know there's no
			 point. They told me 'I'm sorry, we can't give you a visa until your country is
			 safe again'. They didn't give me any more information than that. […] It's very
			 expensive and you have to pay even if you're not successful.</q> 
		  <p>This was the end of 1997, when the shocking massacres very near this
			 man's house were front-page news around the world. The story he relates, if
			 accurate, illustrates the difficulty of obtaining a visa, even for someone in
			 his privileged position at an extremely dangerous time.</p> 
		  <p>The visa section in the British embassy in Algiers remained closed
			 until the summer of 2002. In research studies undertaken with the Algerian
			 population, this difficulty of obtaining a visa for the UK was frequently given
			 as the reason for undocumented entry.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining
				change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France
				and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the
				British Library.</note></p></div><div><head>Asylum</head> 
		  <p>In the past, Algerians could emigrate easily but since the
			 introduction of visa restrictions, asylum is now one of the only options for
			 those wishing to migrate. The ongoing conflict in Algeria has produced a
			 significant emigration of refugees and more Algerians request asylum in Europe
			 than enter Europe for any other reason.</p> 
		  <p>The results of claims registered by Algerians have fluctuated
			 considerably in the UK. Asylum claims from Algerians were especially successful
			 in 1998 and 1999 but in the early 1990s and since 1999, Algerians have been
			 less likely to be granted asylum than all nationalities taken
			 together.<note>Based on the number of Algerians who were granted asylum [after
				the first decision and on appeal] as a percentage of all Algerians who
				requested asylum, compared with the same indicator for all
				nationalities.</note> From 1990 onwards, Algerians have also been far less
			 likely to receive Exceptional Leave to Remain [ELR] than the average for all
			 nationalities combined.<note>All based on Home Office statistics.</note></p> 
		  <p>Several observations have been advanced to suggest that asylum
			 policy does not impact positively on Algerians' decisions to choose the UK as
			 an asylum destination.</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>In common with most asylum seekers in the UK, Algerians have
				very little information on the asylum system before they arrive. Even those
				interviewed in the Red Cross Centre at Sangatte could give no precise
				information on the British asylum system.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining
				  change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France
				  and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the
				  British Library.</note></item> 
			 <item>The rise in the number of Algerian asylum seekers in certain
				years does not correspond to the years when they were most likely to receive
				asylum, suggesting that the likelihood of receiving a positive decision on
				their claim was not a factor.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in
				  established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK'
				  University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British
				  Library.</note></item> 
			 <item>Despite the fact that the interpretation of the issue of agents
				of persecution in the British courts is favourable to Algerians [see box 1],
				the UK still does not receive large numbers of Algerian asylum seekers.</item> 
		  </list> 
		  <div type="box"><head>Agents of persecution</head> 
		  <p>Article 1A[2] of the 1951 Geneva Convention on the Status of
			 Refugees defines who is a refugee. One of the essential elements in this
			 definition is 'a well founded fear of being persecuted'. The Geneva Convention
			 is not specific as to the source of this persecution but it is generally
			 accepted that it may arise under three sets of circumstances.<note>Creach, X.
				and Schreiner. C. [1996] 'Regards sur la Jurisprudence Française en matière
				d'agents de persécution' 
				<title>Migrations Société</title> 8[48], pp. 45-56.</note></p> 
		  <list type="ordered" rend="lower-roman"> 
			 <item>the persecution is derived from the state</item> 
			 <item>the persecution is derived from an agent other than the state
				but the state encourages or tolerates this persecution</item> 
			 <item> the persecution is derived from an agent other than the state
				but the state is powerless to offer any protection</item> 
		  </list> 
		  <p>Situations [i] and [ii] are uncontroversial and asylum is usually
			 granted. Controversy arises in the third case and there is disagreement between
			 European judicial systems over whether the third case counts as persecution or
			 not. Any Algerian fleeing persecution from an armed group will fall into this
			 category since this persecution is occurring because the government is
			 powerless to prevent it. The French and German judicial systems both argue that
			 type [iii] is not persecution and have rejected a great many asylum claims from
			 Algerians as a result. The Franco-German position is referred to as the
			 'authorisation principle' since the state must authorise the persecution. This
			 interpretation has been criticised as incorrect by a range of
			 NGOs,<note>Cimade, LDH, MRAP [1997], 'Les lois en discussion sur la
				nationalite, l'entrée et le sejour des etrangers' Confluences no.24 pp. 121-127
				; USCR [1999] 
				<title>Gross Negligence Dressed up in Legalese: restrictive
				  interpretations on 'Agents of Persecution' and their impact on Algerian asylum
				  seekers in Germany and France</title>, US Committee for Refugees,
				Washington.</note> the UNHCR<note>UNHCR [1995] 
				<title>Lignes directrices du HCR concernant l'éligibilité au statut
				  des demandeurs d'asile algériens.</title> UNHCR, Geneva.</note> and a number of
			 lawyers.<note>Creach, X. and Schreiner. C. [1996] 'Regards sur la Jurisprudence
				Française en matière d'agents de persécution' 
				<title>Migrations Société</title> 8[48], pp. 45-56.</note> The
			 British system does not apply the authorisation principle and so tends to
			 recognise Algerians fleeing persecution from 'non-state agents'. </p> 
		  <p>One of the most famous cases and an important test case for this
			 principle is Aitsegeur, an Algerian man who had entered Britain from France and
			 claimed asylum. The Secretary of State had ruled that he should be returned to
			 France under the Dublin Convention [see below] but the House of Lords
			 disagreed, arguing that due to the likelihood of him being returned to Algeria
			 from France, France, effectively, was not a safe country and he should
			 remain.<note>R. v. Sec of State ex parte Adan and Aitsegeur House of Lords
				[2000].</note> This case reveals the difficulty of harmonising asylum law in
			 Europe, as well as the precarious nature of the position of many Algerian
			 asylum seekers.</p> 
		  <list> 
		  </list></div></div><div> 
			 <p>Due to the difficulty of obtaining a visa to get to the UK,
				Algerian asylum seekers typically arrive without documents directly from
				France. Under the Dublin Convention, Algerian asylum seekers arriving in this
				way would normally be sent back directly. Important legal precedents have been
				established to prevent this occurring but it is possible that now that Dublin
				II has been approved these will be over ruled.</p><div type="box"><head>The
			 Dublin Convention</head> 
		  <p>The Dublin Convention was signed between member states of the
			 European Union in 1990 and finally came into force in September 1997. It sets
			 out to determine which member state is responsible for assessing an asylum
			 claim. The Convention was widely criticised as ineffective and unjust<note>ECRE
				[2001] 
				<title>Comments from the European Council on Refugees and Exiles on
				  the Proposal for a Council Regulation establishing the criteria and mechanisms
				  for determining the Member State responsible for examining an asylum
				  application lodged in one of the Member States by a third country
				  national,</title> ECRE, London; European Commission [2000] 
				<title>Commission Staff Working Paper Revisiting the Dublin
				  Convention</title> SEC [2000] 522.</note> and not much used.<note>The
				Convention came into force in September 1997 and its use for Algerians was
				shaken by the case of Aitsegeur. Following the House of Lords judgement in this
				case the Convention virtually ceased to apply to Algerians. The Danish Refugee
				Council undertook the only comprehensive empirical analysis of the workings of
				the Dublin Convention from 1997 to 2000 [Danish Refugee Council, 2001, 
				<xref url="http://www.flygtning.dk/publikationer/rapporter/dublin/dublin.pdf" type="pdf"><title>Analysis of the Dublin Convention</title></xref>]. This study
				gives no indication of separate nationality groups but reveals that in 1998 and
				1999, approximately 20% of all asylum applications to the UK were investigated
				under the Dublin Convention.</note> In 2001, the European Commission proposed a
			 regulation to replace the Dublin Convention which has become known as 'Dublin
			 II'. The proposal was not very different but introduced a new aim of preventing
			 'secondary movement' of asylum seekers from one member state to another. This
			 proposal was finally approved by the European Council in December 2003. The
			 final text resembles the original Dublin Convention even more closely than the
			 proposal and may well be implemented more effectively than the original
			 regulation.</p> 
		  <p>The Dublin Convention replaced an existing bilateral agreement on
			 return of asylum seekers between the UK and France [often called the
			 'gentleman's agreement'] signed in 1995. There has been considerable debate in
			 parliament on whether this agreement was replaced by Dublin, or was allowed to
			 lapse by the Labour government. Once it became clear that the Dublin Convention
			 was not performing as well as had been hoped, the UK government attempted to
			 renegotiate the bilateral agreement.<note>The question of renegotiation was
				first discussed at the Anglo-French summit in Cahors on 9 February 2001
				[<title>Guardian</title> 6.2.01] but this was unsuccessful.</note> However, the
			 situation of the Red Cross centre at Sangatte complicated the issue and this
			 bilateral agreement has still not been
			 signed.</p></div></div><div><head>Detention of asylum seekers</head> 
		  <p>Since the early 1990s, Algerian asylum seekers have been more likely
			 to be detained than asylum seekers of other nationalities [see statistics
			 section].<note>Home Office statistical bulletins [1990 -
				2001].</note></p></div><div><head>Anti-terrorism legislation</head> 
		  <p>From 2000 onwards, Algerians have been disproportionately affected
			 by anti-terrorism legislation and its implementation.</p> 
		  <p>There have been two important acts:</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item><xref url="http://www.hmso.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/20000011.htm">The Terrorism Act
				  [2000]</xref> defined terrorism as an international issue for the first time
				and proscribed a number of organisations including the Algerian Groupe
				Islamique Armée [GIA], [added to Schedule 2].</item> 
			 <item><xref url="http://www.hmso.gov.uk/acts/acts2001/20010024.htm">The Anti-Terrorism,
				  Crime and Security Act [2001]</xref> related terrorism explicitly to
				immigration and asylum [in part 4] and allowed for indefinite detention without
				charge for individuals 'suspected' by the Home Secretary of being linked to
				terrorism.</item> 
		  </list> 
		  <p>The French government have been openly critical of the British and
			 German positions on granting asylum to members of the Algerian Islamist
			 opposition since soon after the beginning of the conflict in Algeria.<note>In
				October 1994, the French Minister of the Interior, Charles Pasqua was openly
				critical of the British and German governments for not acting on his request to
				ban the FIS [<title>Le Monde</title> 4.10.94].</note> The Terrorism Act [2000]
			 was an acknowledgement of their criticism. The Anti-Terrorism, Crime and
			 Security Act [2001] was a direct response to the events of 11 September 2001
			 and went further in granting the <foreign>Home Secretary</foreign> considerable powers. The
			 majority of individuals detained under both of these acts have been Algerian,
			 though many of those people arrested have been released without charge [see key
			 issues section].</p> 
		  <p>Only one Algerian has been conclusively linked with 'serious
			 non-political crimes' in the British courts [see below]. This occurred in 1996,
			 well before either of these acts was passed, and suggests that previous
			 legislation may have been sufficient to protect Britain from violent
			 individuals.</p></div> 
		  <div type="box"><head>The case of T</head> 
		  <p>T claimed asylum in the UK in 1994. He admitted involvement in a
			 bomb attack on Algiers airport in which 10 people had died but argued that this
			 was a political act and should not bar him from refugee status in the UK. His
			 case eventually went to the House of Lords in 1996, and has become an important
			 test case for the exclusion clause [Article 1F] of the Geneva Convention. In
			 his judgement, Lord Mustill argued:</p><q>Those who use violence and fear to
			 struggle against oppression may themselves be oppressors, causing as much
			 suffering to the defenceless as those whom they seek to displace. When they
			 flee to a foreign country the impulse to protect them from persecution remains,
			 but it is muted. The community as a whole has a moral right to protection,
			 which should not be compromised by offering too ready a refuge to those who,
			 having embroiled the population in violence, find themselves on the losing
			 side.<note>T v Secretary of State for the Home Department House of Lords [1996]
				2 All ER 865, [1996] 2 WLR 766.</note></q> 
		  <p>Although Lord Mustill accepted that, but for these violent acts, T
			 would be considered a refugee, this violent activity was sufficient to exclude
			 him under article 1F. This finding is important since on the only occasion when
			 it has been demonstrated that an Algerian has been involved in violent
			 activity, the legal framework that existed in 1996 was sufficient to exclude
			 him from protection as a refugee. </p></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_05"> 
		  <body><head>Statistics </head><div><head>Algerians present in the
			 UK</head> 
		  <p>The 1991 <foreign>UK</foreign> census recorded 3,453 people of Algerian origin present
			 in the <foreign>UK</foreign>. However, it is important to note that this figure is based only on
			 the number of people born in Algeria. This <foreign>obviously</foreign> includes people who may
			 well not consider themselves to be Algerian [such as pieds noirs, for example]
			 and, conversely, does not include others who may consider themselves to be
			 Algerian, such as British or French-born children of Algerian migrants. The
			 immigration status of individuals is not recorded in the census, so it is
			 impossible to determine how many of this number are recognised refugees and how
			 many entered through other channels. Data from the 2001 <foreign>UK</foreign> census will be
			 available from April 2003 and this section will be updated at that
			 stage.</p></div><div><head>Algerians acquiring British citizenship</head> 
		  <p>Statistics for the number of Algerians acquiring British citizenship
			 may indicate the extent to which Algerians are becoming committed to living in
			 Britain. These naturalisations are split fairly equally between naturalisation
			 by residency and by marriage. 
		  </p> 
		  <table cols="2"> 
			 <row><cell role="label">Year</cell><cell role="label">Number of
				  Algerians granted British Citizenship</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1987</hi></cell><cell role="data">47</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1988</hi></cell><cell role="data">37</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1989</hi></cell><cell role="data">27</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1990</hi></cell><cell role="data">56</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1991</hi></cell><cell role="data">139</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1992</hi></cell><cell role="data">122</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1993</hi></cell><cell role="data">150</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1994</hi></cell><cell role="data">212</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1995</hi></cell><cell role="data">218</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1996</hi></cell><cell role="data">289</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1997</hi></cell><cell role="data">233</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1998</hi></cell><cell role="data">332</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">1999</hi></cell><cell role="data">376</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">2000</hi></cell><cell role="data">629</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell role="data"><hi rend="bold">2001</hi></cell><cell role="data">705</cell> 
			 </row> 
		  </table><p> 
			 <figure url="c002"> 
			 </figure></p> 
		  </div><div><head>Results of asylum requests made by Algerians</head> 
		  <p>Apart from the years 1998 and 1999, Algerians had an extremely small
			 chance of being offered asylum in the <foreign>UK</foreign>, much smaller than the average for all
			 nationalities.<note>Similar data for asylum seekers of all nationalities
				reveals very different results, particularly for 1998 and 1999.</note> The
			 terrible massacres at the end of 1997 were very widely publicised in the UK and
			 provoked a growing concern for the situation in Algeria. It is possible that
			 these events highlighted the plight of Algerians in the minds of asylum
			 adjudicators. It is also possible that the numbers granted refugee status were
			 inflated in these years by the efforts of the new Labour government to reduce
			 the backlog of cases, though decisions on applications from other nationalities
			 were not so dramatically affected.</p><div><head>Results of asylum requests
			 made by Algerians in the UK from 1990 to 2002<note>These figures do not always
				add up exactly as they are rounded to the nearest 5 by the Home Office and
				information on some decisions near the end of the period is not always
				available when statistics are compiled so this information is added to the
				following period.</note></head> 
		   
		  <table cols="6"> 
			 <row><cell role="label">Year</cell><cell role="label">Number of
				  applications</cell><cell role="label">Number of decisions</cell><cell role="label">Granted refugee status</cell><cell role="label">Granted
				  Exceptional Leave to Remain</cell><cell role="label">Refused</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1990</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>10</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1991</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1992</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1993</cell><cell>275</cell><cell>140</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>115</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1994</cell><cell>995</cell><cell>440</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>410</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1995</cell><cell>1865</cell><cell>745</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>720</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1996</cell><cell>715</cell><cell>1880</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>1835</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1997</cell><cell>715</cell><cell>765</cell><cell>105</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>655</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1998</cell><cell>1260</cell><cell>500</cell><cell>310</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>180</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>1999</cell><cell>1385</cell><cell>905</cell><cell>475</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>160</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>2000</cell><cell>1545</cell><cell>1627</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>1553</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>2001</cell><cell>1115</cell><cell>2645</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>75</cell><cell>2530</cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row><cell>2002</cell><cell>1060</cell><cell>1115</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>1065</cell>
				
			 </row> 
		  </table><p>Source: 
			 <xref url="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk">Home
				Office</xref></p></div><div><head>Results of asylum requests made by Algerians
			 in the UK from 1993 - 2002</head> 
		  <p> 
			 <figure url="c003"> 
			 </figure></p></div></div><div><head>Algerian asylum detainees in the
			 UK</head> 
		  <p>At any one time, there are relatively few Algerian asylum seekers in
			 detention. The highest number for a single date is 78, from January to March
			 1997. However the graph shows that if this is expressed as a percentage of the
			 total number of asylum seekers in detention and then compared to the proportion
			 of Algerians in the total number of asylum seekers, we see that Algerians have
			 been more likely to be detained than the average for all nationalities. The
			 most recent available statistics on detention, show that this proportion is
			 falling. These statistics do not include the high profile detentions of
			 Algerians during 2002 [see key issues section] but suggest that, at least in
			 the immediate aftermath of September 11th 2001, Algerian asylum seekers did not
			 suffer any measurable negative results in terms of increased
			 detention.</p><div><head>Algerians detained in the UK as a percentage of the
			 total number of people detained, compared to the number of Algerians claiming
			 asylum as a percentage of the total number claiming asylum 1994 -
			 2002<note>This data includes only those asylum seekers who have been detained
				during their application procedure and are included in the Home Office
				statistical bulletin 'Asylum Statistics' for the relevant year. Since 2000,
				these reports can be found on the web at 
				<xref url="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration1.html">http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration1.html</xref>.
				Data is for the number of individuals in detention on the specific date
				mentioned. Some dates are not shown for clarity. Unmarked dates are not always
				midway between marked dates.</note></head> 
		  <p> 
			 <figure url="c004"> 
			 </figure></p></div></div><div><head>How many Algerians request asylum
			 elsewhere?</head> 
		  <p>Although Algerians have requested asylum in increasing numbers in
			 the UK, other destinations continue to be far more significant. Comparable data
			 for movement other than asylum seeking are not available. The only organisation
			 that collects these data, SOPEMI, only specifies the most significant national
			 groups. Algerians only migrate in sufficiently large numbers to be considered
			 separately to France, which received between 8,000 and 12,000 Algerians a year
			 between 1990 and 2000. Comparable data do exist for asylum applications and are
			 shown in the table below.</p><div><head>Asylum applications made by Algerians
			 1990 - 2002 [For the eight countries to have received most applications]</head>
		  
		   
		  <table> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="label" rows="2">Year</cell> 
				<cell role="label" cols="8">Total number of Algerian asylum
				  applicants</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="label">Germany</cell> 
				<cell role="label">Belguim</cell> 
				<cell role="label">France</cell> 
				<cell role="label">NH</cell> 
				<cell role="label">Spain</cell> 
				<cell role="label">Switzerland</cell> 
				<cell role="label">UK</cell> 
				<cell role="label">Canada</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1990</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1035</cell> 
				<cell role="data">31</cell> 
				<cell role="data">141</cell> 
				<cell role="data">103</cell> 
				<cell role="data">0</cell> 
				<cell role="data">73</cell> 
				<cell role="data">15</cell> 
				<cell role="data">187</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1991</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1388</cell> 
				<cell role="data">61</cell> 
				<cell role="data">185</cell> 
				<cell role="data">80</cell> 
				<cell role="data">0</cell> 
				<cell role="data">109</cell> 
				<cell role="data">40</cell> 
				<cell role="data">123</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1992</cell> 
				<cell role="data">7669</cell> 
				<cell role="data">59</cell> 
				<cell role="data">677</cell> 
				<cell role="data">147</cell> 
				<cell role="data">0</cell> 
				<cell role="data">226</cell> 
				<cell role="data">0</cell> 
				<cell role="data">179</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1993</cell> 
				<cell role="data">11262</cell> 
				<cell role="data">236</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1098</cell> 
				<cell role="data">343</cell> 
				<cell role="data">87</cell> 
				<cell role="data">751</cell> 
				<cell role="data">275</cell> 
				<cell role="data">255</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1994</cell> 
				<cell role="data">2784</cell> 
				<cell role="data">402</cell> 
				<cell role="data">2303</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1321</cell> 
				<cell role="data">301</cell> 
				<cell role="data">303</cell> 
				<cell role="data">995</cell> 
				<cell role="data">721</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1995</cell> 
				<cell role="data">2940</cell> 
				<cell role="data">316</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1790</cell> 
				<cell role="data">650</cell> 
				<cell role="data">270</cell> 
				<cell role="data">388</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1870</cell> 
				<cell role="data">801</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1996</cell> 
				<cell role="data">2360</cell> 
				<cell role="data">225</cell> 
				<cell role="data">640</cell> 
				<cell role="data">440</cell> 
				<cell role="data">110</cell> 
				<cell role="data">396</cell> 
				<cell role="data">720</cell> 
				<cell role="data">609</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1997</cell> 
				<cell role="data">2620</cell> 
				<cell role="data">281</cell> 
				<cell role="data">900</cell> 
				<cell role="data">530</cell> 
				<cell role="data">270</cell> 
				<cell role="data">564</cell> 
				<cell role="data">720</cell> 
				<cell role="data">857</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1998</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1572</cell> 
				<cell role="data">337</cell> 
				<cell role="data">920</cell> 
				<cell role="data">821</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1581</cell> 
				<cell role="data">529</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1260</cell> 
				<cell role="data">813</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">1999</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1491</cell> 
				<cell role="data">351</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1306</cell> 
				<cell role="data">635</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1342</cell> 
				<cell role="data">491</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1385</cell> 
				<cell role="data">569</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">2000</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1381</cell> 
				<cell role="data">807</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1775</cell> 
				<cell role="data">279</cell> 
				<cell role="data">276</cell> 
				<cell role="data">492</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1635</cell> 
				<cell role="data">422</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">2001</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1981</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1709</cell> 
				<cell role="data">2924</cell> 
				<cell role="data">328</cell> 
				<cell role="data">225</cell> 
				<cell role="data">830</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1115</cell> 
				<cell role="data">543</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="data">2002</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1733</cell> 
				<cell role="data">936</cell> 
				<cell role="data">2839</cell> 
				<cell role="data">202</cell> 
				<cell role="data">344</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1031</cell> 
				<cell role="data">1055</cell> 
				<cell role="data">119</cell> 
			 </row> 
		  </table><p>Source: UNHCR<note>UNHCR [November 2001] 
				<title>Asylum Applications in Industrialised Countries: 1980 -
				  1999</title>; UNHCR [March 2002] 
				<title>Asylum Trends in Europe, North America. Australia, and New
				  Zealand: 1999 - 2001</title>; UNHCR [February 2003] 
				<title>Asylum applications lodged in industrialized countries:
				  Levels and trends 2000-2002</title>. All available at 
				<xref url="http://www.unhcr.ch">http://www.unhcr.ch</xref>.</note></p> 
		  <p>These figures relate to the graph in the historical context section.
			 It is clear that the large majority of Algerian asylum seekers initially went
			 to Germany and Germany continues to be significant.<note>The high number of
				applications in Germany was common to all asylum applications at the time. In
				the early 1990s, 60% of asylum applications in Europe were made in Germany so
				Algerians were not exceptional in this.</note> The UK received the second
			 largest number of applications in 1995 and 2000 but other than those years, a
			 smaller proportion of Algerians have come to the UK. In France, the application
			 procedure for the 'B-status' of asylum, called asile territorial, is entirely
			 separate and so not included in these figures. Estimates suggest that up to
			 7,000<note>ECRE [1999] 
				<title>Country Report : France</title>, ECRE, London; Delouvin, P.
				[2000] 'The evolution of asylum in France' 
				<title>Journal of Refugee Studies</title> 13[1], pp. 61-73.</note>
			 Algerians may have applied for the French 'B-status' over this period. If these
			 figures were included they would further inflate the numbers of Algerians going
			 to France.</p></div></div><div><head>Asylum support</head> 
		  <p>Since April 2000, destitute asylum seekers have been able to apply
			 for accommodation and subsistence support from the National Asylum Support
			 Service [NASS].<note>Home Office [2002] 
				<xref url="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs2/hosb902.pdf"><title>Asylum
					 statistics United Kingdom 2001</title></xref>. This provision has fluctuated
				somewhat with the recent withdrawal of support from in-country applicants and
				the reconfiguration of this change due to court appeals. See the 
				<xref url="http://www.refugeecouncil.org.uk/downloads/briefings/nia_act_02/section55_app_sum.pdf">Refugee
				  Council briefing</xref> for more information.</note> At the end of 2000, 470
			 Algerians were being supported under NASS. Of these, 105 received subsistence
			 only, and 355 also received accommodation. Those who received no accommodation
			 were likely to be staying with friends or had simply rejected the accommodation
			 offered to them. During 2001, 970 Algerians were supported: 240 for subsistence
			 only and 625 for full support. At the end of 2001, a total of 1010 Algerians
			 were receiving support under NASS. These figures are slightly less than the
			 number of Algerians who requested asylum in 2001 since some people obviously
			 refused, or were refused, support. More recent figures suggest that in January
			 2003, 1,009 Algerians were receiving accommodation and subsistence support from
			 NASS. Figures for those receiving subsistence only support were not available
			 at the time of writing. </p></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_06"> 
		  <body><head>Cultural background</head> 
		  <p>The Algerian population in the UK has only begun to grow
			 significantly over the last 10 years and is still small compared to many more
			 established national groups. The rich cultural heritage of Algeria is therefore
			 not widely recognised in Britain. Algeria has well developed traditions of art,
			 literature, music, film and cuisine. This section aims to give a brief
			 introduction to these aspects of Algerian cultural practices for the
			 non-specialist. Representing the cultural diversity of Algeria is not an easy
			 task. The 'Year of Algeria' in France [2003] presents an extremely rich
			 programme of Algerian cultural events but has raised controversy in a number of
			 areas. A large group of significant political and civil society figures have
			 criticised this programme as a public relations exercise for the Algerian
			 government.<note>'L'Année de quelle Algérie?' 
				<title>Le Monde</title> 6.2.03.</note> Such voices of dissent have
			 been raised with regard to other special events, notably during the 'Year of
			 Morocco' in 1999, but the criticisms of the 'Year of Algeria' are rather more
			 mainstream. Even the FNAC [a large French chain of stores selling books, music
			 and equipment] announced a special programme called 'Another vision of
			 Algeria'. Cultural expression is, arguably, always a political act, but this is
			 especially the case in a divided society such as
			 Algeria.</p><div><head>Literature</head> 
		  <p>Although there is a long tradition of written work in Algeria - from
			 the fourth century work of Saint Augustine, in Latin, to the nineteenth century
			 theological writings of Abdel-Kader, in Arabic - the novel only arrived with
			 the French. Previous to this, fiction had been expressed as poetry and oral
			 storytelling but by the beginning of the twentieth century, Algerian writers
			 began producing long fiction. Initially this work was written very much in the
			 French style for a French audience, but a powerful and often extremely
			 political Algerian voice soon developed. This work considered major issues of
			 Algerian history and independence, Berber cultural identity, the place of Islam
			 in Algerian society and, more recently, the current conflict. Algerian
			 literature in French and Arabic now constitutes a very rich body of work in
			 world literature, but unfortunately comparatively little has been translated
			 into English.<note>See 
				<xref url="http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/In_English_Translation/index.htm">http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/In_English_Translation/index.htm</xref>
				for a full and continually updated listing of the work of Algerian writers
				available in English.</note></p> 
		  <p>From the beginning of the twentieth century, novels written in
			 French began to appear by a French-educated Algerian elite. These typically
			 reflected the negative view of the indigenous population that was dominant
			 among French colonisers and idealised the French occupation of Algeria;
			 occasionally they were even co-authored with French writers.<note>Such as
				<hi>Saad Ben Ali and René Pottier </hi>[1933] 
				<title>La Tente noire, roman saharien</title>, Les Oeuvres
				Représentatives, Paris.</note> More realistic novels were initially rejected by
			 French publishers; Mouloud Feraoun wrote the semi-autobiographical 
		  <title>Le Fils du pauvre</title> [the son of the poor man] in 1939
		  which was not published until 1950. It tells the story of a family from a small
		  village in the Berber province of Kabylia where life is extremely hard and
		  there are no visible signs of the French 'civilising mission' despite more than
		  a century of French presence. Eventually the father of the family leaves to
		  find work in France, as Feroun's father did and as was the case for a growing
		  number of Kabyle men from the 1920s onwards. Feroun's second novel, 
		  <title>La Terre et le sang</title> [earth and blood] published in 1953,
		  further explored the experience of emigrating to France. A number of other
		  novels of the period also dealt with emigration, such as<title>La Colline
			 oubliée</title>, [the forgotten hill] written by Feroun's friend Mouloud
		  Mammeri in 1952.<title> La Colline oubliée</title> was made into a film,
		  directed by Abderrahmane Bouguermouh, in 1995.<note>Interestingly, the film was
			 finished thanks to financial support from the emigrant community, particularly 
			 <xref url="http://www.ee.umd.edu/~sellami/DEC95/colline.html">La
				Colline Oubliée Fund</xref> based in New Jersey.</note></p> 
		  <p>Mohammed Dib, one of the most prolific Algerian writers, published
			 the first volume of his 'Algeria' trilogy in 1952, 
		  <title>La Grande Maison</title> [the large house], followed by 
		  <title>L'Incendie </title>[the fire] [1954] and 
		  <title>Le Métier à tisser</title> [the loom] [1957]. These books
		  present a picture of the highly exploitative relationship between the
		  colonisers and the local population in the region of Tlemcen. The books are
		  ostensibly set around the beginning of the Second World War but critics have
		  demonstrated<note>Bonn, C. [1985] 
			 <title>Le Roman Algérien de langue française</title>, Editions
			 L'Harmattan, Paris.</note> that the events relate to a strike by agricultural
		  workers that Dib covered for a national paper in 1951. The events of the strike
		  are dealt with in 
		  <title>L'Incendie</title>, which was published a few months before the
		  beginning of the 1954-62 war. </p> 
		  <p><title>Nedjma</title>, by Kateb Yacine
		  [1956]<note><title>Nedjma</title> is available in English translation,
			 published in 1991 by the University Press of Virginia.</note> is another
		  powerfully nationalist novel. 
		  <title>Nedjma</title> also considers revolt against the colonial
		  presence in a similar way to Dib's trilogy but Kateb also rebelled against the
		  French form of the novel, introducing a number of striking stylistic
		  innovations, such as breaking up the accepted chronological pattern of story
		  telling. Because of this dramatic departure from French tradition, 
		  <title>Nedjma</title> is widely considered to mark the beginning of a
		  new wave of Algerian writing and established Kateb as one of the most respected
		  Algerian writers. Assia Djebar is another very highly respected writer who
		  began writing during this period with<title> La Soif </title>[the thirst] in
		  1957 and 
		  <title>Les Impatients</title> [impatient people] the following year.
		  Djebar is interested in the position of women in Algeria immediately before the
		  1954-62 war. Her heroines are educated women who reflect on their situation and
		  their relationship with French women and she is keen to show that education is
		  the route to the emancipation of women.</p>
		  <p>It is, of course, difficult to do justice to Algerian literature in
			 a few paragraphs, and new work is continuously being published.<note>For one of
				the best current and continually updated reviews of new Algerian writing in
				French see 
				<xref url="http://www.algeriades.com/news/sommaire_themes.php3?id_mot=4">http://www.algeriades.com/news/sommaire_themes.php3?id_mot=4</xref>.</note>
			 Many people consider that a second wave of literary style was launched with the
			 publication of 
		  <title>La Répudiation</title> [the repudiation] by Rachid Boudjedra
		  [1969], which focused on the place of Islam in Algerian society. The literature
		  d'urgence provoked by the current conflict is undoubtedly another new
		  development. A number of writers, such as Kateb and Boudjedra, began to write
		  in Arabic, while other significant Algerian writers, such as Tahar Ouettar,
		  write exclusively in Arabic. Finally, there is the very significant
		  contribution from pieds noirs writers, most famously Albert Camus but also Jean
		  Senac, who chose Algerian nationality on independence rather than returning to
		  France. He was killed soon after independence. Mouloud Feraoun was also
		  murdered by departing pieds noirs following independence. These are further
		  reminders how political the act of writing so often is in Algeria and an
		  unpleasant avatar of threats and attacks on writers in the more recent
		  conflict.</p></div><div type="box"><head>The 'literature d'urgence'</head> 
		  <p>In May 1993, the writer and journalist Tahar Djaout was assassinated
			 in Algiers. His death was the first in a long line of murders of prominent
			 intellectuals and artists over the summer of 1993. This level of violence
			 forced a large number of intellectual figures into exile; the second major
			 movement out of Algeria after the first wave of Islamist politicians and
			 activists in 1992. Djaout was a highly respected author best known for his
			 novels,<note>Djaout is perhaps best known for 
				<title>Les chercheurs d'os</title> [Searching for bones] [1984] and
				
				<title>Dernier été de la raison</title> [The last summer of reason]
				published posthumously in 1999.</note> a regular contributor to national
			 newspapers and a prominent critic of both the government and the FIS. He has
			 become a symbol for the resistance of writers to intimidation and violence in
			 Algeria that has provoked a phenomenal flourishing of artistic production often
			 referred to as the 'literature d'urgence'. This has seen established writers
			 turn their attentions to the conflict and its effects and a tremendous growth
			 in literary expression from people who may well never have written at all if
			 not for their need to find an outlet for the distress they witnessed around
			 them. Most of this writing remains firmly in the tradition of politically
			 engaged fiction that has characterised the Algerian novel since before
			 independence. </p> 
		  <p>Among this new literature, the strongly anti-Islamist novels of
			 Yasmina Khadra are one of the most widely read examples.<note>Khadra, Y. [1998]
				
				<title>Les agneaux du seigneur.</title> Julliard, Paris; Khadra, Y.
				[1999] 
				<title>A quoi rêvent les loups</title>. Julliard, Paris.</note> In
			 2000, Khadra revealed that, as many people had suspected, she was in fact a
			 male officer in the special forces of the Algerian army, though she continues
			 to write under the same name [and continues to be referred to as 'she' in the
			 press]. Khadra's novels are published in France. Other work is produced by less
			 well-known Algerian publishers,<note>Such as Arezki Mellal [2000] 
				<title>Maintenant, Ils peuvent venir,</title> Editions barzakh,
				Algiers.</note> although exiled Algerian writers now live all over Europe. The
			 association 
			 <xref url="http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/Algerie_Litterature_Action/index.htm">Algérie
				Literature/Action</xref> has made one of the most significant contributions to
			 publishing current Algerian fiction. Since 1996 they have produced a regular
			 journal [in French] containing new, full-length novels or collections of short
			 stories and poetry, motivated by the conviction that artistic production can
			 contribute to the peaceful resolution of the conflict. In the UK, two Algerian
			 writers contribute to the association 
			 <xref url="http://www.exiledwriters.co.uk/">Exiled Writers
				Ink</xref>; the artist and poet 
			 <xref url="http://www.exiledwriters.co.uk/writers.shtml">Nafissa
				Boudalia</xref> and the poet and short story writer 
			 <xref url="http://www.exiledwriters.co.uk/writers.shtml">Samia
				Dahnaan</xref>.</p></div><div><head>Music</head> 
		  <p>The tremendous diversity of musical styles and traditions in Algeria
			 reflects the diverse ethnic origins of the population.<note>This is clear from
				Algerian radio. A good range of Algerian radio stations is available online at 
				<xref url="http://www.vtuner.com/vtunerweb/static/staticAlgeriaoverall1.html">http://www.vtuner.com/vtunerweb/static/staticAlgeriaoverall1.html</xref>.</note>
			 The most common form of classical music originates in Andalusia, Spain, and
			 arrived in Algeria in the fifteenth century, following the expulsion of the
			 Arabic population from Spain. This music is often called maalouf or andalus and
			 is played on traditional instruments.<note><title>Musique andalouse
				  d'Algérie</title> [Harmonia Mundi 2003] by Nassima is an excellent, recent
				example of this music.</note></p> 
		  <p>There is also a tradition of folk music sung in Berber languages.
			 Idir is currently one of the most popular Berber musicians; he gave a rare
			 concert in the UK in 2002 and played to a huge crowd at the Barbican. Lounes
			 Matoub, another Berber musician, was killed in mysterious circumstances in
			 1998. He was always an extremely popular singer and since his death he has
			 become an extremely powerful symbol of Berber culture and his music is rarely
			 absent from Berber demonstrations.</p> 
		  <p>There is a further cultural influence from the pieds noirs; the
			 tremendously popular Jewish-Algerian singer Enrico Macias retains his links
			 with Algeria, though he now lives in France. Finally there is a long tradition
			 of Arabic folk music or chaabi. Chaabi songs are concerned with classic popular
			 themes of love and duty but also relate a particular vision of developments in
			 Algerian society from emigration in the 1950s to despair at the current
			 conflict today. Contemporary raï music has developed these concerns. In fact it
			 is common for modern raï singers to update classic chaabi songs, such as 'Ya
			 Raya!' [O, you who are leaving]. Written in 1954 about emigration, it has
			 become a standard and most raï singers perform their own version of its
			 classic, easily recognisable melody.</p> 
		  </div><div type="box"><head>Raï</head> 
		  <p>A combination of traditional Algerian rhythms and modern electric
			 instruments, raï developed in the town of Oran in Western Algeria. It
			 originated in the early 1980s and soon became associated with youth rebellion
			 and anti-establishment behaviour. Early raï musicians were strongly disapproved
			 of as socially deviant and morally corrupting by traditionally orientated
			 mainstream society, similar to punk in Britain; indeed musicians such as
			 French-Algerian Rachid Taha continue to make a conscious effort to develop the
			 punk-raï connection. Rai was particularly disapproved of by Islamist groups.
			 The local FIS administration banned the 1991 raï festival in Oran due to the
			 glorification of over-drinking and sex in some raï songs. Raï singers such as
			 Cheb Hasni were targeted in the wave of assassinations of 1993 and 1994 and
			 many joined other artists in exile. Raï is sometimes seen as a form of
			 resistance to Islamism, though the relationship between the two is undoubtedly
			 more complex than this.<note>Marc Schade-Poulsen has conducted an extremely
				interesting ethnography exploring the social significance of raï in his book 
				<title>Men and popular music in Algeria</title> [1999], University
				of Texas Press. Extracts from this book can be found at 
				<xref url="http://inic.utexas.edu/menic/rai/">http://inic.utexas.edu/menic/rai/</xref></note>
			 </p> 
		  <p>Raï has become far more respectable and mainstream in recent years
			 and many raï singers now wish to distance themselves from the associations of
			 raï with more excessive behaviour. Raï spread to France in the mid-1980s and it
			 was well known and commercially successful by the early 1990s. Today the most
			 influential musicians, such as Khaled or Cheb Mami, are internationally known.
			 There are currently two accomplished raï musicians living and performing
			 regularly in the UK. Abdelkader Saadoun has an informative 
			 <xref url="http://www.saadoun.com/">website</xref> with details of
			 his upcoming concerts and his last album, Saadia. Abdel Ali Slimani has two
			 albums: <hi>Mraya</hi> [2000] on Real World and <hi>Espoir</hi> [2003] on
			 Harmonia Mundi.</p></div><div><head>Film</head> 
		  <p>One of the most famous Algerian films, 
		  <title>The Battle of Algiers</title>[1966] was actually directed by an
		  Italian, Gillo Pontecorvo. It tells the story of the fight for the capital
		  between January and March 1957. It is astonishing to imagine the major events
		  of this battle re-enacted in Algiers less than four years after the end of the
		  war. Many of the major figures in the battle, including Saadi Yacef, the head
		  of the FLN's Algiers network actually play themselves in the film, making it an
		  extremely important historical document, as well as a valuable recreation of
		  one of the most famous episodes of the entire war.</p> 
		  <p>Algerian directors soon became established overseas. In 1975, 
		  <title>Chronique des années de braise</title> [Chronicle of the years
		  of embers] won the Palme d'Or at Cannes. The following year, the now celebrated
		  director Merzak Allouache released his first film, 
		  <title>Omar Gatlato</title> [1976] which explored divisions and
		  destitution in the suburb of Algiers where he lived, Bab el Oued. After
		  producing a number of acclaimed documentaries for television, Allouache
		  returned to Bab el Oued almost 20 years later to film the rise of the Islamist
		  movement. The resulting Bab el Oued City won the International Critics Prize at
		  Cannes in 1994. He recorded his experiences of making the film in an
		  entertaining book of the same name [1995, Le Seuil, Paris]. In 1995 Allouache
		  turned to comedy with 
		  <title>Salut Cousin!</title>, a complex story of travel and trade
		  between Algeria and Paris and his most recent film 
		  <title>Chouchou</title> [2003] is also very light hearted.</p> 
		  <p>The novelist Assia Djebar has also made a number of powerful films
			 addressing similar issues as her books; the history of Algeria and the place of
			 women in constructing that history. Her first film, 
		  <title>La Zerda et les Chants de l'oubli</title> [1978] mixed
		  documentary and narrative techniques to relate the story of a woman who returns
		  to Algeria 15 years after independence and is caught up in her memories of the
		  war. There is of course no reason why Algerian filmmakers should restrict
		  themselves to the subject of Algeria, although many have done. A notable
		  exception is Rachid Bouchareb's 
		  <title>Little Senegal </title> [2000] which tells the story of a young
		  man's migration from Senegal to a neighbourhood of Harlem.</p> 
		  <p>Filming in Algeria over the past decade has been extremely difficult
			 and little was produced during the 1990s other than a small number of
			 documentaries, such as 
		  <title>Femme Taxi à Sidi Bel-Abbés</title> [2000] in which director
		  Belkacem Hadjadj constructed a portrait of the only female taxi driver in Sidi
		  Bel-Abbés, a town in western Algeria. Algerian directors have filmed outside of
		  Algeria, often retaining the theme of the war, such as Merzak Allouche's [1999]
		  
		  <title>Algiers Beirut</title>, filmed almost entirely in Beirut about
		  an Algerian who has come to Lebanon to try and escape war at home. A range of
		  films by Algerian directors have also focused on other aspects of Algerian
		  life, such as the history of migration, mainly to France. This is a theme which
		  Yamina Benguigui made her own with 
		  <title>Memoire d'Immigrés</title> [Immigrants' memories] in 1997.
		  Benguigui has recently returned to the history of emigration with 
		  <title>Inch'Allah Dimanche</title> [Sunday, if God wishes], 2001.
		  Yamina Bachir-Chouikh's 
		  <title>Rachida</title> [2002] returns to the theme of the current
		  conflict with a harrowing examination of a female teacher's struggle to
		  overcome an attack. The recent flourishing of Algerian cinema has been given a
		  further boost by the announcement of French funding for 10 full-length feature
		  films as part of the 'Year of Algeria' [2003] in France.<note>This was reported
			 in the February - March special issue of the Cahiers du Cinema entitled 'Ou va
			 le cinema Algérien?'. This special issue provides an excellent overview of the
			 history of Algerian cinema.</note></p></div><div><head>Cuisine</head> 
		  <p>Although cuisine is more of a craft than an art, it is worth
			 mentioning since the introduction of Algerian cafés and restaurants is a
			 visible result of the growth of the Algerian community in the UK. Cafés also
			 seem to provide an important economic base for some of the community and there
			 are now a number of Algerian cafés in Finsbury Park where it is possible to
			 sample cakes and listen to Algerian television. Algerian food is very similar
			 to the cuisine of neighbouring Morocco and Tunisia, including rich soups,
			 couscous with a variety of sauces, sweet cakes and mint tea. Moroccan
			 restaurants are increasingly common, at least in London, but it is still
			 unusual to find an Algerian restaurant; the Souk, off St Martin's Lane, central
			 London, is a rare exception.</p></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_07"> 
		  <body><head>Key issues</head> 
		  <p>The most significant issues facing the Algerian community in the UK
			 can be grouped into eight categories: asylum, undocumented status, detention
			 and deportation, employment, isolation, the effects of anti-terrorist
			 legislation, contact with Algeria and the growth of the Algerian population in
			 the UK.</p><div><head>Asylum</head> 
		  <p>The large majority of the Algerian population in the UK [estimates
			 range from 70% to 90%] has arrived over the last 10 years, during the period of
			 conflict. The conflict is likely to have affected everyone in Algeria. Most
			 people are likely to know someone who has been killed or injured, many have
			 witnessed the deaths of friends and family and many more recount scenes of
			 astonishing barbarity. The most pressing need for this population is therefore
			 for a secure period of residency elsewhere.</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Apart from the years 1998 and 1999, on average, Algerians were
				less likely to receive asylum in the UK than other national groups.</item> 
			 <item>Many Algerians would prefer a shorter period of protection
				since the symbolic break with the home country that is associated with refugee
				status deters many people from applying.<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining
				  change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France
				  and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the
				  British Library; this point is also commonly made in French literature on
				  Algerian asylum requests e.g. GISTI [1999] 
				  <title>Les droits des Algériens en France</title>, Les cahiers
				  juridiques. GISTI, Paris.</note></item> 
			 <item>The French system of 'B-status' 'territorial asylum', which
				lasts for a limited time and carries fewer benefits than full Convention status
				was tailor made for the Algerian population.</item> 
			 <item>Both territorial asylum, in France and Exceptional Leave to
				Remain [ELR], in the UK are very rarely given to Algerians; figures vary
				between one per cent and four per cent, depending on the year.<note>Home Office
				  statistical bulletins; Amnesty International Section Française [1997] 
				  <title>l'Asile en France, Etat des lieux</title>, Paris; Delouvin
				  [2000] 'The Evolution of Asylum In France' 
				  <title>Journal of Refugee Studies</title> 13[1], pp.
				  61-73.</note></item> 
		  </list> 
		  <p>This information points to a very significant 'protection gap' for
			 the Algerian population. Many Algerians, if refused asylum, prefer to remain
			 undocumented than risk returning to Algeria and more than half the Algerian
			 population in the UK is thought to be undocumented. Asylum has a number of
			 disadvantages for Algerians:</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>The Algerian government has suggested that those people who are
				granted asylum in Europe are more likely to be terrorists or
				deserters.<note>Benyamina, A. [1998] 'Foreign interference in the situation in
				  Algeria: The Algerian government's position'. 
				  <title>Cambridge Review of International Affairs</title> 1998
				  vol. XI no.2, pp. 184 - 195.</note> This is often repeated by undocumented
				Algerians as a reason for not claiming asylum. Many are concerned what their
				family will think of them if they tell them that they have claimed asylum. The
				director of the Algerian Refugee Council commented:<q> 'Many people don't even
				  tell their parents that they have claimed asylum […] Some people have lived
				  here for ten years and even though they have a life threatening situation in
				  Algeria, they don't claim asylum.'</q><note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining
				  change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France
				  and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the
				  British Library.</note></item> 
			 <item>Those that do claim asylum find it extremely difficult to be
				cut off from their families in Algeria.</item> 
			 <item>Others associated claiming asylum with laziness since they
				wished to work and were unwilling to take benefits. A 42 year-old man who had
				been undocumented for 2 years, having rejected the possibility of claiming
				asylum, reported: 'They pay for your house - I didn't want that, I didn't want
				that, really, I didn't want that, because I can work, I'm not lazy. That's what
				I say, if you're not lazy, you don't need that.'<note>Collyer, M. [2002]
				  'Explaining change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians
				  to France and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at
				  the British Library.</note></item> 
			 <item>An Algerian refugee support worker reported that Algerians
				referred to the regular collection of vouchers under NASS as 'the
				shame'<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established migration
				  systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK' University of Sussex,
				  DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British Library.</note>.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Undocumented status</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Estimates of the size of the Algerian population in the UK,
				based on 'best guesses' of NGOs and individuals, and existing statistical
				data<note>1991 British census, acquisitions of citizenship and number of asylum
				  applicants. It is not possible to tell exactly what status these people have,
				  though we know that since 1991, 1009 Algerians have been granted refugee status
				  [see statistics section].</note> suggest that there are somewhere between
				25,000 and 30,000 Algerians in the UK. Statistical information suggests that
				approximately 10,000 of these are legally resident.<note>This number cannot be
				  exact as there is no basis for cross-referencing different sources of
				  statistical information. For example it is likely that there is some overlap
				  between Algerians granted refugee status and those granted British citizenship
				  a few years later but the size of this overlap can only be estimated.</note>
				Therefore somewhere around 60 % of Algerians in the UK may have no legal
				status.</item> 
			 <item>Legal status is increasingly significant in the UK since
				without it access to many basic services is denied. In addition to services
				such as health and education, a number of other issues arise from legal status
				that have serious implications for the life of Algerians in the UK. The two
				most significant are that financial management is problematic as it is
				impossible to open a bank account and difficult to cash pay-cheques, and that
				residence is extremely precarious as detention and deportation can occur at any
				time.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Detention and deportation</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Since the early 1990s, Algerian asylum seekers have been more
				likely to be detained than the average for all groups of asylum seekers in the
				UK. Asylum seekers are obviously not undocumented but there is a link, since
				undocumented Algerians are likely to request asylum if they are discovered by
				police or immigration services. If an individual claims asylum after arrest for
				illegal immigration, their asylum claim will be treated with some suspicion and
				they are likely to be detained.<note>The notion of 'manifestly unfounded
				  claims' from the Immigration and Asylum Act [1996] onwards is very clear on
				  this point.</note> Refugee support groups reiterate that asylum claims should
				be judged on the substantive facts of the case and not on the circumstances
				surrounding the application,<note>Such as Refugee Council [2003] 
				  <title>In Exile</title>, January/February, Refugee Council,
				  London.</note> but using detention in this way is still common.</item> 
			 <item>Although deportations to Algeria were suspended during the
				years of the worst violence from 1997 to 1999, they have now resumed.</item> 
			 <item>The level of cooperation between the Algerian and British
				governments is increasing and the Home Office minister Ben Bradshaw has made at
				least three visits to Algeria in recent years. The possibility of deporting
				Algerians more speedily was, according to the BBC, a topic of discussion on
				each occasion.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Work</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>By common consent it is not difficult to find work in the UK,
				even for those without documentation. 'Djamal'<note>Not his real name.</note> a
				35 year old man, speaking in French, explained: 
				<p>Djamal: I didn't want to make money. In this country you can
				  find a job, and I found a job. I don't need to work five hours a day, sometimes
				  I work five days, six days, just pay my rent, transport, some food and that's
				  it.</p> 
				<p>Int.: <hi>What sort of work did you do?</hi></p> 
				<p>Djamal: I worked cooking, in the kitchen. It's the only job you
				  can find, with the language.</p> 
				<p>Int.: <hi>Were you able to find that work fairly
				  easily?</hi></p> 
				<p>Djamal: Easy, easy, I find a lot of jobs. […] you can have two
				  jobs, three jobs.'<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established
					 migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK' University
					 of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British
					 Library.</note></p></item> 
			 <item>However the Algerian population in the UK is particularly
				highly qualified and it is difficult for people to find work commensurate with
				their qualifications, even with documentation. Farid, also undocumented,
				described his work: 
				<q>'You know, you have to fight for yourself if you work illegally
				  with someone and he knows you're illegal. So the person, what does he think -
				  "he's illegal, I can do whatever I like". Some people, [with me, no, it doesn't
				  work] but some people, they're scared: "If I say something to him he's going to
				  call immigration" you see? So I was surviving, just doing bits and pieces here,
				  cleaning for someone in this shop, helping to carry stuff for him, doing things
				  like that, just to get my money for the day, then tomorrow, another day, we'll
				  see what's going to happen.'</q><note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in
				  established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK'
				  University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British
				  Library.</note></item> 
			 <item>The situation for doctors is particularly severe since many
				Algerian doctors did some of their training in France and are used to European
				health systems and allowed to work in France. This is not considered relevant
				for the process of transferring their qualifications in the UK and in addition,
				they must pass an extremely rigorous language test. Amin had been a doctor in
				the Algerian army but had not been prepared to follow some of the orders he
				received and had to leave the country. In England, he found that he had little
				chance of working as a doctor: 
				<q> 'Every day on the television I see "shortage of doctors,
				  shortage of doctors' and I want to work, but they won't have me, I can't work
				  in this country. [….] I'm not going to sweep or stack
				  shelves."</q><note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in established
				  migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK' University
				  of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British
				  Library.</note></item> 
			 <item>The World University Service and the British Medical
				Association are addressing the concerns around the qualifications of doctors
				but these are obviously issues which need much wider consideration if the
				skills of refugee populations, such as Algerians, are not to be wasted.</item> 
			 <item>The issue of employment for undocumented migrants or those
				whose asylum claim has been rejected is linked to a much larger set of issues
				that are beyond the scope of this guide.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Isolation</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>The uncertainty of the conflict has undermined Algerians' trust
				in each other and left many feeling extremely isolated.<note>All data in this
				  section refer to the author's thesis unless otherwise stated: Collyer, M.
				  [2002] 'Explaining change in established migration systems: the movement of
				  Algerians to France and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and
				  recorded at the British Library.</note></item> 
			 <item>Few of them have established the solidarity networks that exist
				within more established refugee populations.</item> 
			 <item>The fact that such a large proportion of the Algerian
				population in the UK have arrived so recently also leads to a widespread
				unfamiliarity with the dominant culture.</item> 
			 <item>In terms of religious observance most Algerians questioned as
				part of the author's research were able to visit local mosques if they wished
				and, though there is certainly no mosque particularly linked to the Algerian
				community, they felt very welcome worshipping with the dominant South Asian
				Muslim group. One man who had been dispersed under the government scheme to
				Bournemouth was delighted at the diversity he found:<q rend="block">"We have a
				  small mosque with about 200 people who attend regularly, from everywhere;
				  Algerians, yes, but there are also Iraqis, Indonesians, Congolese, Tunisians,
				  Moroccans, it is very diverse!"<note>Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining change in
					 established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the UK'
					 University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the British
					 Library.</note></q></item> 
			 <item>Algerians who have been in the UK a significant amount of time
				speak English well or fluently, but it is still more common for those arriving
				to speak French better than English. This reduces the opportunities for contact
				with those who do not speak French or Arabic/Tamaziyt.</item> 
			 <item>Algerians are very highly represented among the client group of
				several refugee mental health services in London. It is possible that there is
				less stigma attached to mental health issues for Algerians than other refugee
				groups,<note>This possibility was suggested by the founder of a refugee mental
				  health group in Waltham Forest to explain the huge numbers of Algerians she
				  assisted. Algerians have been exposed to a modern health care system for a
				  great many years, even if they did not always have access to it.</note> but
				this may also be due to the combination of a history of trauma and the
				isolation from any significant community life that many report once they arrive
				in the UK.</item> 
			 <item>Algerians fall outside of commonly used ethnic categories in
				the UK. Caroline Nagel has highlighted the effects of belonging to the 'Other
				Other' category in the UK census as a feeling of marginalisation in the UK
				discourse on the politics of race.<note>Nagel, C. [2001] 'Hidden minorities and
				  the politics of 'race': the case of British Arab activists in London' 
				  <title>Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies</title>
				  27.</note></item> 
			 <item>The 
				<xref url="http://www.consalglond.u-net.com/Embassy.htm">Algerian
				  consulate</xref> in London provides a range of practical services for the
				Algerian community but they have an ambiguous relationship with the
				asylum-seeking population who have, in their eyes, distanced themselves from
				the Algerian state. The previous Algerian Ambassador in London was sharply
				critical of Algerian asylum seekers, even to the extent of undermining their
				asylum claims.<note>Benyamina, A. [1998] 'Foreign interference in the situation
				  in Algeria: The Algerian government's position' 
				  <title>Cambridge Review of International Affairs</title> 1998
				  vol. XI no.2 pp. 184 - 195.</note></item> 
			 <item>Overall, Algerians in the UK are often in a difficult position
				with no organised community to which they may belong or feel they
				belong.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Effects of anti-terrorism legislation</head> 
		  <p>Algerians have been seriously affected by the Terrorism Act [2000]
			 and the Anti-Terrorism, Crime and Security Act [2001]. The majority of
			 individuals detained under these acts have been Algerian. More importantly
			 however, the resulting press coverage has portrayed an extremely unfavourable
			 picture of Algerians and since the Algerian population is poorly known in the
			 UK, this has had the effect of encouraging the association of Algerians with
			 terrorism. This association has unsurprisingly had negative effects on the
			 resident Algerian population as a whole.</p> 
		  <p>The direct impact of these acts on Algerians:</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>Six of the initial nine people detained under the
				Anti-Terrorism, Crime and Security Act in January 2002 were Algerian.</item> 
			 <item>The events of January 2003 predominantly involved Algerians and
				were all linked to the first arrests. 
				<list> 
				  <item>On 5 January 2003, four Algerians in London were charged
					 under the Terrorism Act following the discovery of chemicals linked to the
					 nerve agent ricin in their flat.</item> 
				  <item>On 15 January 2003, three Algerians [and a fourth the
					 following day] in Manchester were charged with offences under the Terrorism
					 Act. During the arrest one of the men stabbed the police officer, Steven Oakes,
					 who later died.</item> 
				  <item>On 20 January 2003, seven people were arrested following
					 the raid on the Finsbury Park mosque, six of them were Algerian. Only one was
					 charged under the Anti-Terrorism, Crime and Security Act.</item> 
				  <item>On 29 January 2003, four further Algerians were arrested in
					 Manchester and were charged with offences under the Terrorism Act.</item> 
				</list></item> 
		  </list> 
		  <p> Results of these developments:</p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>It is obviously essential that violent acts are controlled and
				the activities of the individuals arrested certainly raise concerns. However,
				we should be prepared to draw a clear distinction between being charged with an
				offence and being found guilty of that offence. The media has not always been
				willing to respect this difference. For example, the arrest of seven
				individuals at Finsbury Park mosque was given far more media coverage than the
				subsequent release without charge of six of the seven initially
				arrested.</item> 
			 <item>The Geneva Convention [1951] includes two exclusion clauses
				[articles 1f and 33[2]] which have been shown to work effectively [see section
				on legal issues]. The only Algerian asylum seeker to be found to fall within
				these exclusion clauses was not offered legal residence in the UK.</item> 
			 <item>Many Algerians in the UK report feeling increasingly
				uncomfortable in the current climate,<note>Based on personal communication with
				  Algerians in London during January and February 2003.</note> although the most
				recent data on detentions of asylum seekers [December 2002] actually suggests
				that the number of Algerians detained is falling as a percentage of all
				detainees.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Contacts with Algeria</head> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>The need to return or maintain some contact with Algeria is
				growing in importance as the Algerian population becomes more settled.</item> 
			 <item>They have arrived so recently that there is really no
				infrastructure to support exchanges, return to, or even contact with
				Algeria.</item> 
			 <item>Algiers is one of the few capital cities in the world with no
				direct flight to London.</item> 
			 <item>Information on Algeria can only be obtained through specialist
				news sources since the dominant media rarely covers Algerian issues.</item> 
			 <item>The official exchange rate to return money to Algeria is
				extremely disadvantageous. Where there are well-established Algerian
				communities, there are also established alternative channels. There is little
				indication that this is the case in relation to the UK.</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>The growth of the Algerian population in the
			 UK</head> 
		  <p>One of the key questions on the Algerian population in the UK is why
			 has it grown at all; why are Algerians keen to claim asylum in the UK and not
			 in France? There are a number of possibilities that contribute towards an
			 explanation of this question.<note>This was the focus of the author's thesis
				and all information in this section comes from Collyer, M. [2002] 'Explaining
				change in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France
				and the UK' University of Sussex, DPhil thesis, bound and recorded at the
				British Library.</note></p> 
		  <list> 
			 <item>The reasons why many other asylum seekers are keen to come to
				the UK are also relevant for Algerians; family [for Algerians this is a growing
				consideration], the English language, the ease of finding work.</item> 
			 <item>The perception that Algerians will not be the focus of the same
				degree of racism that occurs in France. Many individuals have stated that this
				is not because Britain is not a racist country [they believed it is, in a
				different way], it's just that Algerians form a sufficiently small group to
				escape targeting.</item> 
			 <item>The desire to get to the USA. The UK is sometimes seen as a
				bridge to the USA due to the perceived cultural links between the countries and
				the possibility of learning English in preparation.</item> 
			 <item>Concerns about the close relationship between the French and
				Algerian governments and the effects this could have on their position in
				France.</item> 
		  </list></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_08"> 
		  <body><head>Resources</head> 
		  <p>This section contains references for useful resources on this
			 population. If you would like to suggest a resource to be included in the list,
			 please contact 
			 <xref url="icar@kcl.ac.uk" rend="email">icar@kcl.ac.uk</xref>.</p><div><head>Publications</head> 
		  <listBibl rend="padding"> 
			 <bibl><name>Adamson, K.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 
				<title>Algeria: a study in competing ideologies</title>. London:
				Casswell</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Addi, L.</name> [<date>1996</date>] 'Réflexion politique
				sur la tragédie algérienne', 
				<title>Confluences</title> 20. pp. 43-51</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Addi, L.</name> [<date>1999</date>] 'L'armée, la nation
				et l'Etat en Algérie', 
				<title>Confluences</title> 29, pp. 39-47</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Ait Amara, H.</name>, 
				<name>J. Gallot</name>, 
				<name>B. Mediene</name> and 
				<name>P. Sindic</name> [<date>2000</date>] 
				<title>Algérie, débats pour un issue: Assises pour un nouveau
				  partenariat Algérie, France, Europe, Marseille 27-28 novembre 1998</title>.
				Paris: Publisud.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Allouache, M.</name> [<date>1994</date>] 
				<title>Bab el Oued City 1995</title>. Paris: Le Seuil.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Ben Ali, S.</name> and 
				<name>R. Pottier</name> [<date>1933</date>] 
				<title>La Tente noire, roman saharien</title>. Paris: Les Oeuvres
				Représentatives.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Benyamina, A.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 'Foreign
				interference in the situation in Algeria: The Algerian government's position'. 
				<title>Cambridge Review of International Affairs</title> vol. XI
				no.2, pp.184 - 195.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Bonn, C.</name> [<date>1985</date>] 
				<title>Le Roman Algérien de langue française</title>. Paris:
				Editions L'Harmattan.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><hi rend="bold">Cahiers du Cinema</hi> hors serie fevrier-mars
				[<date>2003</date>] 
				<title>Ou va le cinema Algérien?</title>.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Cimade</name>, 
				<name>LDH</name>, 
				<name>MRAP</name> [<date>1997</date>] 'Les lois en discussion sur
				la nationalité, l'entrée et le séjour des etrangers' 
				<title>Confluences</title> no.24, pp.121-127.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Cimade</name>, 
				<name>LDH</name>, 
				<name>MRAP</name>, 
				<name>USCR</name> [<date>1999</date>] 
				<title>Gross Negligence Dressed up in legalese: restrictive
				  interpretations on 'Agents of Persecution' and their impact on Algerian asylum
				  seekers in Germany and France</title>. Washington: US Committee for
				Refugees.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Collyer, M.</name> [<date>2003</date>] 'Are there
				national borders in cyberspace? Evidence from the Algerian transnational
				community', 
				<title>Geography</title> [forthcoming].</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Collyer, M.</name> [<date>2003</date>] 'Explaining change
				in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the
				UK', 
				<title>Sussex Migration Working Paper</title> 15. Brighton: Sussex
				Centre for Migration Research.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Collyer, M.</name> [<date>2002</date>] 'Explaining change
				in established migration systems: the movement of Algerians to France and the
				UK', DPhil thesis. Brighton: Sussex University.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Creach, X.</name> and 
				<name>Schreiner. C.</name> [<date>1996</date>] 'Regards sur la
				Jurisprudence Française en matière d'agents de persécution', 
				<title>Migrations Société</title> 8[48], pp. 45-56.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Delouvin, P.</name> [<date>2000</date>] 'The Evolution of
				Asylum in France', 
				<title>Journal of Refugee Studies</title> 13[1], pp. 61-73.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Denaud, P.</name> [<date>1997</date>] 
				<title>Le FIS : Sa direction parle…</title> Paris :
				Harmattan.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Djaout, T.</name> [<date>1984</date>] 
				<title>Les chercheurs d'os</title>. Paris: Seuil.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Djaout, T.</name> [<date>1999</date>] 
				<title>Dernier été de la raison</title>. Paris: Seuil.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Djerbal, D.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 'Algerie: La
				Communaute Internationale et les Droits de l'Homme: Entre Soverainete et Droit
				d'Ingerence'. 
				<title>Monde Arabe Maghreb Machrek</title> 162, pp.119-127.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>European Council for Refugees and Exiles [ECRE]</name>
				[<date>1999</date>] 
				<title>Country Report: France</title>. London: ECRE.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>ECRE</name> [<date>2001</date>] 
				<title>Comments from the European Council on Refugees and Exiles on
				  the Proposal for a Council Regulation establishing the criteria and mechanisms
				  for determining the Member State responsible for examining an asylum
				  application lodged in one of the Member States by a third country
				  national</title>. London: ECRE.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>European Commission</name> [<date>2000</date>] 
				<title>Commission Staff Working Paper Revisiting the Dublin
				  Convention SEC</title> [<date>2000</date>] 522.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Foreign and Commonwealth Office</name>
				[<date>1995</date>] 'Algeria since independence', 
				<title>Background Brief</title>.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Foreign and Commonwealth Office</name>
				[<date>1998</date>] 'Conflict in Algeria', 
				<title>Background Brief</title>.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Ghiles, F.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 'L'armée a-t-elle
				une politique économique: chronique de douze années de compromis incertains', 
				<title>Pouvoirs</title> 86, pp. 85-106.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Horne, A.</name> [<date>1996</date>] 
				<title>A Savage war of peace: Algeria 1954-1962</title>. London:
				Papermac.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Khadra, Y.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 
				<title>Les agneaux du seigneur</title>. Paris: Julliard.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Khadra, Y.</name> [<date>1999</date>] A<title> quoi
				  rêvent les loups</title>. Paris: Julliard.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Khelassi, N.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 'La Violence', 
				<title>Pouvoirs</title> 86, pp.107-116</bibl> 
			 <bibl><hi rend="bold"><title>Le Monde</title></hi> 
				<date>6.2.03</date> 'L'Année de quelle Algérie?'</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Martinez, L.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 
				<title>La guerre civile en Algérie</title>. Paris: Karthala.</bibl>
			 
			 <bibl><name>Mellal, A.</name> [<date>2000</date>] 
				<title>Maintenant, Ils peuvent venir</title>. Algiers: éditions
				barzakh.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Muselle, M.S.</name> [<date>2000</date>] 'La situation
				sociale en Algérie', 
				<title>Monde arabe Maghreb Machrek</title> 167, pp. 93-105.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Nagel, C.</name> [<date>2001</date>] 'Hidden minorities
				and the politics of 'race': the case of British Arab activists in London' 
				<title>Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies</title> 27.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Provost, L.</name> [<date>1996</date>] 
				<title>La seconde guerre d'Algérie. Le quidproquo
				  franco-algérien</title>. Paris: Flammarion.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Reporteurs Sans Frontiers</name> [<date>1994</date>] 
				<title>Le Drame Algerien un peuple en otage</title>. Paris : La
				Decouverte.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Roberts, H.</name> [<date>2003</date>] 
				<title>The Battlefield Algeria 1988-2002: Studies in a broken
				  policy</title>. London: Verso.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Rocheron, Y.</name> [<date>2002</date>] 'Paradoxes of
				Hijrah [Exile]: Tales from Algerian Men in Britain' in S. Ouditt [ed.] 
				<title>Displaced persons: Conditions of exile in European
				  culture</title>. Aldershot: Ashgate.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Schade-Poulsen, M.</name> [<date>1999</date>] 
				<title>Men and popular music in Algeria [1999]</title>. Texas:
				University of Texas Press.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Silverstein, P.A.</name> [<date>2000</date>] 'Regimes of
				[un]truth: Conspiracy theory and the transnationalization of the Algerian civil
				war', 
				<title>Middle East Report</title> 214, pp. 6-10.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Souaïdia, H.</name> [<date>2001</date>] 
				<title>La Sale guerre</title>. Paris: La Découverte.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Stora, B.</name> [<date>1991</date>] 
				<title>Histoire de l'Algérie coloniale [1830-1954]</title>. Paris:
				La Découverte.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Stora, B.</name> [<date>1992</date>] 
				<title>Ils Venaient d'Algérie: L'immigration Algérienne en France
				  1912-1992</title>. Paris: Fayard.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Stora, B.</name> [<date>2001</date>] 
				<title>La Guerre invisible: Algérie, années 90</title>. Paris:
				Presses de Sciences Po.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Taheri, A.</name> [<date>1998</date>] 'Entretien avec le
				général X: Algérie: Les grands cimeterres sous la lune'. 
				<title>Politique Internationale</title> 79, pp. 11-32.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>UNHCR</name> [<date>1995</date>] 
				<title>Lignes directrices du HCR concernant l'éligibilité au statut
				  des demandeurs d'asile algériens</title>. Geneva : UNHCR.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>UNHCR</name> [<date>November 2001</date>] 
				<title>Asylum Applications in Industrialised Countries: 1980 -
				  1999</title>. Geneva: UNHCR.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>UNHCR</name> [<date>March 2002</date>] 
				<title>Asylum Trends in Europe, North America. Australia, and New
				  Zealand: 1999 - 2001</title>. Geneva: UNHCR.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>UNHCR</name> [<date>February 2003</date>] 
				<title>Asylum Applications lodged in industrialized countries:
				  Levels and trends 2000-2002</title>, published. Geneva: UNHCR.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Willis, M.</name> [<date>1996</date>] 
				<title>The Islamist Challenge in Algeria</title>. Reading: Ithaca
				Press.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Yacine, K.</name> [<date>1991</date>] 
				<title>Nedjma</title>. Virginia: University Press of
				Virginia.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Yous, N.</name> [<date>2000</date>] 
				<title>Qui a tué a Bentalha? Algérie: chronique d'un massacre
				  annoncé</title>. Paris: La Découverte.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><name>Zolberg, A.R.</name>, 
				<name>Suhrke, A.</name> and 
				<name>Aguayo, S.</name> [<date>1989</date>] 
				<title>Escape from violence: Conflict and the refugee crisis in the
				  developing world</title>. New York, OUP.</bibl> 
		  </listBibl></div><div><head>Legal cases</head> 
		  <list type="simple"> 
			 <item>T. v. Secretary of State for the Home Department [1996] 2 All
				ER 865, [1996] 2 WLR 766 [House of Lords].</item> 
			 <item>R. v. Secretary of State ex parte Adan and Aitsegeur [2000]
				[House of Lords].</item> 
		  </list></div><div><head>Music</head> 
		  <listBibl> 
			 <bibl><author>Nassima</author> 
				<title>Musique andalouse d'Algérie</title> [2003]. Harmonia
				Mundi.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><author>Abdelkader Saadoun</author> 
				<title>Saadia</title> [2000].</bibl> 
			 <bibl><author>Abdel Ali Slimani</author> 
				<title>Espoir</title> [2003]. Harmonia Mundi.</bibl> 
			 <bibl><author>Abdel Ali Slimani</author> 
				<title>Mraya</title> [2000]. Real World.</bibl> 
		  </listBibl></div><div><head>Films</head> 
		  <table rend="special"> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://www.middleeastuk.com/culture/film/Algiers-beirut.htm">Algiers
					 Beirut</xref> [1999]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Merzak Allouache </cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">90 minutes</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://www.arabfilm.com/item/17/">Bab el Oued City</xref> [1994]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Merzak Allouache</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://film.guardian.co.uk/Century_Of_Films/Story/0,4135,345300,00.html">The
					 Battle of Algiers</xref> [1965]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Gillo Pontecorvo</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">136 minutes</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Chronique des années de braise [1975]</cell>
				
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Lakhdar Mohamed Hamina</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://www.warnerbros.fr/movies/chouchou/index_uk.html">Chouchou</xref>
				  [2003]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Merzak Allouache</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Femme Taxi à Sidi Bel-Abbés [2000]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Belkacem Hadjadj</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://movies.yahoo.com/shop?d=hp&amp;cf=prev&amp;id=1808464450">Inch'Allah
					 Dimanche</xref> [2001]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Written and directed by Yamina Benguigui,
				  distributed by Film Movement</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Little Senegal [2000]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Rachid Bouchareb</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">98 minutes</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Memoire d'Immigrés [1997]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Yamina Benguigui</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://www.arabfilm.com/item/110/">Omar Gatlato</xref> [1976]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Merzak Allouache</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">90 minutes</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://www.rlff.com/db_world02/cinema.cgi/films/view_249.htm#pubreview">Rachida</xref>
				  [2002]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Yamina Bachir-Chouikh</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">100 minutes</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://www.arabfilm.com/item/125/">Salut Cousin!</xref> [1996]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Directed by Merzak Allouache </cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">104 minutes</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">La Zerda et les Chants de l'oubli
				  [1978]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Written and directed by 
				  <xref url="http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/djebar.htm" rend="external">Assia Djebar</xref>.</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
			 </row> 
		  </table></div><div><head>Online
			 resources</head><div><head>Historical context</head> 
		  <table rend="special"> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algerian Consulate</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Country profile</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.consalglond.u-net.com/CounrtyProfile.htm">http://www.consalglond.u-net.com/CounrtyProfile.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algeriafocus</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Business orientated news and
				  information</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeriafocus.com">http://www.algeriafocus.com</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algerian National Statistics Office</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.ons.dz/index.htm">http://www.ons.dz/index.htm</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">AlgerieOnline.com</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Short historical overview </cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.rcd-dz.org/index.htm">http://www.rcd-dz.org/index.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Amnesty International</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Reports on Algeria</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://web.amnesty.org/library/eng-dza/index">http://web.amnesty.org/library/eng-dza/index</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Arabji.com</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">List of online Algerian newspapers</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.arabji.com/algeria/Media.htm">http://www.arabji.com/algeria/Media.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Ethnologue</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Languages in Algeria</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.ethnologue.com/show_country.asp?name=Algeria">http://www.ethnologue.com/show_country.asp?name=Algeria</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Global IDP project</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Algeria information menu</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.db.idpproject.org/Sites/IdpProjectDb/idpSurvey.nsf/wCountries/Algeria">http://www.db.idpproject.org/Sites/IdpProjectDb/idpSurvey.nsf/wCountries/Algeria</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Human Rights Watch</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Reports on Algeria</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.hrw.org/mideast/algeria.php">http://www.hrw.org/mideast/algeria.php</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Library of Congress</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Algeria, a country study</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/dztoc.html">http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/dztoc.html</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">US Committee for Refugees</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Information by country: Algeria</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.refugees.org/world/countryrpt/africa/2002/algeria.cfm">http://www.refugees.org/world/countryrpt/africa/2002/algeria.cfm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
		  </table></div><div><head>Algerian pressure groups/political
			 parties</head> 
		  <table rend="special"> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algeria interface</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Excellent middle of the road general news
				  source [in English and French].</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeria-interface.com/">http://www.algeria-interface.com/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algeria Watch</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Focusing on highlighting problems with the
				  Algerian regime [in French and German].</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeria-watch.org/francais.htm">http://www.algeria-watch.org/francais.htm</xref>;
				  
				  <xref url="http://www.kabyle.com/">http://www.kabyle.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algeriens du Monde</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">French based development focused/solidarity
				  organisation [in French].</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeriensdumonde.org/">http://www.algeriensdumonde.org/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Arabji.com</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Links guide to directory or information about
				  Algeria [in English and Arabic].</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.arabji.com/algeria/">http://www.arabji.com/algeria/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Front Islamique du Salut [FIS]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.fis-info.net/index.php">http://www.fis-info.net/index.php</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Hijra International Online</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl">http://home.worldcom.ch/~hijra/</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Kabyle.com</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Berber site covering politics, history and
				  culture [in English and Tamaziyt].</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.kabyle.com/">http://www.kabyle.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">MAOL [Mouvement Algerien des Officiers
				  Libres]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.anp.org/">http://www.anp.org/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Planet DZ</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Range of listings, mostly focused on Paris
				  and Algiers but details on the UK scene where appropriate [in French].</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.planet-dz.com/">http://www.planet-dz.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">POUR!</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Almost daily review of Algerian press and
				  large dossier on Islamist organisations in Europe. Strongly
				  anti-Islamist.</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://pourinfo.ouvaton.org/go.htm">http://pourinfo.ouvaton.org/go.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Rachda [Rassemblement contre la hogra et
				  pour les droits des algeriennes]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Women's pressure group [in French, Spanish
				  and Italian].</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.nodo50.org/mujeresred/RACHDA.html">http://www.nodo50.org/mujeresred/RACHDA.html</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Rassemblement pour la Culture et la
				  Democratie [RCD]</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Home site of this Berber focused political
				  party.</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.rcd-algerie.org/">http://www.rcd-algerie.org/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
		  </table></div><div><head>Legal issues</head> 
		  <table TEIform="linkBib" rend="linkbib"> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="linkTitle"><bibl><author>Danish Refugee
						Council</author> [2001] 
					 <title>Analysis of the Dublin Convention</title></bibl></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.flygtning.dk/publikationer/rapporter/dublin">http://www.flygtning.dk/publikationer/rapporter/dublin</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
		  </table></div><div><head>Statistics</head> 
		  <table rend="special"> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algerian National Statistics Office</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.ons.dz/index.htm">http://www.ons.dz/index.htm</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Home Office</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">UK asylum statistics</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration1.html">http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/immigration1.html</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">UNHCR</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Asylum statistics</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.unhcr.ch">http://www.unhcr.ch</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
		  </table></div><div><head>Cultural background</head> 
		  <table rend="special"> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Abdelkader Saadoun</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Musician's website</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.saadoun.com/">http://www.saadoun.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algeriades.com</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Reviews of recently published Algerian
				  literature [in French]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeriades.com/news/sommaire_themes.php3?id_mot=4">http://www.algeriades.com/news/sommaire_themes.php3?id_mot=4</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Algeriades.com</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Details of Algerian films</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeriades.com/news/sommaire_themes.php3?id_mot=6">http://www.algeriades.com/news/sommaire_themes.php3?id_mot=6</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">DZ Foot</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Home site of the Algerian national football
				  team</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.dzfoot.com/fiches/fiche.php?fiche_id=134">http://www.dzfoot.com/fiches/fiche.php?fiche_id=134</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Emusic</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Downloadable MP3s on Middle Eastern
				  music</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.emusic.com/genres_popular/390/">http://www.emusic.com/genres_popular/390/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Exiled Writers Ink</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.exiledwriters.co.uk/index.shtml">http://www.exiledwriters.co.uk/index.shtml</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">French Year of Algeria [2003] website</cell>
				
				<cell role="itemDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.djazair2003.org/?Une_Annee_de_l_Algerie_en_France">http://www.djazair2003.org/?Une_Annee_de_l_Algerie_en_France</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Introduction to the literature of the
				  Maghreb</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Site providing an overview of Algerian
				  literature</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/literature-intro.htm">http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/literature-intro.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Introduction to raï music</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Glossary on raï, extracts from Schade-Poulsen
				  [1999]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://inic.utexas.edu/menic/rai/">http://inic.utexas.edu/menic/rai/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Littératures du Maghreb</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">French site on Algerian literature</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.limag.com">http://www.limag.com</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">Maghrebi literature in translation</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Details of English translations</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/In_English_Translation/index.htm">http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/In_English_Translation/index.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle">V.Tuner</cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Lists range of Algerian radio stations</cell>
				
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.vtuner.com/vtunerweb/static/staticAlgeriaoverall1.html ">http://www.vtuner.com/vtunerweb/static/staticAlgeriaoverall1.html
					 </xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="itemTitle"><xref url="http://www.maroc.net/">www.Maroc.net</xref></cell> 
				<cell role="itemDesc">Information on Algerian music</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.maroc.net/maghreb_music/algeria.htm">http://www.maroc.net/maghreb_music/algeria.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
		  </table></div></div> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_09"> 
		  <body><head>Projects and initiatives</head> 
		  <p>There is currently no ongoing publicly available research on the
			 Algerian community in the UK nor any projects relating to service provision or
			 integration that are solely aimed at the Algerian community.</p> 
		  </body> 
		</text> 
		<text id="p4_ng003_10"> 
		  <body><head>Links and contacts</head> 
		   
		  <table rend="projList"> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Abdelkader Saadoun</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Musician's website</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.saadoun.com/">http://www.saadoun.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algeriades.com</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Details of Algerian cultural events and
				  activities</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeriades.com">http://www.algeriades.com</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algeriafocus</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Business orientated news and
				  information</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeriafocus.com">http://www.algeriafocus.com</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algeria interface</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Excellent middle of the road general news
				  source [in English and French]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeria-interface.com/">http://www.algeria-interface.com/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algerian Consulate</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.consalglond.u-net.com/Embassy.htm">http://www.consalglond.u-net.com/Embassy.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algerian National Statistics Office</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.ons.dz/index.htm">http://www.ons.dz/index.htm</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algerian Refugee Council UK</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl">No contact available for the instant.</cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algeria Watch</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Focusing on highlighting problems with the
				  Algerian regime [in French and German]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeria-watch.org/francais.htm">http://www.algeria-watch.org/francais.htm</xref>;
				  
				  <xref url="http://www.kabyle.com/">http://www.kabyle.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Algeriens du Monde</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">French based development focused/solidarity
				  organisation [in French]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.algeriensdumonde.org/">http://www.algeriensdumonde.org/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">AlgerieOnline.com</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.rcd-dz.org/index.htm">http://www.rcd-dz.org/index.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Arabji.com, Algerian section</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.arabji.com/algeria/index.htm">http://www.arabji.com/algeria/index.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">DZ Foot</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Home site of the Algerian national football
				  team</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.dzfoot.com/fiches/fiche.php?fiche_id=134">http://www.dzfoot.com/fiches/fiche.php?fiche_id=134</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">French Year of Algeria [2003] website</cell>
				
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.djazair2003.org/?Une_Annee_de_l_Algerie_en_France">http://www.djazair2003.org/?Une_Annee_de_l_Algerie_en_France</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Front Islamique du Salut [FIS]</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.fis-info.net/index.php">http://www.fis-info.net/index.php</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Hijra International Online</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://home.worldcom.ch/~hijra/">http://home.worldcom.ch/~hijra/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Introduction to the literature of the
				  Maghreb</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Site providing an overview of Algerian
				  literature</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/literature-intro.htm">http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/literature-intro.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Introduction to raï music</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Glossary on raï, extracts from Schade-Poulsen
				  [1999]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://inic.utexas.edu/menic/rai/">http://inic.utexas.edu/menic/rai/</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Kabyle.com</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Berber site covering politics, history and
				  culture [in English and Tamaziyt]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.kabyle.com/">http://www.kabyle.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Littératures du Maghreb</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">French site on Algerian literature</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.limag.com">http://www.limag.com</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Maghrebi literature in translation</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Details of English translations</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/In_English_Translation/index.htm">http://goa.cet.middlebury.edu/mtoler/In_English_Translation/index.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">MAOL [Mouvement Algerien des Officiers
				  Libres]</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc"></cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.anp.org/">http://www.anp.org/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Planet DZ</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Range of listings, mostly focused on Paris
				  and Algiers but details on the UK scene where appropriate [in French]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.planet-dz.com/">http://www.planet-dz.com/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">POUR!</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Almost daily review of Algerian press and
				  large dossier on Islamist organisations in Europe. Strongly
				  anti-Islamist.</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://pourinfo.ouvaton.org/go.htm">http://pourinfo.ouvaton.org/go.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Rachda [Rassemblement contre la hogra et
				  pour les droits des algeriennes]</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Women's pressure group [in French, Spanish
				  and Italian]</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.nodo50.org/mujeresred/RACHDA.html">http://www.nodo50.org/mujeresred/RACHDA.html</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Rassemblement pour la Culture et la
				  Democratie [RCD]</cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Home site of this Berber focused political
				  party</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.rcd-algerie.org/">http://www.rcd-algerie.org/</xref></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle">Society for Algerian Studies [affiliated to
				  the Centre for Near and Middle Eastern Studies] </cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Contact John King [president], email 
				  <xref rend="email" url="Contact John King (president), email coolpressjk@hotmail.com">coolpressjk@hotmail.com</xref></cell>
				
				<cell role="linkUrl"></cell> 
			 </row> 
			 <row> 
				<cell role="projTitle"><xref url="http://www.Maroc.net">www.Maroc.net</xref></cell> 
				<cell role="projDesc">Information on Algerian music</cell> 
				<cell role="linkUrl"><xref url="http://www.maroc.net/maghreb_music/algeria.htm">http://www.maroc.net/maghreb_music/algeria.htm</xref></cell>
				
			 </row> 
		  </table></body> 
		</text> 
	 </group> 
  </text> 
</TEI.2>
