<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="glossary01" TEIform="TEI.2">
    <teiHeader status="new" TEIform="teiHeader" type="text">
        <fileDesc TEIform="fileDesc">
            <titleStmt TEIform="titleStmt">
                <title TEIform="title">Glossary</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt TEIform="publicationStmt">
                <publisher TEIform="publisher">Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address TEIform="address">
        <addrLine TEIform="addrLine">Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine TEIform="addrLine">http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
      </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc TEIform="sourceDesc" default="NO">
                <p TEIform="p"/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc TEIform="encodingDesc">
            <p TEIform="p">Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc TEIform="revisionDesc">
            <change TEIform="change">
                <date TEIform="date">2006-01-19</date>
                <respStmt TEIform="respStmt">
                    <name TEIform="name">Lorna G</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item TEIform="item">inserted bold</item>
            </change>
            <change TEIform="change">
                <date TEIform="date">2006-01-17</date>
                <respStmt TEIform="respStmt">
                    <name TEIform="name">Lorna G</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item TEIform="item">inserted SD's glossary</item>
            </change>
            <change TEIform="change">
                <date TEIform="date">2005-12-06</date>
                <respStmt TEIform="respStmt">
                    <name TEIform="name">Lorna G</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item TEIform="item">updated text</item>
            </change>
            <change TEIform="change">
                <date TEIform="date">2005-12-05</date>
                <respStmt TEIform="respStmt">
                    <name TEIform="name">Lorna G</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item TEIform="item">created page</item>
            </change>

        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text TEIform="text">
        <body TEIform="body">


            <head TEIform="head">Glossary</head>

            <p TEIform="p">
                <list type="gloss" TEIform="list">
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e1">Access Grid</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">an Advanced Collaborative Environment that brings people and resources together. It constitutes a
                            global network of 3400 locations, or Access Grid nodes, which provide large-screen multimedia information digitization and
                            exchange in real time. The aim of the Access Grid is to provide an effective environment for remote group-to-group
                            collaborations by providing a sense of presence that approaches that experienced during face-to-face meetings. Access Grid
                            is often described at the next generation of videoconferencing, but whereas videoconferencing can deliver only one-to-one
                            conversations, Access Grid can facilitate a conversation between many nodes at the same time.<xref
                                url="http://www.accessgrid.org" to="DITTO" type="external" from="ROOT" targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">
                                http://www.accessgrid.org</xref></gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e2">Access Grid Node</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the physical location of Access Grid technology, from which user groups conduct meetings Analysis The
                            extraction of information/knowledge/meaning from a resource.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e3">Collaborative Technology</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">see <ref target="e26" targOrder="U" TEIform="ref">Grid</ref>.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e4">Computational Grid </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the sharing of processing power via a network of computers. This is only occasionally relevant to the
                            Arts and Humanities, but there are some potential uses.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e5">Cyberinfrastructure</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">see Virtual Research Environment.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e6">Data</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the primary resource produced directly by the research process. It may or may not be readable by a
                            computer. Data that is not machine-readable can be made so by using digitisation. By a process of analysis, data in any
                            form can be developed into information.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e7">Data Grid</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">data grid provides the tools for large-scale data management and sharing, and will be a vital means of
                            meeting the present grand challenge to Arts and Humanities e-Science: how to locate, access and integrate the content of
                            resources that embrace text, still and moving images and sound, are highly distributed, of variable quality, encoded and
                            described using different standards, and often incomplete, fuzzy, and complex.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e8">Data Modelling</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the means by which data objects (e.g. records, images, parts of a text) can be organised to form a
                            coherent entity. A common example of a data model is the database.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e9">Database </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a collection or grouping of similar or related data, usually assembled as a matter of record, or for
                            research. Also called a dataset.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e10">Digital Library</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a collection of archive materials on any subject converted to machine-readable format for preservation
                            or to provide electronic access. Also library materials produced in electronic formats, including e-zines, e-journals,
                            e-books, reference works published online and on CD-ROM, bibliographic databases, and other Web-based resources.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e11">Digital Preservation</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the active process of maintaining, in a condition suitable for use or reuse, digital data, thus
                            offsetting the dangers caused to digital material by changing file formats, deteriorating media (e.g. CDs, floppy discs)
                            and changing software and hardware environments. For outputs created via AHRC funding, this role is carried out by the
                                <xref url="http://ahds.ac.uk" to="DITTO" type="external" from="ROOT" targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">Arts and Humanities
                                Data Service</xref>.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e12">Digital Resource</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a general term to describe any programme, application, database etc which can be used to assist in
                            research and teaching; or any element of the physical infrastructure which enables such resolution, usage or
                        sharing.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e13">Digitisation/Data Capture</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">digitisation can refer to the general process of creating a digital resource, or be a synonym for data
                            capture, the more precise procedure of creating digital objects from analogue data or real-world objects. See the AHDS
                            paper <xref url="http://ahds.ac.uk/creating/information-papers/creating-introduction/" to="DITTO" type="external"
                                from="ROOT" targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">Introduction to Creating Digital Resources</xref>.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e14">Dissemination</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the presentation and dissemination/communication of the results of a research project. Dissemination
                            via the internet is distinct from e-publication, in that it does not imply the same degree of editorial control and/or
                            peer-review.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e15">E</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">anything in electronic, or more exactly in digital form: stored for use on a computer in electronic
                            bits, conventionally represented as the digits 0 or 1 see also digitisation). The opposite of digital is analogue: a music
                            CD is digital, a cassette tape is analogue.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e16">E-Book</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">in the broadest sense, any books published in digital form. Commonly used for digital versions of
                            printed books in formats that allow reading and browsing, but not manipulation or analysisfor reading, for instance, on a
                            Pocket PC. But there are also more innovative e-books that make much more powerful use of digital resources, by combining
                            text with images (moving or still) and/or sound in multi-media systems. These may be the e-books of the future.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e17">E-Edition</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a particularly powerful application of digital technology to replace printed critical editions of
                            primary texts. E-editions can use hyperlinks to connect the text of a critical edition with images and transcriptions of
                            the printed books or manuscripts it is based on, all within a single system.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e18">E-Journal </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a common form of e-publication. Currently a major subject of debate, since they can offer an
                            alternative to high-cost conventionally published scientific journals. Many e-journals are charged for by commercial
                            publishers at subscription rates similar to their printed equivalents, or ‘bundled’ under expensive licensing arrangements
                            providing access to entire journal collections. But some e-journals are freely available on open access, the cost of
                            production being met by the producer, sometimes with, sometimes without, contributions from authors. There is now a strong
                            movement in favour of shifting payment for e-journals from the reader (or usually, the library) to the author (or
                            probably, the author's institution or grant-awarder), particularly in the sciences. There are arguments for and against
                            this: the advantages of free access to readers are obvious, but the commercial publishing market has played a major role
                            in journal development, there are substantial overseas earnings, learned societies have benefited significantly from
                            journal royalties, and the prospects of authors being charged for publications raises all sorts of problems, especially in
                            the arts and humanities.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e19">E-Monograph</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">some presses are making printed monographs available for purchase or subscription in digital form. As a
                            cheaper alternative for the publication of highly specialized research, in particular, this clearly merits further
                            development. But again, from an academic/RAE point of view it is important to ensure adequate processes of refereeing and
                            editorial control. There is much more to be done in this respect.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e20">E-Learning</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the use of digital resources for teaching and learning: currently a major agenda item for the DfES and
                            HEFCE. Considerable resources were recently put into the ill-fated UK e-University, which aimed to generate overseas
                            earnings through distance learning. The current emphasis is on ‘mixed-mode’ e-leaning, combining the use of digital
                            resources with direct-contact teaching. Universities now make extensive use of Virtual Learning Environments (VLEs),
                            software systems (e.g. Blackboard) for managing and delivering digital resources for teaching and learning. A VLE can in
                            turn be part of a Managed Learning Environment (MLE), a larger-scale system that makes all the datasets relevant to a
                            student’s learning process seamlessly accessible through a single portal: student records and registration, information on
                            university programmes and facilities, library catalogues, etc., as well as the VLE. There are interesting potential
                            overlaps between the development of MLEs and Virtual Research Environments.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e21">E-Publication</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">in the broadest sense, anything made public in digital form. Thus a personal web page or a [we]blog
                            could count as an e-publication. However, since ‘publication’ usually implies a process of editorial quality control,
                            often including peer-review, the term e-publication is probably best reserved for materials that can lay claim to this. In
                            the context of the current debate, ‘e-publications’ usually refers to digital versions of conventional forms of printed
                            output: e-journals, e-monographs, etc.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e22">E-Science</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">e-Science involves developing shared access to distributed computational resources (both
                            high-performance computing and large data collections), which enables bigger, better and different research to take place.
                            This is also known as grid computing. E-Science encourages multidisciplinary research by distributed, collaborative
                            research teams. Under the broader umbrella of e-research, e-Science is capable of making substantial differences to
                            research within the Arts and Humanities. Click <xref url="http://www.ahrc.ac.uk/e-science." to="DITTO" type="external"
                                from="ROOT" targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">here</xref> for further information about the AHRC's e-science
                        initiative.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e23">E-Science Core Programme</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the inter-Research Council body established in 2000 to develop lead the national agenda for E-Science
                            in the UK. Click <xref url="http://www.rcuk.ac.uk/escience" to="DITTO" type="external" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"
                                TEIform="xref">here</xref>.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e24">E-Theses </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">electronic versions of doctoral and masters theses, increasingly made available by institutions through
                            institutional repositories or other Open Archives.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e25">Geographical Information Systems (GIS)</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">GIS allows for the analysis and visualisation of data with a spatial context. Click <xref
                                url="http://ads.ahds.ac.uk/project/goodguides/gis/index.html." to="DITTO" type="external" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"
                                TEIform="xref">here</xref> for further information.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e26">Grid (Grid computing)</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">see also Computational Grid, Data Grid and Access Grid. The computing infrastructure for e-Science.
                            Grids provides a way of utilising computing power that may be distributed across the internet. The term originally derives
                            from the electricity grid, where you access power from a socket without knowing where or by whom it is generated.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e27">ICT</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">Information and Communication Technology.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e28">Metadata</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">most commonly described as “data about data”. This is information that describes key information about
                            a digital object or collection of digital objects, including information on the creator, time and date of creation, rights
                            issues, accessing history etc. There are many different standards for metadata, and data creators can choose and even
                            amend various standards according to whether they are describing images, texts, webpages, databases etc. A common baseline
                            standard is Dublin Core developed and maintained by the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative (DCMI). The AHDS provides an
                            article on Metadata for your Digital Resource. Services such as the Humbul Humanities Hub or Artifact use Dublin Core to
                            describe Web sites.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e29">Middleware </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">software which connects two applications online via a network: it is sometimes referred to informally
                            as “plumbing”. Middleware can be respective elements of two applications which allow connectivity between them, or a third
                            piece of software which connects two separate products. It must not therefore be confused with the Import/Export
                            facilities available in many packages: these merely deal with the translation and transference of data from one place to
                            another, not the combining or linking of the applications themselves.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e30">Open Access</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">commonly used to refer to digital objects (e.g. research outputs, images, finding aids, learning
                            objects), which have been made freely available by an institution or organisation through an Open Access Archive.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e31">Open Access Archive</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">an online service or repository, which provides Open Access to digital objects or metadata.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e32">Open Source Software</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">software applications which are distributed together with the underlying programming code ("source
                            code") and which may be freely copied, reused, and modified according to the terms of an Open Source Software licence.
                            Most Open Source Software is distributed free of charge though the concept of 'free' when applied to Open Source Software
                            actually refers to the freedoms protected within an Open Source Software licence. The JISC-funded OSS Watch provides
                            unbiased advice and guidance about free and open source software for UK higher education.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e33">Portal </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a portal is an online service which brings together content from diverse distributed resources using
                            functionality such as cross searching, linking and aggregation, newsfeeds, and alerting services. Generally a portal
                            allows for a degree of personalisation of what content and services are available and presents information via a Web site.
                            Technically, portals can comprise frameworks and portlets. The latter have the potential to be re-presented in other
                            online services, for example, an institutional portal or virtual learning environment. The success of any portal depends
                            on both delivering a service from the user's own preferred starting point and ensuring the functionality and content
                            conforms to open standards.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e34">Preservation </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">see Digital Preservation.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e35">Semantic Web</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">an extension to the World Wide Web which contains “Machine Understandable” data. At its most basic
                            level, this in information which allows computers, not just human beings, to access and navigate the internet.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e36">Shared Whiteboards</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">these interactive, collaborative tools allow people to share text and drawings over the Internet on a
                            shared drawing surface, like a normal white or blackboard, except that the users may not be in the same physical location.
                            Typical shared whiteboards are designed for informal conversation, but they may also serve structured communications or
                            more sophisticated drawing tasks, such as collaborative graphic design, publishing or engineering applications. Click
                                <xref url="http://www.ncess.ac.uk/resources/tutorials/fasttrack/resources/q0.html" to="DITTO" type="external"
                                from="ROOT" targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">here</xref> for an example of a Shared Whiteboard. </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e37">Structuring and Enhancement</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">the organisation and integration of the data captured from one or various sources into a uniform
                            conceptual framework. This would typically include the design of the resource's information structure/data model as well
                            as the normalisation, standardisation and enhancement of its data.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e38">Taxonomy of Computational Methods</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a schema developed by the Arts and Humanities Data Service for classifying ICT methods in the Arts and
                            Humanities. Click <xref url="http://ahds.ac.uk/about/projects/documents/pmdb_taxonomy_v1_3_1.pdf" to="DITTO"
                                type="external" from="ROOT" targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">here</xref> for further details.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e39">Videoconferencing</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a collection of technologies that integrate video with audio and to some extent, data sharing, to
                            enable communication and meetings between participants at physically separated sites. Either IP or ISDN networks are used
                            to carry the audio and video streams with participants having a camera(s), microphone(s) and speakers. The Access Grid
                            provides a more advanced form of videoconferencing, using better quality display and integrating other forms of data
                            sharing, helping to provide a more immersive experience for participants. Click <xref
                                url="http://www.ncess.ac.uk/resources//tutorials/fasttrack/resources/q0.html" to="DITTO" type="external" from="ROOT"
                                targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">here</xref> for further information.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e40">Virtual Communities </term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">groups of people joined by using the same electronic conferencing system.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e41">Virtual Organisations</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">groups which collaborate within an e-Science research activity, often within a grid computing
                            environment.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e42">Virtual Reality</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">Virtual Reality 'worlds' are computer-based three-dimensional environments. They represent real-world
                            or conceptual environments that can be navigated through, interacted with and updated in real-time.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item TEIform="item">
                        <label TEIform="label">
                            <term id="e43">Virtual Research Environment (VRE)</term>
                        </label>
                        <gloss TEIform="gloss">a coherent set of online services, tools, systems or processes interoperating to facilitate or enhance
                            the research lifecycle within and beyond institutional boundaries. A VRE may be institutional or subject-specific. Four
                            VRE demonstrator projects funded by the JISC are located in the Arts and Humanities domains. Click<xref
                                url="http://www.ahrcict.rdg.ac.uk/vre" to="DITTO" type="external" from="ROOT" targOrder="U" TEIform="xref">
                            here</xref> for further information.</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
