<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p6">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of the project</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>


        <body>
            <div>

                <head>Editorial Decisions</head>


                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> attempts to represent its serials in their own terms:
                    in other words, to edit them in digital form in ways that maintain their links
                    with nineteenth-century print culture. In practice, this was not
                    straightforward, as conflicts arose between our desire not to misrepresent the
                    complexities of the source material and the technical demands of another medium:
                    the digital. Below are a number of short accounts of editorial decisions that
                    attempt to reconcile the forms of the source material with the necessity of
                    imposing order upon them for digitization.</p>

                <div id="rat">
                    <head>Editorial Rationale</head>

                    <p>Serials are not well-ordered objects from which to begin a digitization
                        project. The historical production and preservation of serials means that it
                        is difficult to identify one distinct manifestation of their form. Serials
                        consist of articles, often themselves consisting of different types of print
                        and images [internal link], gathered into departments, published in issues,
                        and often bound in volumes [internal link]. There is a tendency to consider
                        volumes [internal link] as discrete uniform objects that gather together
                        diverse content. However, as many critics have noted, the process of binding
                        individual issues, plus any front or end matter [internal link] that might
                        also be issued, involved a considerable transformation. Part of this was the
                        common practice of stripping out matter that pertains to the selling of
                        individual issues, most notoriously advertisements [internal link], but also
                        multiple editions [internal link], supplements [internal link], and wrappers
                        [internal link]. Equally, just as a volume is something different than a
                        combination of the year’s issues, so issues are more than a series of
                        articles. Items in the periodical and newspaper press are remarkably
                        diverse, including advertisements, filler, title pages and imprints,
                        headings and signatures, news, leaders, correspondence, literature, reviews,
                        essays, science, and tables. Visual material might comprise the cover
                        design, mastheads, illustrations, graphic devices such as ornaments, rules,
                        or space, typography, and layout. Not only are they diverse in terms of
                        their genre, but their significance is also affected by where in the issue
                        they appear and how they are presented on the page. Editors were keenly
                        aware of how different constituents of an issue related to each other, and
                        considered both how an item should look and where it should appear. </p>
                    <p>Serial texts become problematic when one attempts to identify them as a
                        single object, rather than texts that differ remarkably between titles and
                        that change over time. It is the seriality of these texts that is often
                        overlooked, even though it is this that determines both the form of
                        individual issues and the various ways in which individual issues were
                        archived by institutions such as libraries, as well as readers themselves.
                        Our methodology responded to this by considering serials as processes: as
                        objects with histories that meant that they did not always look like the
                        forms in which they have survived into the present. When deciding on how to
                        edit them – i.e. when considering what aspects of their text was important –
                        we tried to ensure that we maintained those parts of the journal that
                        gesture towards its prior forms. When you browse ncse, you will see that we
                        have found a place for multiple editions, advertisements, and supplements;
                        departments, issues and volumes. Although we often had to intervene in order
                        to impose a degree of order onto the material for its translation into a new
                        medium, we edited it with a view to permitting the periodicals and
                        newspapers to tell their own histories as far as possible.</p>
                </div>

                <div id="clu">
                    <head>Choice of the Cluster</head>
                    <p>For details about why these six titles were chosen, click here [link to
                        05_01_choice]</p>
                </div>

                <div id="mul">
                    <head>Multiple editions</head>
                    <p>When we first began to explore the state of the British Library holdings of
                        our six titles, we were pleased to find that the librarians had preserved
                        more than one edition of each issue of two of our weeklies, the <title>
                            <xref type="internal" from="p2_2">Northern Star</xref>
                        </title> and the <title>
                            <xref type="internal" from="p2_3">Leader</xref>
                        </title>. The presence of these multiples created editorial challenges: to
                        include them would expand the edition considerably; to exclude them would
                        involve a complex process of pruning that would necessarily have to nominate
                        one edition instead of another to represent that week’s issue. In accordance
                        with the responsibility we felt to represent the serials as serials – i.e.
                        as part of a broader print culture – we felt that excluding the multiples
                        would misrepresent the production of the titles. We decided to keep them in.
                        For more about our decisions regarding multiples, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_6">here</xref>.</p>
                </div>
               
                <div id="num"><head>Page numbering</head>
                <p>The pages that you browse in <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> are obtained from pdf documents that
                    correspond to individual issues. To make these pdf documents, we had to ‘bind’
                    together individual page images that were filmed from either microfilm or the
                    hard copy itself. Each stage in this process interposed its own way of recording
                    the order in which pages should appear: the page images (tiffs) had their own
                    numbers that corresponded to the number of frames created from either a reel or
                    bound volume; and the pdf documents labelled each page in an issue, then
                    restarted the sequence for the next. This meant that in order for the page
                    numbers in the edition to correspond to those printed on the pages, they would
                    have to be inputted as data rather than being produced as part of the production
                    process. This represented a huge task as every single one of our c100,000 pages
                    would have to have page number data entered upon it. Although it was common
                    practice for periodicals to number their pages continuously throughout a volume
                    (so that, for instance, vol. 1. no. 1 of the <title>Leader </title>is pp. 1-24 and
                    vol. 1 no. 2 is pp. 25-48 ) this was not the case for newspapers such as the
                        <title>Northern Star</title>, which tended to number each issue separately
                    (i.e. vol. 1. no. 1 is pp. 1-8 and vol. 1. no. 2 is also pp. 1-8). This meant
                    that although we had to be careful, it was possible – more or less – to enter
                    page numbers automatically as a sequence. However, this was complicated by the
                    nineteenth-century practice of paginating front and end matter, supplements, and
                    advertising wrappers separately; and of course the presence of multiple editions
                    meant that there would be two or more of every page for certain titles. Our
                    policy here was to follow the page numbers printed upon the pages themselves.
                    This way we followed the way in which the journals represented their contents to
                    their readers.</p>
                <p>This policy presented two interesting problems. The first was that many of the
                    pages simply were not paginated. The digitisation medium required us to enter a
                    value in order to show that this was the case (and not simply a page that we had
                    missed out) and so we decided to use ‘unpag’ to indicate a page that had no page
                    number. In this way we ensured that navigation within the edition still worked
                    (the system knows which ‘unpag’ page is which and where it goes) while
                    demonstrating to our users the way in which the pages were originally paginated.
                    The second problem was what to do when the journals printed a page number that
                    appeared to be incorrect. This was a difficult question as our overall policy
                    meant that we tended to privilege the actual state of the material, but leaving
                    incorrect numbers might be confusing for our users. Practical considerations
                    finally persuaded us to keep the incorrect page numbers in the edition. We were
                    concerned about users who would come to the edition to look up a reference from
                    another source that referred to a page number that we had altered. We also
                    thought it might be confusing to go to a page that was labelled differently on
                    the page to how it was labelled within the edition. The most important
                    consideration, however, was that if we were to correct what appeared to be an
                    incorrect pagination sequence, we would have to trust that the journal itself
                    eventually reverted to what we thought was the correct sequence. As this was not
                    always the case, with incorrect page sequences sometimes continuing until the
                    end of a volume, we felt we had no choice than to follow the page numbers
                    printed on the journal.</p></div>
                
                <div id="str"><head>Structure of the Edition</head>
                <p>In the early stages of the project we attempted to map all the types of data that
                    we felt were important and how they related to each other. Needless to say, this
                    resulted in an incredibly complex map, which you can download here [link to
                    data_map.pdf]. While we were undertook this exercise, we were also working with
                    Olive Software to investigate the degree of accuracy with which a computer
                    program could identify units of content and their relationship according to a
                    set of predefined rules. Although the system had some success distinguishing
                    between items, we found that the typographic information in the original that
                    dictated what an item was (and so how it related to other items) was not
                    distinct enough and/or not consistent enough to be reliably detected by
                    automatic processing. Considering both of these exercises, we decided to adopt a
                    simple structure for ncse:</p>
                <p>Edition &gt; title &gt; volume &gt; issue &gt; department
                    &gt; item</p>
                <p>Not only was this an easy structure to model, but it was flexible enough to
                    contain all the different types of content within ncse. Rather than ask the
                    system to distinguish between types of content, we simply wrote rules that asked
                    it to distinguish between items on a page. We included some rules to identify
                    how to recognize an item that signalled a change in department, but these were
                    largely for the guidance of human editors who checked the output. These sets of
                    rules were called segmentation policies [internal link]. For a definition of our
                    terminology, click here [link to 05_03_terminology].</p></div>
                
                
                <div id="dep"><head>Departments / Items</head>
                <p>The organization of articles into sections that we call departments [link to
                    05_03_terminology] was common across nineteenth-century newspapers and
                    magazines. As an important structural demarcation, we felt we had to encode this
                    into the edition and, according to our editorial principles, it had to be done
                    according to each title’s own categories. Olive Software’s applications
                    supported a ‘Table of Components’ that would list each article in a journal and
                    could also group them into sections. However, in order to do this, we would have
                    to segment a page in a way that would identify whole articles. This was
                    certainly possible but a page of a periodical or newspaper is not constituted
                    solely by the articles upon it: rather, it contains a range of items including
                    headlines, mastheads, lists of contents, advertisements, rules etc. Isolating
                    articles from this miscellaneous collection of content would privilege one type
                    of material above another. Instead, we nominated <title>items </title>[link to
                    05_03_terminology] as our basic unit within the edition, and defined articles as
                    one type of item amongst others. A department then would be a collection of
                    items, most of which would be articles, but might also be headlines,
                    advertisements, or other types of content.</p>
                <p>We investigated the potential for software to identify different items on a page
                    with a view to automating as much of the classification and subsequent
                    structuring into a hierarchy as possible. However, although some of these
                    experiments were encouraging, they demanded a great deal of time from all
                    involved. Not only was programming made difficult by the way the titles changed
                    over time, but we had to carefully scope each issue before running the
                    programmes and then review the results. Once we made the decision to keep
                    multiple editions within the edition, we were committed to processing c100,000
                    pages (although to see a report on our proposed alternative – the core – click
                    here [link to 05_09_core]). We had the greatest success setting parameters that
                    would distinguish between every item on the page. This included all the
                    articles, whatever their content, as well as things like advertisements,
                    mastheads, filler, publisher’s imprints, etc… We recognized that some users
                    would not find a ‘Table of Components’ that contained all this diverse material
                    very useful and, as some issues contained over two hundred items, such a table
                    would be too long to navigate easily. In addition, early pilots of the Olive
                    application populated the Table of Components from the OCR transcript that was
                    produced during processing. Because of the quality of the surviving newsprint,
                    we knew our OCR transcript would be too inaccurate to display in an uncorrected
                    form and, as we were dealing with 100,000 pages, we would not have time to
                    undertake its correction. Instead, we decided to restrict the Table of
                    Components to department level, and populate it with images of department
                    headers rather than text strings from the OCR transcript. This also suited one
                    of our primary aims in the edition, to foreground the structure of serials and
                    not only what is normally defined as their ‘contents’. </p>
                <p>The distinction between items and departments in <hi>ncse</hi> is encoded into
                    the way each issue is structured. When we corrected the segmentation of each
                    issue, we identified which items – usually in this case a headline – signalled
                    the beginning of a department. These then appeared in the Table of Components,
                    and all the items that followed it were associated with that department. This
                    structure was vital in order to allow us to populate the edition with metadata
                    [internal link].</p></div>
                
                <div id="seg"><head>Segmentation Policies</head>
                <p>Segmentation policies were documents designed to guide either a non-expert to
                    decide on how to distinguish between items and then to decide on which items
                    constituted a division between one department and the next. For each publication
                    we wrote an overall description that laid out rules, and then prepared a
                    selection of marked-up pdf documents to show how rules should be applied.
                    Examples of our segmentation policies can be downloaded here:</p>
                
                    <div><head>Monthly Repository:</head>
                <list type="bulleted">
                    <item>
                        <p>Monthly Repository Segmentation Guidelines [link to
                            07.03.07_mr_segmentation_policy.pdf and rename
                            ‘mr_segmentation_policy.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>2 July 1809 (pdf document) [link to 041-MRP-1809-07-02-001-SINGLE.PDF and
                            rename ‘mr_segmentation_1809.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>31 December 1826 (pdf document) [link to
                            041-MRP-1826-12-31-001-SINGLE.PDF and rename
                        ‘mr_segmentation_1826.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                </list></div>
                
                    <div><head>Northern Star:</head>
                <list type="bulleted">
                    <item>
                        <p>Northern Star Segmentation Guidelines [link to
                            07.01.19_ns_segmentation_policy.pdf and rename
                            ‘ns_segmentation_policy.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>26 Sepetember 1840 (pdf document) [link to
                            041-NSS-1840-09-26-001-SINGLE.PDF and rename
                        ‘ns_segmentation_1840.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>29 December 1845 (pdf document) [link to
                            041-NSS-1845-12-29-001-SINGLE.PDF and rename
                        ‘ns_segmentation_1845.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>9 June 1849 (pdf document) [link to 041-NSS-1849-06-09-001-SINGLE.PDF and
                            rename ‘ns_segmentation_1849.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>26 June 1852 (pdf document) [link to 041-NSS-1852-06-26-001-SINGLE.PDF
                            and rename]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>25 September 1852 (pdf document) [link to
                            041-NSS-1852-09-25-001-SINGLE.PDF and rename]</p>
                    </item>
                </list></div>
                
                    <div><head>Leader:</head>
                <list type="bulleted">
                    <item>
                        <p>Leader Segmentation Guidelines [link to ldr_segmentation_guide.pdf]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>4 May 1850 (pdf document) [link to ldr_segmentation2.pdf and rename
                            ‘ldr_segmentation_1850.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>9 October 1858 (pdf document) [link to ldr_segmentation1.pdf and rename
                            ‘ldr_segmentation_1858.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                </list></div>
                
                    <div><head>English Womans' Journal:</head>
                <list type="bulleted">
                    <item>
                        <p>English Womans' Journal Segmentation Guidelines [link to
                            07.04.02_ewj_segmentation_policy.pdf and rename
                            ‘ewj_segmentation_policy.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>1 July 1861 (pdf document) [link to 041-EWJ-1861-07-01-001-SINGLE.PDF and
                            rename ‘ewj_segmentation_1861.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                </list></div>
                
                    <div><head>Tomahawk:</head>
                <list type="bulleted">
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <title>Tomahawk</title> Segmentation Guidelines [link to
                            07.02.17_th_segmentation_policy.pdf and rename
                            ‘thk_segmentation_policy.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>10 May 1867 (pdf document) [link to 041-TTW-1867-05-10-001-SINGLE.PDF and
                            rename ‘thk_segmentation_1867.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Index 1868 (pdf document) [link to 041-TTW-1868-01-01-001-SINGLE.PDF and
                            rename ‘thk_segmentation_index.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Almanack 1869 (pdf document) [link to 041-TTW-1869-01-01-001-SINGLE.PDF
                            and rename ‘thk_segmentation_almanack.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>20 August 1870 (pdf document) [link to 041-TTW-1870-08-20-001-SINGLE.PDF
                            and rename ‘thk_segmentaion_1870.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                </list></div>
                
                    <div><head>Publishers' Circular:</head>
                <list type="bulleted">
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <title>Publishers' Circular</title> Segmenation Guidelines [link to
                            pc_segmentation_guide.pdf and rename ‘pc_segmentation_policy.pdf’]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>15 April 1887 [link to pc_segmentation_1887.pdf]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>English Catalogue of Books, 1887 [link to pc_segmentation_engcat.pdf]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>6 December 1888 (Christmas Number) [link to
                        pc_segmentation_xmas1888.pdf]</p>
                    </item>
                </list></div></div>
           
                <div id="vol"><head>Volumes</head>
                <p>Although we were committed to recording the histories of our titles up to the
                    point at which we digitized them, we were also conscious that we had to make
                    editorial interventions in order to present the material in a way that would
                    make sense to users. Our proposed structure of the edition [internal link] set
                    out how each element in the hierarchy related to all the others, but the actual
                    condition of the hard copy did not always fall neatly into the categories that
                    we set out. This was particularly the case with the internal arrangement of
                    content within volumes. </p>
                <p>Even though nearly all the hard copy from which we sourced <hi>ncse </hi>was in
                    volume form, these bound volumes were not consistent in terms of their contents
                    or appearance. Often the volumes had been bound in different ways according to
                    individual binders – both within the same institution and when compared between
                    insitutions – and binding practices altered with the content over time. Although
                    we could leave the content in the condition in which we found it, thus
                    preserving the history of the particular bound volume’s production and
                    preservation, our decision to merge runs from different sources meant we were
                    already committed to radically altering the ‘found’ state of large parts of the
                    edition. For instance, our run of <title>Tomahawk </title>consists of two separate
                    runs: one stored by the British Library at St Pancras and one by the British
                    Library at Colindale. While the run at St Pancras is more complete in terms of
                    issues than the one at Colindale, it lacks all of the advertising wrappers; the
                    run at Colindale is not as complete as that at St Pancras, but it has the
                    advertising wrappers and a few issues missing from the St Pancras run. By
                    merging the two runs we were committed to reconstructing the form of the volume,
                    and so had to come up with a model of what a volume might be. We adopted the
                    following basic model:</p>
                <p>Front matter </p>
                <p>Issues</p>
                <p>End matter</p>
                <p>Front matter contains things like prefaces, volume title pages, volume tables of
                    contents, or any illustrative material that was intended to be bound at the
                    beginning of a volume. Issues contain the run of issues defined by the number
                    that each issuecarries on its front page. End matter contains the indices that
                    it was common practice for publishers to provide for the end of a volume.</p>
                <p>As you may notice, the way we have implemented this model varies from title to
                    title. It was common for editors to issue, sometimes at extra cost, the textual
                    apparatus (prefaces, indices, volume title pages) for collecting single issues
                    into bound volumes. As these components often (but not always) survive within
                    the bound volumes, we could be guided in designing our model of a volume by the
                    way in which they were conceived by the titles themselves. Where possible, this
                    is what we’ve done: for instance, we’ve placed the supplements to the
                        <title>Monthly Repository</title> before the end matter as they are indexed
                    within the index that it contains. The <title>Northern Star</title>, although
                    labelling its issues with issue numbers and volume numbers, did not issue
                    indices or volume title pages. As a result, neither front matter nor end matter
                    appears in the folder tree for volumes of the <title>Northern Star</title>.</p>
                <p>The decision to reorder content into consistent volumes particularly concerned
                    two titles: <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>and <title>Tomahawk</title>. The
                    editors of the <title>Publishers’ Circular </title>tended to issue a volume title
                    page in the advertising section of one of the issues published in January for
                    the volume that ended the previous December. In the run of <title>Publishers’
                        Circular </title>at the British Library, some of these volume title pages had
                    been removed from the advertising sections and bound at the beginning of the
                    previous volume, but some had not. In addition, the positions to which title
                    pages were moved were not always consistent: the volume title page for 1882, for
                    instance, was bound as the third page of the <title>English Catalogue of
                    Books</title>, rather than placed at the front of the volume as a whole.By moving the volume title page so that it always appears as front
                    matter at the start of a volume we might elide the histories of the specific
                    bound volumes with which we worked, but we have provided a consistent resource
                    that is based upon the printed intentions of its producers. The same is true of
                        <title>Tomahawk</title>. <title>Tomahawk</title> published two volumes each
                    year, one in January and one in July. However, in December they also published
                    an almanack that looked forward to the coming year. Although these were separate
                    publications (they were a penny more expensive than regular issues), the run in
                    the British Library has them bound in with the rest of <title>Tomahawk</title>.
                    However, sometimes they have been bound in variously, at the beginning of the
                    January volume and at the beginning of the July volume. Again, our decision to
                    move the almanacks so that they appear at the beginning of the January volume of
                    the year to which they apply masks the history of the particular hard copy with
                    which we are dealing, but does make this content appear in a consistent
                    position, easily located within the context of the rest of the run.</p></div>
               
        
                <div id="iss"><head>Division of content into issues</head>
                <p>The decision to work with an abstract model of the constituents of a volume meant
                    that it was necessary to separate front and end matter from the issues
                    themselves. Olive Software work with pdf documents that correspond to individual
                    documents within their system. Each issue is a single pdf document, and it is
                    the pdfs that are segmented in order to delineate and structure their contents.
                    Just as every issue is therefore a single pdf document, so too are pieces of
                    front matter, indices, or supplements. Our policy with this material was to use
                    a separate pdf document for every component that was issued separately. As such,
                    we have made each individual supplement a separate issue, but have usually kept
                    all front matter (i.e. titlepages and prefaces) as a single issue.</p></div>
               
               <div id="wra"> <head>Wrappers</head>
                <p>Although wrappers are notoriously hard to find in bound volumes of periodicals,
                    we have quite a few wrappers for two of our six titles: <title>Publishers’
                        Circular </title>and<title> Tomahawk</title>. The <title>Leader </title>also
                    reorganises its advertising section as a wrapper in 1858, allowing it to be
                    stripped off prior to binding should the reader choose to do so. For further
                    information about wrappers, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_5">here</xref>.</p>
                <p>We were committed to including wrappers in <hi rend="bold">ncse </hi>but had to
                    devise a way in which content in wrappers could be distinguished from that from
                    within issues. As all content in <hi>ncse</hi> is taken from pdf documents that
                    correspond to whole issues, there was no distinction between wrappers and issues
                    at this level [internal link]. We structured content within issues with
                    segmentation that distinguished between items and then grouped items into
                    departments [internal link]. By inserting a metadata field called ‘Bibliographic
                    location’ with two values, ‘number contents’ and ‘wrapper’, it was possible to
                    mark up items with their location on the wrapper or in the issue. This still
                    left us with a potential problem as this was a metadata field that needed to be
                    applied to all the items in the edition. However, using a combination of
                    segmentation and metadata, we devised a way to avoid having to enter this
                    information manually to all the content. First of all we marked all content as
                    ‘number contents’ and then we segmented wrappers so that we could easily change
                    this value later. The way we did this was to segment wrappers so that the first
                    item on a wrapper marked a new department. By ensuring that the first item in an
                    issue marked the next department, it was possible to label the first item on a
                    wrapper as ‘wrapper’ and have that information inherited to all the other items
                    on the wrapper up to the department that marked the beginning of the number. For
                    more information on metadata, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_11">here</xref>.</p>
                </div><div id="adv">
                <head>Advertisements</head>
                <p>Advertisements are a crucial part of serial texts, providing valuable income
                    streams that might complement money raised by direct sale and subscription. Not
                    only this, but they have considerable historical value as often they are the one
                    means of gauging the readership of a particular title, or establishing how much
                    things actually cost. Advertisements were also appealing to nineteenth-century
                    readers: they often provided the most visually striking pages in an issue and it
                    might also be argued that they provided an important news function. As such, we
                    ensured that advertisements were distinguished from other items. Due to the size
                    of the edition, we could not mark up all advertisements by hand. Instead, we
                    used Olive’s segmentation process to make a first attempt at identifying
                    advertisements, and then corrected this by hand during segmentation. </p>
                <p>Although this strategy succeeded in demarcating all the advertisements, making
                    them searchable through the Olvie interface, it restricted their functionality.
                    As advertisements often contain images we were keen that they interacted with
                    our image metadata schema. However, Olive’s way of marking up content meant that
                    items had to be either ‘Image’, ‘Article’ or ‘Advertisement’. Our solution was
                    to retain the Olive distinctions between content at item level, but use our own
                    metadata to permit one type of content to appear in a search for another. This
                    means that although an advertisement is not recognized as an image in the Olive
                    system, it will still be returned through an image metadata search.</p></div>
                <div id="ima"><head>Images</head>
                <p>Images, like advertisements [internal link], are demarcated as a one of three
                    types of content (articles is the third) by Olive during segmentation. However,
                    images might occur within articles and, if this is the case, this relationship
                    should be preserved. Olive’s segmentation tool permits images to be embedded
                    within articles: what this means for <hi>ncse </hi>is that it is possible for an
                    image to be embedded into an item, allowing users to either view the item as a
                    whole (with the image within it) in the component viewer, or to simply view the
                    image.</p>
                <p>For information on how we labelled images with image metadata, click <xref type="internal" from="p5_11">here</xref> to view the schema, and here [link to 05_04_visual] for how
                    we applied it.</p></div>
               
              <div id="fro">  <head>Front and end matter</head>
                <p>See Division of content into <ref n="iss">issues</ref> [internal link] above.</p></div>
              
            </div>
        </body>













    </text>
</TEI.2>
