<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p6">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of the project</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>


        <body>
            <div><p>This section of the site provides details about the history of <hi rend="bold"
                >ncse</hi> from the commencement of the project grant in January 2005 to the launch
                in May 2008.</p>
            <list type="bulleted">
                <item><xref type="internal" from="p6_1">Project team</xref></item>
                <item>
                    <xref type="internal" from="p6_2">Publications</xref>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <xref type="internal" from="p6_3">Conferences</xref>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <xref type="internal" from="p6_6"><hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> symposia</xref>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <xref type="internal" from="p6_5">Publicity</xref>
                </item>
            </list>
            <p>Below is a brief account of the history of the project. We will provide a fuller,
                more reflective account of its history after the launch.</p>

            <div>
                <head>January to June 2005</head>
                <p>This early period of the project was taken up with administrative tasks such as
                    setting up the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> office at Birkbeck College, arranging
                    facilities at the British Library, setting up the project website, and
                    completing the Memorandum of Understanding between the project and the British
                    Library. The research team completed snapshots of the six titles, filling in
                    templates (click here to download a sample <xref type="redist"
                        from="pdf/template.pdf">template</xref> [PDF file]) to familiarize ourselves
                    with the titles, establish what was missing, and begin to identify relevant
                    categories of data. After these had been completed, the team began a more
                    thorough process of page turning the hard copy. On the basis of the snapshots
                    and page turning, the British Library began to produce microfilm and the team
                    approached other institutions to supplement its holdings.</p>
                <p>The research team began to create profiles for each of the pages, marking up
                    photocopies of pages to show which portions should be recognized and their
                    relationship to each other. We also began to work on <xref type="internal"
                        from="p5_10">concept mapping</xref> and the creation of advanced <xref
                        type="internal" from="p5_11">metadata categories</xref>.</p>
                <p>The team were successful in obtaining a place and funding for the NINES Summer
                    Workshop, and began to put together the plans for the first of the <hi
                        rend="bold">ncse</hi> symposia. They presented a paper for the Centre for
                    Nineteenth-Century Studies at Birkbeck College.</p>
                <p> At the end of June we met with representatives from Olive Software in London for
                    the first time, allowing both parties to gain a sense of the technological
                    requirements of the project.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>June to December 2005</head>
                <p>A follow-up visit to Olive Software in Israel by Harold Short gave the project
                    team a better sense of the level of metadata and annotation that it would be
                    possible to achieve. We reviewed the page turning exercise and used it to do
                    some calculations to establish more precisely the size of the edition. Our
                    estimate was that the edition, discounting any multiple editions, would total
                    67,000pp. When multiple editions were included, we estimated that <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> would contain 110,000pp.</p>
                <p>We began to see the first pilots from Olive Software and entered into
                    negotiations about the level of work that they could do on a project of this
                    size. Their responses, and our own thoughts about including multiple editions,
                    prompted us to devise a two-tier model we called the <xref type="internal" from="p5_9">'core'</xref>.</p>
                <p>The research team continued to work on advanced metadata, compiling lists of data
                    that might serve as authority lists. Work also continued on concept mapping, but
                    was put on hold while we investigated alternative ways of implementing it in
                    light of the size of the edition.</p>
                <p>We received a set of tiff images from Olive Software created from the microfilm
                    we had sent them from the British Library. The research team began to review
                    these page images to ascertain their completeness and quality. Production of
                    microfilm continued, particularly for portions of the edition not held by the
                    British Library.</p>
                <p>Plans continued to develop for the first <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> symposia, to be held the
                    following February. The members of the research team presented papers at various
                    conferences and seminars and published a paper in <xref type="external" url="http://www.19.bbk.ac.uk/"><title>19</title></xref>, a new e-journal set up by the Centre for
                    Nineteenth-Century Studies at Birkbeck College. The research team also moved
                    offices within Birkbeck and relaunched the website.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>January to June 2006</head>
                <p>On reviewing the tiffs so far we found that many of the multiple editions had not
                    been filmed. With the agreement of Olive and the British Library, the project
                    team arranged for the missing content to be filmed and then incorporated with
                    the digital material that had already been produced. The team then continued
                    checking the tiffs, revising the estimate of the total number of pages
                    (including multiples) to 100,000pp</p>
                <p> After presenting the core at the first <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> symposium, the project team
                    and Olive Software began investigating the extent to which the entire 100,000pp
                    edition could be segmented. Working with pilots produced by Olive Software, it
                    was agreed that we would abandon the core model and segment the whole edition to
                    item level, reconstituting the hierarchy between items and departments through
                    metadata.</p>
                <p>The team then stepped-up work on the metadata schema, taking advice from the Arts
                    and Humanities Data Service and NINES. The team also began negotiating with the
                    National Portrait Gallery to obtain copies of the <title>Northern Star</title>
                    portraits.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>July to December 2006</head>
                <p>A workflow schedule and procedure for segmentation was agreed between the project
                    team and Olive Software. This involved the team producing segmentation profiles
                    that provided rule-sets for determining departments in each title, and then
                    Olive producing a pilot showing how effectively these could be applied. Work was
                    carried out on a title-by-title basis, beginning with the <title>Leader</title> in
                    September. At this stage we were still using the tiff images as a corpus of
                    content, with tiff numbers as a reference guide to content. However, we found
                    that these tiff images had already been converted into pdfs (that corresponded
                    with issues) and there was no way of mapping tiff number to pdf pages. As the
                    pdfs were to become the content of the resource, we began to check them for
                    accuracy.</p>
                <p>The team met with Olive in October – a meeting that allowed the various parties
                    to establish a good working relationship and clarify certain areas of the
                    project. This was followed up through the instigation of weekly status calls
                    between the postdoctoral research assistants and the project manager at Olive.
                    These, and the relationship they fostered, helped us work through a number of
                    problems that arose as we attempted to process the material. Work also continued
                    on the metadata: with Olive we refined the bibliographic terms; and with Centre
                    for Computing in the Humanities (CCH) at King’s we began research into text
                    mining and concordances. The project team also worked more closely with Olive’s
                    extant applications, and began to draft a specification for our own application. </p>
                <p>The team gave a range of conference papers over the summer and began to plan the
                    next <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> symposium, this time to be held at CCH in February 2007.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>January to June 2007</head>
                <p>The team continued to work closely with Olive Software, checking pdf files,
                    providing profiles, and evaluating the resulting pilots. This was complex,
                    time-consuming work, involving a great deal of communication between the team
                    and Olive. As part of this work, the team received training on Olive’s tools,
                    allowing correction of processed material and addition of metadata to be carried
                    out in London. The burden of correcting the errors in the content was also
                    redistributed in order to speed things up, with more of the correction
                    undertaken in London. With this in mind, the project began to recruit
                    postgraduate editorial assistants. For the remainder of the project our workflow
                    was:</p>
                <p>Check pdfs &gt; send to Olive &gt; create segmentation profile for a
                    title &gt; review sample of segmentation &gt; run segmentation on all
                    pdfs for a title &gt; send segmented pdfs to <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>
                    &gt; correct segmentation &gt; send segmented pdfs to Olive &gt;
                    output to produce xml &gt; send outputted material to <hi rend="bold"
                    >ncse</hi> to be uploaded into application &gt; review</p>
                <p>The second symposium took place in February, and we took the opportunity to do
                    some initial research into what our users thought about the project. These
                    results were useful in developing the specification for our application, and a
                    more advanced user testing session was planned for September. The team continued
                    to give papers and produced a chapter for an edited collection published in
                    2008. Work began to plan the launch in May 2008.</p>
                <p>The research team and the British Library worked to get new colour digital images
                    of some of the badly reproduced <title>Tomahawk </title>images. These were
                    inserted into the workflow when we began producing the segmentation profile for
                        <title>Tomahawk</title>.</p>
                <p>In May we saw the first mock-ups of Olive’s new Viewpoint application, with
                    customization for <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>. This was an exciting moment,
                    especially as the processing picked up momentum. The team continued to work on
                    advanced metadata, sourcing lists and producing training data for text
                mining.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>July to December 2007</head>
                <p>This was the last portion of the project on which the two postdoctoral research
                    assistants were formally employed. The processing of the material occupied most
                    of the time but with the help of the editorial assistants to correct the
                    original pdfs we made good progress on the remaining titles. In September
                    representatives from Olive Software came to London to provide further training
                    and discuss some of the details arising from processing and the implementation
                    of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> content in their software. Shortly after the visit
                    the project received the first version of Viewpoint, allowing content to be seen
                    in the application for the first time. We invited members of the International
                    Advisory Board and other interested parties to attend a user testing session
                    based upon this application. The results were compiled and used to guide our
                    work with Olive on customizing the application so that it matched both project
                    requirements and the expectations of users.</p>
                <p>The metadata schema was finalized and the fields supplied to Olive who
                    implemented them in Viewpoint and their Content Administrator. The research team
                    worked closely with CCH to develop the image metadata schema and the way in
                    which it could be implemented in the edition. Work also advanced on the various
                    advanced metadata fields. Training data was prepared for text mining,
                    experiments were carried out for named entity extraction, and the team
                    investigated various subject classification schemes and thesauruses.</p>
                <p>By December the majority of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> was either on servers in London and
                    working within the Olive interface, or due to be delivered soon. A visit to
                    Olive by representatives of the project from CCH provided a better understanding
                    of how the Olive components could be integrated with the interface to be built
                    by the team. The full-time researcher left the project at this point, and
                    although ncse had obtained an extension and was due to continue until June 2008,
                    it was necessary to move the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> office from Birkbeck and take up
                    residence at CCH. The team now was reconfigured, with the part-time researcher
                    working closely with the Editorial Assistants, Olive, CCH and other members of
                    the Research team. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>January to May 2008</head>
                <p>From January the Editorial Assistants added bibliographic and image metadata to
                    the content as it was delivered from Olive. While this was being completed the
                    team worked closely with Olive checking the resource and correcting any problems
                    with either the content or the way it functioned. Work began on the structural
                    design of the overall resource, particularly the ways in which the advanced
                    metadata would be implemented and the Olive resource combined with the tools
                    designed by CCH. Once the content was finalized and the metadata completed in
                    April, the data was extracted from the edition and used to construct both the
                    advanced browsing and search mechanisms, as well as the way results were
                    returned. </p>
                <p>As the launch drew closer the team worked hard to provide contextual material for
                    the site while checking the functionality of the resource as a whole.</p>
            </div></div>
        </body>













    </text>
</TEI.2>
