<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "../../../dtd/tei/cch_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="p6_1">
    <teiHeader status="new" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>ncse Team</title>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                      <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                  </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2008-03-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EL</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created file</item>
            </change>


        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>


        <body>
            <p>The Nineteenth-Century Serials Edition was a collaboration between Birkbeck,
                University of London , King’s College London (Centre for Computing in the Humanities
                and the Department of English), the British Library and Olive Software, all of whom
                were named partners in the AHRC project. Over the funded period of the project a
                number of people worked on it from these institutions. In the latter stages of the
                project, we also employed a team of editorial assistants who helped with the digital
                editing of the resource. This page provides brief details about everyone who
                contributed to the project.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Birkbeck, University of London </head>
                <div>
                    <head>Associate Director</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">Dr Isobel Armstrong</hi>, Emeritus Professor of English at
                        Birkbeck, University of London.</p>
                    <p>Isobel was one of the initiators of the project. She has recently published a
                        monograph entitled <emph>Victorian Glassworlds: Glass Culture and the
                            Imagination, 1830-1880 </emph>published by Oxford University Press. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Project Director </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">Dr Laurel Brake</hi>, Senior Research Fellow, Birkbeck,
                        University of London and Emeritus Professor of Literature and Print Culture.</p>
                    <p>Laurel was the Project Director of <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>. She is also
                        co-editor of the <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Nineteenth-Century Journalism</hi> and has
                        published widely on nineteenth-century print culture.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Postdoctoral Researcher </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">Dr Jim Mussell</hi>, Lecturer in English at the University
                        of Birmingham.</p>
                    <p>Jim was the part-time postdoctoral researcher on <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi>
                        until December 2007, and saw it through its final development January-May
                        2008. He is the author of <emph>Science, Time and Space in the Late
                            Nineteenth-Century Periodical Press</emph>, published by Ashgate in
                        2007. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Postdoctoral Researcher </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">Dr Suzanne Paylor.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                        </hi>Suzanne worked on the project as the full-time postdoctoral
                        researcher until December 2007.  She has a background in history of science,
                        print culture and digital humanties. She convenes a postgraduate
                        'Introduction to Digital Humanities' course at Birkbeck, University of London and
                        provides consultancy to various e-learning, database and digitisation based
                        projects in academia and the public sector . </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>King’s College London </head>
                <div><head>Centre for Computing in the Humanities (CCH)</head><div>
                    <head>Technical Research Directors</head>
                    <list>
                        <item>Harold Short</item>
                        <item>Marylin Deegan</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Current Project Team</head>
                    <list>
                        <item>Tamara Lopez (project co-ordinator and lead analyst, system
                            architecture)</item>
                        <item>Gerhard Brey (lead analyst, text mining)</item>
                        <item>Simon Tanner (consultancy and QA on digitisation)</item>
                        <item>José Miguel Vieira (lead analyst, web application development)</item>
                        <item>Zaneta Au (web application development)</item>
                        <item>Damien Doherty (Visual design) [<xref type="external"
                                url="http://www.damiendoherty.com"
                            >http://www.damiendoherty.com</xref>] </item>
                        <item>Paul Vetch (lead analyst, system integration and web application
                            development)</item>

                        <item>Eleonora Litta Modignani Picozzi (editorial and web support)</item>



                        <item>Richard Palmer (server setup)</item>

                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Also:</head>
                    <list>
                        <item>Paul Spence (consultancy on web publication)</item>
                        <item>Arianna Ciula (web development and support)</item>
                        <item>Patrick Tschorn (Java development interface to text mining program
                            packages, consultancy in computational linguistics)</item>

                        <item>Alexandros Skaliotis (Java development, interface to text mining
                            program packages)</item>

                        <item> Abu Zafer M Dayem Ullah (Java development, interface to text mining
                            program packages)</item>

                        <item> Dr Manolis Christodoulakis (Development and implementation of OCR
                            correction algorithms)</item>
                    </list>
                </div></div>
                <div>
                    <head>Department of English</head>

                    <div>
                        <head>Associate Director</head>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Dr Mark Turner</hi>, Reader in English at King’s College
                            London.</p>
                        <p>Mark worked closely on <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> from its inception. He
                            is Reader in English Literature and has published widely on
                            nineteenth-century print culture and queer studies.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>British Library</head>

                <div>
                    <head>Associate Director</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold">Ed King</hi>, Head of Newspapers at the British Library.</p>
                    <p>Ed has been involved closely with <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> from its outset.
                        He is Head of Newspapers at the British Library and has published on
                        nineteenth-century print culture. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Olive Software</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Chezkie Kasnett</hi>, Project Manager for Olive Software </p>
                <p>Chezkie worked closely on the Olive components of <hi rend="bold">ncse </hi>from
                    2007, and very closely with the<hi rend="bold"> ncse </hi>team in the closing
                    stages of the project</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Uri Ben Tvzi</hi>, Project Manager for Olive Software.</p>
                <p>Uri was Olive’s representative for the <hi rend="bold">ncse</hi> work in 2006. </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Irit Reznikov</hi>, Project Manager for Olive Software.</p>
                <p>Irit was Olive’s representative at the beginning of the project, from January
                    2005 to 2006.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Editorial Assistants</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Dr Chrissie Bradstreet.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Chrisse was an editorial assistant from June to July 2007. Chrissie currently
                    works at the Watts Gallery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Clara Brennan</hi>, postgraduate student, Kingston University</p>
                <p>Clara was an editorial assistant from September 2007 until the project launch in
                    May 2008. She is a playwright and is currently working on a PhD on Theatre and
                    Human Rights at Kingston University.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Dr Greta Depledge.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Greta was an editorial assistant from July to November 2007. She has recently
                    completed a PhD at Birkbeck, University of London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Rob Maidens</hi>, postgraduate student in English, Birkbeck
                    College</p>
                <p>Rob was an editorial assistant from May 2007 until the project launch in May
                    2008. He is working on a PhD in the mid nineteenth-century novel at Birkbeck
                    College.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Brian Murray</hi>, postgraduate student in English, King’s
                    College London</p>
                <p>Brian was an editorial assistant from September 2007 until the project launch in
                    May 2008. He is working on a PhD on the journalist, author and explorer Henry
                    Morton Stanley.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Jason Narlock</hi>, postgraduate student in English, King’s
                    College London</p>
                <p>Jason was an editorial assistant from September 2007 until March 2008. He is
                    currently writing a PhD at King’s College London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Indra Pillay</hi>,<hi rend="bold"> </hi>postgraduate student in
                    English, King’s College London</p>
                <p>Indra was an editorial assistant from December 2007 until the project launch in
                    May 2008. She is currently writing an MPhil in English at King’s College London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Dr Matthew Taunton. </hi>
                </p>
                <p>Matthew Taunton was an editorial assistant April-May 2007. He recently completed
                    a PhD at the London Consortium.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Faye Thompson</hi>, postgraduate, MA in History of the Book,
                    Institute of English Studies, University of London</p>
                <p>Faye Thompson supervised the work of the Editorial Assistants on <hi rend="bold"
                        >ncse</hi>. She worked on the project from June 2007 until the project
                    launch in May 2008.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Dr Victoria Williams.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Victoria was an editorial assistant from September 2007 until the project launch
                    in May 2008. Her doctorate investigated fairytales in nineteenth-century
                    literature, art and film.</p>
            </div>
        </body>














    </text>
</TEI.2>
